<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.masshist.org/publications/pub/schema/djqa-prep-2016.rng" type="xml"?>
        <?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="DJQA-authorViewMaybe.css"?>
<div type="month" volume="30" startingOnPage="405">
    <bibl n="metadata">
        <date from="1818-10-01" to="1818-10-31"/>
    </bibl>
        <!-- D/JQA/30.1813 -->
        <!-- October 1818 -->
            
				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-01">
					<head>1 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-01"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Roads</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
					    <dateline type="heading">October 1818</dateline>
					    <p><dateline>1. VI:</dateline> Thursday. Seventh and last sitting to <persRef ref="stuart-gilbert">Stewart</persRef>. He at first told me he should
                want only four sittings, from an hour and a half to two hours each. I sat this
                Morning before Breakfast, and he finished the head. From Breakfast time till one
                O’clock there was a continual succession of visitors, among whom were <persRef ref="austin-benjamin">B. Austin</persRef>, <persRef ref="brazier-john">J.
                    Brazier</persRef>, <persRef ref="waters-unknown">J. Waters</persRef>, <persRef ref="degrand-peter">De Grand</persRef>, <persRef ref="orne-unknown">Orne</persRef>, and a <persRef ref="unknown7">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persRef><space>    </space>a ropemaker who
                complained of ill-usage from the Commissioners of the Navy— We took a collation at
                12. O’Clock, and our Son <persRef ref="adams-charles2">Charles</persRef> came and took leave of us. <persRef ref="adams-john2">John</persRef> came to the door,
                but to avoid a parting went away without seeing us. At one O’Clock the Mail-Stage
                came and took us up and between eight and nine in the Evening we arrived at
                Worcester, now less than forty miles from Boston, by the turnpike over which we
                travelled. By the former road it was 48. We had several fellow passengers from
                Boston, among whom was <persRef ref="baxter-joseph">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Jos. Baxter jun<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi></persRef>
                who was going to Alexandria, and who proceeded from Worcester in the Stage this
                Evening; a younger <persRef ref="bigelow-unknown">son</persRef> of <persRef ref="bigelow-timothy">T. Bigelow</persRef> the Speaker of the Massachusetts House of
					        Representatives, and a young man named <persRef ref="seaver-unknown">Seaver</persRef> in whom I recognized a strong likeness
					        of my Classmate <persRef ref="seaver-john">John Seaver</persRef>, and whom I took for a Son of his brother <persRef ref="seaver-william">William
                Seaver</persRef>. They were only coming to Worcester, where Seaver’s father resided— We lodge
					        at <persRef ref="sikes-rueben">Sikes’s</persRef> tavern— We saw the Moon, just after Sunset, this being only its second
                day.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-02">
					<head>2 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-02"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
					    <note type="subject">Roads</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
						<p><dateline>2. VI:</dateline> Made up a packet of papers and despatches belonging to the Department of
						    State, which I enclosed to <persRef ref="brent-daniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> D. Brent</persRef> and left at the Post
						    Office. <persRef ref="lincoln-levi">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Levi Lincoln</persRef> formerly Attorney-General of the United
                States, and afterwards Lieutenant-Governor of Massachusetts came and paid us a
                visit, and offered us many civilities. He resides upon his farm here, entirely
                retired from public life; and has been some years nearly blind— Was couched for
                Cataracts in both eyes, by which he lost altogether the sight of one, but recovered
                that of the other— He told me again that he had been directed to the profession of
                the Law, by hearing while he was at College, my <persRef ref="adams-john">father</persRef> argue a Cause at Boston. The
                Stage which left Boston at two O’Clock this Morning reached Worcester at ten, and we
                took passage in it— we dined at Brookfield; and after being detained nearly an hour
                at Belchertown, arrived at half past nine in the Evening at <persRef ref="lyman-unknown">Lyman’s</persRef> tavern
                Northampton. The Stage and horses at Belchertown has been used by militia-Officers
                for a training day six Miles off, and had not returned when we came to the Stage
                <pb type="ms" n="406"/>house, which was the occasion of our being delayed. The distance from
                Worcester to Northampton is or was fifty two Miles. We had only one fellow-traveller
                in the Stage— He had come with it from Boston this Morning and left it at
                Northampton; apparently much overcome all day with fatigue— The whole road is
                mountainous, and rocky, but the roads as good as in such countries they can be.
                Great part of it is covered with wood—Oak, Birch, and Chestnut. The cleared land
                apparently not fertile; generally pasturage, with some poor, thin looking Indian
                Corn. very few settlements on the road, and no symptoms of increasing population. We
                lodge at Lyman’s.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-03">
					<head>3 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-03"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">African Americans</note>
					    <note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
					    <note type="subject">Roads</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
						<p><dateline>3. IV:</dateline> The usual hour of the Stage’s starting from Northampton is two o’clock in the
                morning, but our driver who had been overplied at yesterday’s training overslept
                himself this morning, and the clock struck four as we left the house. We saw of
                course nothing of Northampton— It sprinkled with rain when we entered the Stage, and
                continued to rain in a succession of heavy showers till noon when the sky cleared
                up, and the Evening was fair. On leaving Northampton we had the Stage to ourselves,
                but took in passengers at several places and arrived at Albany, at half past eight
                this Evening with a full carriage— <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef> was extremely ill,
                all the morning; and I thought we should have been under the necessity of stopping
                at some house on the road, and waiting for the next Stage which will not pass
                through till Tuesday— We breakfasted at Chesterfield— At Peru the next Stage M<hi
                    rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams was most ill— at Pittsfield I procured a vial of
                landanum of which she took 25 drops, and was much relieved. It is surely the
                Nepenthe of the wife of Thone. About nine miles beyond Pittsfield, we entered the
                State of New-York, at the village of Lebanon where there are hot Springs, frequented
                by valetudinarians— This circumstance has given it and the country around it a more
                flourishing appearance than its vicinity within the State of Massachusetts can
                boast. We dined at Nassau about nine miles within the New York line but owing to the
                tardiness of our morning driver, we were belated for dinner till five in the
                afternoon— Our road was still more mountainous than yesterday, and we walked up part
                of Snake hill, which is upwards of two Miles long. The boundary between the two
                States is strongly marked in the difference between the Styles of building of their
                dwelling houses— Those of New-York generally cover more ground and are lower, having
                but one Story, while those of Massachusetts have two, at least in front—with a long
                sloping roof in the rear. The New-York houses have also a sheltered porch or viranda
                extending along the whole front and sometimes also on the sides, indicating the
                approach to a warmer climate. Among the Passengers whom we took in at Pittsfield was
                a young man whose name we found was <persRef ref="larned-unknown">Larned</persRef>, and that he was going to New-Orleans— I
                took him for a trading-person, but M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams with more sagacity
                concluded from his dress, and deportment, and from his reproving a Black man whom he
                heard swearing, that he was a clergyman. At his recommendation we came to the
                Mansion House Hotel, instead of the Eagle tavern to which we were at first
                driven.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-04">
					<head>4 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-04"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Adams Family Relations</note>
					    <note type="subject">Religion</note>
					    <note type="subject">Steam Power</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
						<p><dateline>4. VI:</dateline> I was writing this morning in the parlour which had been given to us, when a
                young woman came in to the room with a stout boy three years old by the hand— I did
                not know her, until she enquired if I was M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Adams, and on my
                answering that I was, she immediately said “I am your Niece,” and I recognized my
                brother <persRef ref="adams-charles">Charles’s</persRef> second daughter <persRef ref="johnson-abigail">Abigail</persRef> now the wife of <persRef ref="johnson-alexander">Alex<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                B. Johnson</persRef> of Utica in this State of New-York. The boy was her son. They came in
						    last Evening from Utica, and are now going to pay a visit to <persRef ref="adams-john;adams-abigail">my Parents</persRef> at Quincy.
						    The boy is named <persRef ref="johnson-john">John Adams</persRef> after my father. I soon became acquainted with M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Johnson, and we went together to Church— After some enquiries
						    for the principal preachers of the place, <persRef ref="cummings-unknown">Cummings</persRef>, <persRef ref="stansbury-unknown">Stansbury</persRef> and <persRef ref="chester-unknown">Chester</persRef>, neither
                of whom officiated, we went in the Morning to the first, and in the afternoon to the
                second Dutch Church; so called from their having been originally dutch; but the
                services are now all in English. We were recommended in the morning to the first
                dutch Church to hear its pastor <persRef ref="dewitt-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> De Witt</persRef>, by a worthy Citizen
                whom we met in the street and who assured us that M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> de Witt was
						    a pupil of <persRef ref="mason-unknown">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Mason’s</persRef> of New-York, and that he was the greatest
                preacher in Albany. But it was not M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> de Witt whom we heard; it
						    was <persRef ref="larned-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Larned</persRef>, the young man who had travelled with us yesterday
                in the Stage from Pittsfield— His Sermon was upon the atonement, according to the
                doctrines usually denominated calvinistic. He preached without notes, and in a style
                of eloquence with which I was much gratified— His manner was fervent, yet chaste—
                His delivery animated, without affectation, his language pure, elegant and
                ornamented with imagery, his pronunciation studiously correct; his reasoning as
                close and sound as the doctrines he inculcated would admit, and <pb type="ms" n="407"/>his
                appeals to the feelings suitably pathetic. I came out from hearing him, not a
                convert to his creed, but quite an admirer of his oratory. At the second Dutch
                church, after dinner we heard a discourse much of the same cast of opinions, but not
                recommended by the same graces. I did not retain the preacher’s name— In the Evening
                I went again, with the Ladies to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Stansbury’s Church, and
                heard M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Larned a second time— The house was very much crowded—
                The discourse was upon the propitiatory sacrifice of Christ, and was in some parts
                higher wrought, and in others less elaborate than that of the morning— This
                attendance three times at Church very fully occupied the day, so that I found
                scarcely an hour for writing.— Between the Morning Meeting and dinner I went with
                    M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Johnson on board the Steam-Boat Paragon; and we engaged
                our passages down the North-river to Newburgh to-morrow— On board the boat, I met
                among the attendants, an old acquaintance, <persRef ref="felt-james">James Felt</persRef>, an English cabin boy, on
                board the Washington, when we came in her from England. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and
                    M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Johnson came here intending to go to Boston and Quincy
                by land, by the same way that we came; but we have persuaded them to go with us down
                the North-River, and proceed by the Connecticut Steam-boat from New-York.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-05">
					<head>5 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-05"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Recreation</note>
					    <note type="subject">Religion</note>
					    <note type="subject">Steam Power</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
					    <p><dateline>5. VI:</dateline> Early this Morning <persRef ref="stuart-unknown">Captain Stuart</persRef> called upon me, and with much civility gave
                us an invitation to stay at his house; a sufficient reason for declining which was,
                that we were going immediately after breakfast on board the Steam-boat. This person
                went to England in the character of Secretary to <persRef ref="aspinwall-thomas">Col<hi rend="superscript">l:</hi> Aspinwall</persRef>
                the American Consul at London and was with him there about a year in that capacity.
                Unfavourable stories are told of him, I believe with too much foundation. Having
                this Morning an hour unoccupied I strolled through the principal street of Albany,
                which was originally a dutch settlement, and still contains many houses built after
                the old dutch fashion, and which give the street a resemblance to those of Haarlem
                or Leyden. <persRef ref="johnson-alexander">Johnson</persRef> says some of them are of bricks brought from Holland. At ten
                O’Clock we embarked in the Steamboat Paragon, and immediately left the wharf. Among
                the Passengers were <persRef ref="porter-peter">General Peter B. Porter</persRef> with whom I had began the Journey from
					        Washington, upon which I am now returning, and <persRef ref="larned-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Larned</persRef>, the
                eloquent preacher, who joined us in the Stage at Pittsfield, and whom I yesterday
                heard preach twice at Albany— There was also an Officer of the Marine corps, just
                from Sacket’s harbour, going to Washington, to settle his Accounts— I did not learn
                his name; but he entered into conversation with me; complained bitterly of the
                smallness of his pay, and of some question made against him with regard to the
                settlement of his accounts. He spoke of some invention which he had introduced for
                discharging a volley of musketry, by the operation of one hand, and said he had an
                anonymous invitation which he believed had been transmitted to him through <persRef ref="duane-william">William
                Duane</persRef>, to enter the service of the South-Americans, with great offers of pay and the
                rank of Colonel. He spoke of himself as undetermined whether to accept or decline
                these offers, and hinted that it would depend upon the facility or difficulty that
                he might find in the adjustment of his Accounts at Washington. He seemed to be
                desirous of drawing an opinion or advice from me without asking it; if this was his
                desire, it was not gratified. Another passenger was an old, pimple-faced,
                purple-nosed, spectacled, brogue-talking, noisy Irishman, named <persRef ref="colwell-unknown">Colwell</persRef>, who came
                drunk on board, became about half sober in the course of the day, and more drunk,
                noisy and disgusting at Night than he had been in the Morning. I was told he was a
                very respectable, and most hospitable inhabitant of Albany; a very useful and
                wealthy manufacturer, but of eccentric temper, and habits of beastly drunkenness.
                These he exhibited to the extent of becoming a nuisance to the boat. The day was
                overcast with occasional rain; and so chilly that we passed great part of the time
                in the Cabins. I saw however the general aspect of the river as we descended until
                Night came on. The Banks are generally high, in many places steep, and covered with
                wood— The settlements are not numerous, nor very considerable. The Estates and
                houses of several persons of the Livingstone family are distinguishable
                <pb type="ms" n="408"/>near Hudson. I found no opportunity either for writing or reading; but
					        played several games of chess with a <persRef ref="billings-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Billings</persRef>, a lawyer, who
                like us was to leave the boat at Newburgh. At the request of several of the
                Passengers, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Larned preached a Sermon in the after Cabin, in
                the Evening, and went through the usual forms of divine service according to the
                presbyterian forms— Two Prayers, thrice Psalm singing, and a Sermon— The discourse
                was from 1. John V.10. He that believeth on the Son of God, hath the witness in
                himself, altogether extemporaneous; with less mark of preparation than those which I
                had heard from him yesterday, but delivered with equal fluency, and language equally
                correct. The Sentiments also were of the same kind, dwelling always upon the
                indispensable necessity and efficacy of faith. It was just midnight when we reached
                Newburgh, where we landed, with M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and <persRef ref="johnson-abigail">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                    Johnson</persRef> and their <persRef ref="johnson-john">child</persRef>. It was sometime before we could rouse the Servants and get
					        in at the Hotel kept by <persRef ref="hunt-unknown">Major Hunt</persRef> and belonging to <persRef ref="dewindt-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> de Wint</persRef>.
                The distance from Albany to Newburgh, is one hundred Miles.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-06">
					<head>6 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-06"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Adams Family Relations</note>
					    <note type="subject">Press</note>
					    <note type="subject">War of 1812</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
						<p><dateline>6. VI:30.</dateline> We intended to cross the river, early this morning, but I was detained by
						    visitors— <persRef ref="ross-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ross</persRef> an active and distinguished member of the
						    Senate of this State, <persRef ref="belknap-unknown">General Belknap</persRef>, a Major-General of the Militia, President of
						    the Bank of Newburgh, and as my Landlord, <persRef ref="hunt-unknown">Major Hunt</persRef>, an old revolutionary Officer
						    described him, a man of many offices; <persRef ref="case-walter">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Case</persRef>, the member of the
						    next Congress, elect, for this district, and <persRef ref="rosa-unknown">Doctor Rosa</persRef>, who according to his own
                statement to me, an old Officer of the Revolution. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ross was
                the only one of these Gentlemen who manifested a disposition to enter deeply into
                political conversation, and he immediately came to complaints that the dispositions
                of the People of this State, were much misunderstood and misrepresented in other
                States; and that the principles and conduct of <persRef ref="clinton-dewitt">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> De Witt
                Clinton</persRef>, the present Governor of the State were also misunderstood— He had very
                erroneously been supposed to be in opposition to the present administration, and to
                the late war, with Great Britain— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ross said he had taken very
                particular pains to inform himself on these subjects— That M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                Clinton was not opposed to the present Administration, nor had he been to the late
                War, excepting that he had not approved the time when it was declared, as we were
                not in a state of preparation for it— Ross said that he himself in the Senate of
                New-York, had supported all the most vigorous measures for carrying on the War— and
                had been altogether opposed to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Clinton’s being set up as a
						    candidate for the Presidency, against <persRef ref="madison-james">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Madison</persRef> in 1812. though
                after it had been determined to run an electoral ticket in his favour, in
                consideration of the interest of the State he had voted for it— As this Gentleman
                was a total stranger to me, never having heard so much as his name mentioned before,
                it seemed to me something strange that he should thus commence our acquaintance by
                this apologetic defence of De Witt Clinton, and this explanation of his own
                inconsistency. It was however one among many proofs of the fact that Clinton has had
                the address to concentrate all the political feelings of this state in his own
                person; and that the parties in it consist only of his friends or opponents— It is
                questionable whether any individual has accomplished this to the same extent; and is
                indicative at once of his talents and of the manner in which he has employed them.
                The other Gentlemen took no share in the communicative humour of M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Ross, not even to relieve him from the embarrassment under which he
                seemed to labour, from a foolish pamphlet, as he called it, published during the
                war, by a <persRef ref="southwick-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Southwick</persRef>, and other friends of M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Clinton, against the War— I did not enter much into the Spirit of M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Ross’s discourse; but spoke in respectful terms of M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Clinton’s character— Possibly Ross may have thought that I was
                traveling into New-York, for political objects, and that it was necessary for him to
                be explicit upon the score of his Clintonianism at once— His partizans in the
                Newspapers as well as those of <persRef ref="clay-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Clay</persRef> have pitted their patrons
                respectively against me, from the mere terror of my standing in the way of their
                ambitious views. A coalition between those two parties has already been formed, more
                than sufficient of itself to discard me from the list of their rivals; utterly
                averse as I am to every thing in the shape of political intrigue, for the purposes
                of personal advancement, and utterly unqualified as I am for it— Doctor Rosa
                introduced himself to me as an old revolutionary character, and one of only three,
                now remaining at Newburgh. While I was with these Gentlemen, <persRef ref="dewindt-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                De Wint</persRef> came over the river to meet us, and we returned with him, in his own
						    horse-boat, to his house, Cedar Grove, Fishkill-landing. <persRef ref="verplanck-daniel">Judge Verplanck</persRef>, whom I
                knew formerly as a member of Congress was with him; and with his family, dined and
                spent the Evening with us at his house. They are neighbours, and the most friendly
                intimacy subsists between the two families. <pb type="ms" n="409"/>There was also at dinner,
						    <persRef ref="christie-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Christie</persRef> of New-York, whom about three years since I had
						    seen in England, where he brought me a Letter of recommendation from <persRef ref="gallatin-albert">M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Gallatin</persRef>. John Peter de Wint is a native of the City of New-York, as was
						    his <persRef ref="dewindt-john2">father</persRef>— His <persRef ref="dewindt-elizabeth">mother</persRef> was born at S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Eustatius, and married in
                the Island of S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Croix. She has been many years a widow, and
                this Estate upon which they all live together belongs to her. There are living with
                them two young women named <persRef ref="smalz-unknown;smalz-unknown2">Smalz</persRef>, and one named <persRef ref="denyfel-unknown">den Yfel</persRef>—relations of the family— De
						    Wint married in 1814 <persRef ref="dewindt-caroline">Caroline Amelia Smith</persRef>, my <persRef ref="smith-abigail">Sister’s</persRef> only daughter, and they have
						    <persRef ref="dewindt-caroline2;dewindt-julia">two daughters</persRef>. De Wint’s family both by father and mother originated from
                Holland.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-07">
					<head>7 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-07"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Recreation</note>
					    <note type="subject">Steam Power </note>
					    <note type="subject">War of 1812</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
					    <p><dateline>7. VI:30.</dateline> <persRef ref="dewindt-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> de Wint</persRef> made up a party for us, and we went in a
                small packet Sloop, to West Point, distant nine Miles from Fish-kill landing. The
                party consisted of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and <persRef ref="dewindt-caroline">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> de Wint</persRef>, <persRef ref="johnson-alexander">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi></persRef> and <persRef ref="johnson-abigail">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Johnson</persRef>, with their boy <persRef ref="johnson-john">John Adams
                        Johnson</persRef>, one <persRef ref="smalz-unknown">Miss Smalz</persRef> and <persRef ref="denyfel-unknown">Miss den Yfel</persRef>, a <persRef ref="verplanck-unknown">son</persRef> of <persRef ref="verplanck-daniel">Judge Verplanck’s</persRef>, and a young
					        man named <persRef ref="fenno-unknown">Fenno</persRef>. <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef>, <persRef ref="hellen-mary">Mary Hellen</persRef> and myself— We left the
                wharf about ten O’Clock, and the weather being fine, and almost calm we were nearly
                three hours in descending the river till we landed at West-Point. We had therefore
                ample leisure to view the celebrated passes of the Highlands. Their elevation on
                both sides the river is between 1300 and 1700 feet; of course not very lofty
                Mountains—high enough however, to give the country a picturesque appearance of wild
                grandeur. The hills are steep from the edge of the river and covered with wood—
                There is a clear and strong echo in the passage on the river between the hills,
                which answered to the horn blown by one of our men in the sloop, with pleasing
                effect. one of the hills is shaped so as to exhibit with some assistance from the
                imagination, the form of a gigantic human face in profile. Another has the form, and
                bears the name of a sugar loaf. On landing at West-Point, de Wint went and bespoke a
                dinner for us at the Inn; while the rest of us stroll’d up one of the hills to view
                the prospect around, and the ruins of an old fort upon the brow of one of them. M<hi
                    rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams, Johnson with his boy and myself lost of our way, and I
                went to the top of a hill nearly double the height of the fort we were seeking.
                After some time and search we found de Wint who was also in search of us, and went
                to the fort, from which the prospect is pleasant, but not very extensive. We
                descended and dined at the Inn, and immediately after dinner, met there, old <persRef ref="tallmadge-benjamin">Colonel
                    Talmadge</persRef>, formerly a member of Congress from Connecticut; his Son <persRef ref="tallmadge-frederick">Col<hi rend="superscript"
                    >l:</hi> Talmadge</persRef>, who served in the late war, and whom I knew two years ago, in
					        England, and another <persRef ref="tallmadge-george">Son</persRef>, now a Cadet at the Academy at West Point. We called on
					        <persRef ref="thayer-sylvanus">Major Thayer</persRef> who is at the head of this Military Academy. He was not at his house,
                but we met him at the public building of the Academy, containing the Library; the
                collection of Maps and the apparatus for the lectures in natural and experimental
                philosophy; all of which he shewed us, together with <persRef ref="lenox-unknown3">Captain Lenox</persRef>, whom he
                introduced to me. The library of twelve hundred volumes was chiefly collected in
                Europe, by Major Thayer himself; as were the maps, many of which are very good.
                There are now he told me two hundred and twenty Cadets at the Academy, upwards of
                one hundred having been admitted this Summer. The establishment can accommodate not
                more than 270. Their exercises literary, and recitations, are in the morning, and
                accordingly I could not witness them; but we saw numbers of them in Platoons, before
                the buildings, drilled by the Cadets of older standing— About five in the afternoon
                we embarked again in our Sloop, and returned with a beautiful, mild and calm Evening
                to Fish-kill landing. We saw the purple tint of the Sunbeams lingering on the tops
                of the Mountains, and heard by Moon-light the distant echo of the horns blown from a
                boat upon the river in the passage between them. About seven in the Evening we
                landed at the wharf from which we had this morning departed— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                and M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Johnson there left us—and crossed the river to Newburgh,
                whence they proceed with the Steam-boat which comes <pb type="ms" n="410"/>this day from
                Albany, down to New-York. The rest of us returned to Cedar grove, where we found
                judge Verplanck, and <persRef ref="dewindt-peter">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Peter de Wint</persRef>, a Cousin of John Peter’s
                and an inmate of the family. Some of the younger part of our party went to a Ball
                this Evening at Fish-kill— We endeavoured to persuade Johnson to stay, till
                to-morrow Night, and then go on with us; but he could not have stayed without
                missing the Steam-boat of Friday Morning from New-York to Norwich, which would have
                delayed him three days at New-York, till next Monday. Johnson’s child is the most
                extraordinary boy, at three years of age that I ever saw; but is indulged by his
                father to such an excess that he is extremely troublesome— He talks incessantly,
                though his articulation is yet defective; and has a quick power of observation and
                retentive memory, loaded with senseless and stupid words which have been taught him
                as jokes, and which he repeats with rudeness— His temper is good and his great
                danger is of being ruined by Mismanagement— His father is nevertheless a sedate,
                sensible and apparently discreet man. His mother now not more than twenty appears
                also of a grave and judicious character, and less disposed to spoil the child than
                her husband.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-08">
					<head>8 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-08"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					        <note type="subject">Recreation</note>
					        <note type="subject">Textile Industry</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
						<p><dateline>8. VI:15.</dateline> Immediately after breakfast <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef> and I took a ride
						    with <persRef ref="dewindt-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persRef> and <persRef ref="dewindt-caroline">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> De Wint</persRef> to one of the
                mountains in the neighbourhood, which we ascended partly in a light uncovered
                waggon, and the rest on foot, to the summit called Solomon’s Barracks, which is
                surmounted by a flag-staff. The prospect from it is extensive, although several of
                the hills in the vicinity are higher— I extract from a newspaper a statement of the
                height of all the principal elevations on Hudson river, said to have been calculated
                by <persRef ref="partridge-alden">Captain Partridge</persRef>.— Catskill-Mountains. Round top. 3105 feet. High Peak 3019.—
                Highlands—New Beacon 1585 Butter Hill 1529. Bull-Hill 1484. Old Beacon 1471. Crow’s
                Nest 1418. Brave-Mount 1350 Break-Neck. 1187. Anthony’s Nose. 935. Sugar-loaf 866.
                Fort Putnam 598. West-Point Plain 188— Below New-York—Hempstead Harbour Hill 319.
                Staten-Island 307 Neversink heights 282. but I think they must be much higher.
                Returning from the hills we stopped at the manufactory of cotton cloths at their
                foot. <persRef ref="schenk-abraham">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Schenk</persRef> formerly a member of Congress, is the manager
                and part owner of them, and shewed us the various machinery for carding spinning and
                weaving used by them— generally the same that I had seen at Alexandrofsky, and at
                Ghent— These works are carried on by Water-Mills and they make no use of the
                Steam-Engine— We had intended to proceed to New-York in the Steam-boat from Albany,
                which will pass by Newburgh this Evening; but finally concluded to postpone our
                departure till to-morrow morning, when a Steam-boat direct from Newburgh goes to
                New-York. We dined with all the De Wint family at <persRef ref="verplanck-daniel">judge Verplanck’s</persRef>, where we met
						    his <persRef ref="verplanck-samuel">father</persRef>, an old man upwards of four-score of very singular habits and opinions.
                We found him standing at the table in the dining room, when we went from the parlour
                in to dinner; and he left the table and withdrew immediately after dinner— We saw no
                more of him. There was also of the party a <persRef ref="bunner-rudolph">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bunner</persRef>; a lawyer
						    who resides at Newburgh, and who some years since married a <persRef ref="bunner-elizabeth">Miss Church</persRef>; the second
						    daughter of the late <persRef ref="church-john">John Barker Church</persRef>. Bunner is a lively, social man of pleasant
                manners and agreeable conversation— We sat some time at table, after the Ladies
                retired; discussing the propriety of that usage— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bunner
                accompanied us in the Evening, when we returned to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> De
                Wint’s.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-09">
					<head>9 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-09"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					   <note type="subject">American Revolution</note>
					    <note type="subject">Steam Power</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
					    <p><dateline>9. VI:</dateline> We took leave this morning of <persRef ref="dewindt-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> de Wint</persRef>, and his family;
                and at eight O’Clock, were taken up, at Fishkill landing, by the Steam-boat
                Fire-fly, <persRef ref="griswald-unknown">Captain Griswold</persRef>, from Newburgh, in which we descended the river, to
                New-York— The distance is seventy miles, and the weather being remarkably fine and
                warm, I passed the whole day upon the deck— The Scenery on the banks of the river is
                similar to that between Albany and Newburgh. The banks of the river on both sides
                generally high, steep, and covered with woods— Few settlements at the landings, and
                not one remarkable Country-seat visible till within five miles of New-York— West
                Point, and its neighbourhood were the Scene of <persRef ref="arnold-benedict">Arnold’s</persRef> treachery, in the American
                revolutionary war; and Captain Griswold pointed out to me several of the places
                which were critical in that transaction such as the Point, from which he took boat
                to go on board the Vulture, Sloop of War— The spot where <persRef ref="andre-john">Andre</persRef> was stopped in his
					        progress to New-York, by the three Militia-men <persRef ref="paulding-john">Paulding</persRef>, <persRef ref="vanwart-isaac">Van Wert</persRef> and <persRef ref="williams-david">Williams</persRef>—
					        Arnold’s Head-Quarters at <persRef ref="robinson-beverley">Robinson’s</persRef> house the landing where Andre was taken across
                the river, and the road to Tappan where he was tried and executed. The position upon
                the river where the Vulture lay, and the sites of other incidents in that Tragedy
                which the traditional memory of the Country has treasured up. The point of Arnold’s
                embarkation goes by the name of Traitor’s Point. The Captain had <persRef ref="smith-joshua">Joshua Hall Smith’s</persRef>
                narrative of that affair, which was published in 1809. and I read it over again, in
                the course of the day. Smith was a Tory, whom Arnold employed to accomplish his
                purpose: <pb type="ms" n="411"/>without disclosing to him his secret— It was he that went on
                board the Vulture, and brought Andre on shore to the interview with Arnold. It was a
                coat of Smith’s that André wore as a disguise, upon his return and Smith accompanied
                him back to within a few miles of where he was taken— From the Account in Smith’s
                book it appears that he was tried himself by a Court-Martial, and was afterwards
                kept two years in close prison until he made his escape. Yet he was suspected on the
                British side of having betrayed Andre and caused his being taken. He professes to
                publish this book for his vindication. — It was eight in the Evening when we reached
                New-York— <persRef ref="smalz-unknown">Miss Smalz</persRef>, and <persRef ref="christie-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Chrystie</persRef> with his <persRef ref="christie-unknown2">Mother</persRef> came down
                the river with us. We took lodgings for the Night, at the City Hotel in
                Broadway.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-10">
					<head>10 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-10"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Steam Power</note>
					    <note type="subject">Roads</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
						<p><dateline>10. VI:</dateline> This was one of the few Morning’s since I have been on this journey, when I
						    have been enabled to write a couple of hours. After breakfast I called upon <persRef ref="clarkson-william">W. S.
						        Clarkson</persRef> at his Bank, and upon <persRef ref="mccormick-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M’Cormick</persRef> at his house—
						    <persRef ref="pitcairn-joseph">Pitcairn</persRef> sailed about ten days since for Europe— At our Hotel I saw again <persRef ref="tallmadge-frederick">Col<hi
                    rend="superscript">l.</hi> Talmadge</persRef> the younger whom we had met at West-Point; and
						    <persRef ref="trumbull-john">Trumbull</persRef> the Painter, whose Picture of the Declaration of Independence is now
                exhibited at New-York. He wishes also to have it exhibited at Boston and at
                Philadelphia, before sending it on to Washington; and asked me, if he could expect
                the President’s permission to that effect— I knew not of any objection, and agreed
                that he should take the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> consent for granted, unless he should hear from
                me to the contrary, hereafter— Between twelve and One, at Noon, we embarked in the
						    <persRef ref="tompkins-daniel">Vice-President’s</persRef> Steam-Boat Nautilus, at White Hall: landed in an hour at
                Staten-Island where we took the Post-Chaise in which we crossed the Island; then
                passed in a Horse-Boat to the Jersey shore and rode four Miles further to
                Woodbridge. The passengers were so numerous that there were two carriages, each
                laden with eleven persons, and the dinner table prepared at Woodbridge allowed seats
                for no more than fourteen or fifteen. I therefore went on without dining, which in
                traveling by land is the most convenient and pleasant way of getting through the
                day. We proceeded from Woodbridge 18 Miles to New Brunswick, 16. to Princeton, and
                10 to Trenton, where we arrived at ten in the Evening— Our companions in the Stage
                were not agreeable, nor conversible, with us, and in the other Carriage, associates
                with us at the Inns, were three drunken common Sailors. At Trenton we obtained one
                bed-chamber for us of my family; but the Supper table was again so full that no
                seats at it were left for us, and after an hour and a half of solicitation and
                intreaty to have tea and supper taken up to our chamber, I was obliged to give up
                the pursuit, and we all lost our Supper, as I had lost my dinner. A more important
                and mortifying loss to me was that of my temper, and I suffered myself to be so far
                irritated and ruffled that after retiring to bed I lay great part of the Night
                sleepless; and heard the grating sound of the Midnight and Morning Clock.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-11">
					<head>11 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-11"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Bank of the United States</note>
					    <note type="subject">Religion</note>
					    <note type="subject">Roads</note>
					    <note type="subject">Steam Power</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
						<p><dateline>11. IV.</dateline> At this hour we were roused to continue our Journey; I had scarcely been
                asleep; but the driver of one of our Carriages overslept himself so that we had
                nearly two hours to wait for him— It was near six when we started from Trenton, but
                we reached Bristol soon after seven— It is a stage of ten Miles. There we
                breakfasted and then proceeded in the Steam-boat Pennsylvania, with a high-pressure
                engine to Philadelphia— We were little more than two hours in traversing the
                twenty-miles, and landed at the lower Market Street wharf soon after ten in the
                Morning— We took a hack, and went to the mansion house, <persRef ref="renshaw-william">Renshaw’s</persRef> where they were
						    full, and could not receive us—then to <persRef ref="frazier-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Frazier’s</persRef>; then to
						    <persRef ref="judd-anson">Judd’s</persRef> Hotel—all full— At last we found apartments at <persRef ref="shinn-elizabeth">Miss Shinn’s</persRef>— N. 30. North
						    third Street— Soon after alighting, I walked out to call upon <persRef ref="connell-john">J. Connell</persRef>, but before
                reaching his house I met him in the Street. He returned with me to my lodgings—came
                again in the afternoon and accompanied us to the Roman Catholic Church of <hi
                    rend="superscript">t.</hi> Augustine where we heard vespers chanted, and, in the
                Evening, when I went with him to the Baptist Church, with the expectation of hearing
						    <persRef ref="staughton-william">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Staughton</persRef> its Minister, but heard instead of him a <persRef ref="skinner-thomas">D<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Skinner</persRef>, a Presbyterian—reputed to be very violent and
                furious, <pb type="ms" n="412"/>but whom I did not find so. His doctrines were those of the
						    Presbyterians generally. Much the same as those preached by <persRef ref="larned-unknown2">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                Larned</persRef>. But he is not so eloquent—and he read his Sermon. The Church was crowded.
						    <persRef ref="jones-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> W. Jones</persRef>, President of the Bank of the United States, and
						    his <persRef ref="jones-unknown">Lady</persRef> paid us visits this Evening, and invited us to dinner to-morrow— At dinner
						    this day we met several gentlemen as boarders at the house— <persRef ref="wright-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
						        Wright</persRef>, a New Englandman; <persRef ref="stith-unknown">Captain Stith</persRef>, a Virginian, a <persRef ref="tracy-unknown">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                Tracy</persRef>, and an Irishman, who discussed among them the merits of the Clergyman,
                Skinner, whom I heard this Evening.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-12">
					<head>12 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-12"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Adams Family Finances</note>
					    <note type="subject">Bank of the United States</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
						<p><dateline>12. VII:15.</dateline> I had several small affairs of private business to transact, at the Bank
                of the United States: at the Office of the permanent Schuylkill Bridge Company, kept
                by <persRef ref="whalen-israel">Israel Whalen</persRef>, in North fourth Street, and with a <persRef ref="allibone-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    Allibone</persRef>, for whom I called at <persRef ref="milner-unknown">Milner</persRef> and <persRef ref="richards-unknown">Richards’s</persRef>, corner of Nine and third
						    Streets. I also called upon <persRef ref="mceuen-thomas">M’Euen</persRef>, <persRef ref="hale-thomas">Hale</persRef> and <persRef ref="davidson-william">Davidson</persRef>, intending to put all the
                Schuylkill Bridge Shares into their hands to be disposed of; but finding them, at
                more than ten per Cent under par, although they still yield an income of six per
                Cent, I determined to keep them somewhat longer.— Visited at <persRef ref="ewing-samuel">S. Ewing’s</persRef> and <persRef ref="sergeant-john">J.
                    Sergeant’s</persRef>. Met in the Street <persRef ref="meredith-william">W. Meredith</persRef>, and Commodore’s <persRef ref="decatur-stephen">Decatur</persRef> and <persRef ref="perry-oliver">Perry</persRef>, who
                was yesterday from Washington, and told me the President was expected there this
                day— Received visits from <persRef ref="walsh-robert">R. Walsh</persRef>, <persRef ref="vaughan-john">J. Vaughan</persRef> who brought me the third volume of
						    <persRef ref="franklin-benjamin">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Franklin’s</persRef> Memoirs, which he had taken from the
						    Custom-house, and which had been sent me by <persRef ref="franklin-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Temple Franklin</persRef>,
						    the Editor— <persRef ref="connell-john">J. Connell</persRef>, J. Sergeant and his <persRef ref="sergeant-thomas">brother</persRef>, whom I saw, <persRef ref="dashkov-andrei">M<hi rend="superscript"
						        >r</hi> Daschkoff</persRef> the Russian and <persRef ref="greuhm-frederick">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Greuhm</persRef> the Prussian
						    Minister had called while I was out— Also <persRef ref="ingersoll-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> C. J. Ingersoll</persRef>, <persRef ref="dallas-george">G.
						        M. Dallas</persRef>, <persRef ref="bache-richard">R. Bache</persRef>, <persRef ref="dallas-sophia">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Dallas</persRef> and <persRef ref="bache-sophia">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
						            Bache</persRef> &amp;c. We dined and spent the Evening at <persRef ref="jones-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> W. Jones’s</persRef>;
                the President of the Bank of the United States. Ingersoll, Dallas and Connell were
                there, and some other company with whom I was unacquainted— I was not satisfied with
                myself this day, having talked too much at dinner— I never take a large share in
                conversation, without saying things which I afterwards wish were unsaid— Yet in the
                estimation of others, I pass off, on the whole better when I talk freely, than when
                silent and reserved— This sometimes stimulates me to talk more than is wise or
                proper, and to give to the conversation of mixed companies, a tone of discussion
                which becomes irksome and tedious. Nor can I always, (I did not this day) altogether
                avoid a dogmatical and peremptory tone and manner, always disgusting, and especially
                offensive in persons, to whose age or situation others consider some deference
                due.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-13">
					<head>13 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-13"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Adams Family Finances</note>
					    <note type="subject">African Americans</note>
					    <note type="subject">Colonization Movements</note>
					    <note type="subject">Science and Technology</note>
					    <note type="subject">Steam Power</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
						<p><dateline>13. V:</dateline> Rising just at daylight, and before I could see distinctly to write or read, I
                walked out, and went down to the upper Market Street wharf, to enquire for the Steam
                Boat AEtna, on board of which I had left my Umbrella, when we were going on to
                Quincy— I found the hours of her departure and arrival had been changed, and that
                she would come in from Bordentown at ten O’clock. Returned to our lodgings, but
                found little time for writing. <persRef ref="allibone-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Allibone</persRef> called, and I settled
                with him the Account for my <persRef ref="adams-abigail">Mother</persRef>— This was the day of the general election, and
                Allibone, who said he was a federalist, added that for the first time a coalition
                had been formed between the federalists, and the Old school democrats; and that the
                federalists had agreed to vote for <persRef ref="leib-michael">M. Leib</persRef>, as a Senator in the State Legislature—
                Leib had always been a man, not only extremely obnoxious to the federalists, but
                there were imputations upon his private character which they had always held up as a
                reproach and infamy to the party supporting— Yet so flexible is their own moral
                purity that they now vote for this man themselves— Allibone said it might be good
                policy; but he doubted whether he could reconcile it to his principles. <persRef ref="perkins-jacob">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Perkins</persRef> came and asked me to call at his work-shop and look at
                his machinery for engraving Steel-plates for Bank-Bills. At Breakfast there was with
                the other Boarders a <persRef ref="clapiers-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Clapiers</persRef>, a Frenchman, brother of one of
						    the <persRef ref="clapiers-unknown2">same name</persRef> whom we saw in Russia. He told me that <persRef ref="barthe-unknown">Barthe</persRef> was dead— At nine
						    O’Clock <persRef ref="vaughan-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Vaughan</persRef> called and I went with him to the apartment
                of the American philosophical Society. He shewed me a collection of maps of America,
                published within these two years at Paris; coloured apparently with a view to
                confine the territories of the United States within the narrowest limits left them
                by the pretensions of all or any other Power whatever—distributing the whole western
                Coast of America, between Spain, Russia and Great Britain— Bordering us upon Spain
                to the South at the line from the Mennentao to Natchitoches, and stopping us
                Westward at the Rocky Mountains. At this apartment I met <persRef ref="duponceau-peter">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    Duponceau</persRef>, <persRef ref="pearson-eliphalet">Professor Pearson</persRef> of Andover, and <persRef ref="winthrop-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> John Winthrop</persRef>;
                the same <pb type="ms" n="413"/>I had seen last year in England. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
						    Vaughan lent me from the Books of the Society the third narrative of <persRef ref="lasalle-robert">La Salle’s</persRef>
						    discoveries, by <persRef ref="hennepin-louis">father Hennepin</persRef>—the other two being at the Library of Congress at
                Washington— I went to Perkins and saw his machinery, and his copperplates taken by
                pressure from Steel-plates. The invention is ingenious, and must be effectual to
                preserve Bank-Bills from being forged, so far as relates to the engraved parts— The
                imitation appears to be scarcely possible. I met there <persRef ref="harrod-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    Charles Harrod</persRef>, brother of <persRef ref="adams-thomas">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> T. B. Adams</persRef>, and settled at
						    New-Orleans— On returning to my lodgings I found there <persRef ref="sanders-prince">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Prince
                Sanders</persRef> the black man; who has returned from his establishments in the kingdom of
						    <persRef ref="christophe-henri">king Henry</persRef> of Haÿti. I asked him if he intended to return thither, to which he did
                not think proper to give a direct answer; but said if he did it would be contrary to
                the advice of his friends. He appeared to be labouring however with the project of
                colonizing Hayti from the free people of colour in the United States. He admitted
                that the Government of King Henry was of rather an arbitrary character, and in
                respect to personal liberty and security was susceptible of some improvements. He
                spoke however very guardedly and with great reserve. I gave him my opinion of king
                Henry’s government very freely. Our conversation was interrupted by the arrival of
                the hour for my departure— At Noon we embarked in the Steam-boat Superior, <persRef ref="milnor-unknown">Captain
                Milnor</persRef> for Wilmington; being the line of Steamboats and Stages, in opposition to
                that of Newcastle and Frenchtown, which we took in going Eastward. The weather was
                rainy, with a heavy gale of wind. We dined on board the Steam-boat; arrived at
                Wilmington by four in the afternoon, and proceeded immediately in Post-Chaises to
                the head of Elk, 20 Miles; where we arrived between seven and eight in the Evening.
                We immediately embarked in the Steamboat Eagle; where I unexpectedly met the <persRef ref="onis-luis">Spanish
                Minister Onis</persRef> and his family, returning like ourselves to Washington. The violence
                of the gale had abated, but there was still a heavy swell in Chesapeake Bay, and the
                Evening was so damp and chill that we were chiefly confined to the Cabins. The
                births were for the most part engaged when we came on board; but the Captain gave me
                his own State-Room. About ten, I retired to bed, but not to sleep.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-14">
					<head>14 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-14"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Adams Family Residences</note>
					    <note type="subject">Dueling</note>
					    <note type="subject">Roads</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
						<p><dateline>14. III:30.</dateline> <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>. Our passage from Elkton to Baltimore
                was very rapid; for at half past three O’Clock in the Morning we were along side of
                the wharf. The opposition line has abridged nearly by one half the time of
                performing the Journey between Philadelphia and Baltimore—for last year I left
                Philadelphia at Noon and reached Baltimore the next day at five in the afternoon—29.
                hours. but now, leaving Philadelphia, at the same hour of Noon, we reached
                Baltimore, between three and four O’Clock the next Morning; less than sixteen hours.
                After waiting in the Boat till near five O’Clock, we walked up to <persRef ref="gadsby-john">Gadsby’s</persRef> tavern,
                and were three hours in ascertaining whether we could have a room there— The house
                being upon our arrival entirely full. <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef> had written from
						    New-York, directing that our <persRef ref="smothers-harry">Coachman Harry</persRef> should come with our light Coaches to
                Baltimore, to be there last Evening. We found he had not arrived; and supposing
                either that the Letter had not been received; or that some accident had prevented
                the Carriage from arriving, I was engaging Seats for us all in the eight O’Clock
                Stage; when Harry came in with our Horses and Carriage. The bad weather of yesterday
                had made such heavy roads, that he had broken the Pole, and a glass of the Carriage,
                and had been obliged to travel all night to reach Baltimore thus early this morning.
                I took Seats therefore in the Stage, only for myself and <persRef ref="scheiling-philip">Philip</persRef>, and left M<hi
                    rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams and <persRef ref="hellen-mary">Mary Hellen</persRef> to come on in our own Carriage this
						    afternoon or to-morrow. <persRef ref="johnson-william">Judge Johnson</persRef> of South Carolina, with his <persRef ref="johnson-unknown">Sister</persRef> and
						    <persRef ref="johnson-anna">daughter</persRef>, were leaving Gadsby’s house, and left a vacant chamber for M<hi rend="superscript"
						        >rs</hi> Adams. We met at Baltimore, <persRef ref="roth-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Roth</persRef>, Secretary to
						    the French legation, just embarking for France, on a leave of absence. <persRef ref="tencate-j">ten Cate</persRef>, the
                late Dutch Charge d’Affaires he told us had been with him and intended to embark
                with him; but yesterday suddenly went off for New-York, he believed to fight a duel,
                with <persRef ref="willink-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Willink</persRef>, a Dutchman <pb type="ms" n="414"/>who had been the
                occasion of ten Cate’s being recalled, and had affronted him, by paying a Bill of
                Exchange, drawn by ten Cate, and which had come back protested; and endorsing upon
                it Paid for the honour of Holland— I had several travelling companions in the Stage;
                and among them <persRef ref="latrobe-benjamin">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Latrobe</persRef> the Architect, a very pleasant and
                social one— The roads were still heavy from the rains of yesterday. We dined at
						    <persRef ref="cookendorfer-thomas">Cokendorfers</persRef>, formerly <persRef ref="ross-unknown2">Ross’s</persRef>; and just at five O’Clock in the afternoon, I alighted
                at my house in Washington; and spent the Evening alone, in reading and writing.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-15">
					<head>15 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-15"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Adams Family Finances</note>
					    <note type="subject">Bank of the United States</note>
					    <note type="subject">Press</note>
					    <note type="subject">Sectionalism</note>
					    <note type="subject">Treaty of Ghent</note>
					    <note type="subject">West, The</note>
					    
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
					    <p><dateline>15. VI:30.</dateline> A young man by the name of <persRef ref="essex-unknown">Essex</persRef> called on me this morning, having Letters
					        from <persRef ref="pope-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John Pope</persRef> to <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef>, and to <persRef ref="boyd-george">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> George Boyd</persRef>, who has removed from this City into Virginia. He
                is an applicant for a warrant as a Midshipman in the Navy. I called at the
					        <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> where I met <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun</persRef>. The President arrived from
                his seat in Virginia last Sunday. His health is better than it was in the Spring,
                but still somewhat infirm— He told me that <persRef ref="crowninshield-benjamin">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crowninshield</persRef> had
                resigned the Office of Secretary of the Navy; it was announced in the National
                Intelligencer of this Morning— The President said that as there was no person who
                occurred to him from the Western Country, he proposed to make his Selection from one
                of the middle Atlantic States; ranging between New-York and Maryland—and he named
                the late <persRef ref="snyder-simon">Governor Snyder</persRef> of Pennsylvania, <persRef ref="thompson-smith">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thompson</persRef>, now Chief
					        Justice of the Supreme Court of New-York, and <persRef ref="porter-peter">General Peter B. Porter</persRef> as persons of
                whom he had thought— Their respective merits were discussed, and as Porter is now a
                Commissioner under two Articles of the Treaty of Ghent, and could not without
                inconvenience be replaced by another person for that service, he was laid out of the
                question— I observed to the President, that it would be very desirable, if possible
                to have one member of the administration from the Western States. It was a great and
                rapidly growing Section of the Union, and there appeared to be some uneasiness among
                them, at what they considered as an exclusion from the Cabinet, as it is usually
                called. The appointment of one member of the Administration from among them I
                thought would have a happy and conciliatory effect. He said he was well aware of the
                weight of these Considerations, and asked if I had thought of any person belonging
                to that part of the Union, suitable for the appointment— I said my acquaintance
                there was very limited, and the more so from the long absence from the United States
                from which I have recently returned. But I thought there must be many individuals
                there, well qualified to preside over a Department and to advise, as a member of the
                Administration— He said he would think further of the subject and asked how I
                thought it would be proper to have the duties of the head of the Department supplied
                in the interval, till the new appointment— It might be, either by assigning them to
                one of the acting Heads of the other Departments—or to the President of the board of
                Commissioners of the Navy—or to <persRef ref="homans-benjamin">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Homans</persRef> the Chief Clerk of the
					        Navy Department. During a late vacancy in the War Department, the Chief Clerk, <persRef ref="graham-george">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r.</hi> George Graham</persRef>, had officiated as acting Secretary; but there
                had been some complaints against M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Homans and certain
                circumstances of his conduct had been brought to light during the last Session of
                Congress, which he, the President thought of very little weight and not affecting
                his integrity; but which others viewed in a more serious light, insomuch that two
                members of Congress had even suggested to him that it should have subjected Homans
                to censure from him— To give him the powers of a head of Department might therefore
                occasion public animadversion; and on the other hand to make a different disposal
                might wound his feelings, and seem to give countenance to those prejudices against
                him, which seemed to be not altogether just. <persRef ref="madison-james">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Madison</persRef>, at his
                late visit to him in Virginia, had intimated an opinion that the Office of Secretary
                of the Navy might be itself abolished, and its duties assigned to the President of
                the Commissioners of the Navy but he did not concur in that opinion, and was
                unwilling to give so much countenance to it as even a temporary appointment of the
                President of the Board, to do the duties of the Secretary of the Navy might
                warrant.— on the subject of foreign Affairs, little was said. There are several
                important despatches received from Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> <persRef ref="rush-richard">Rush</persRef>, <persRef ref="gallatin-albert">Gallatin</persRef>, and
					        <persRef ref="erving-george">Erving</persRef> which I had not yet seen. The mass of papers at the Department, accumulated
                since the direction was received from me to forward no more of them to Boston, is so
                great that I almost despair of getting through the reading of them— I was but a
                short time at the Office and only read over a few of the papers— Called and made
                some arrangements at the Branch and Metropolis Banks— On returning home to dinner, I
                found that <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef> and <persRef ref="hellen-mary">Mary Hellen</persRef> had arrived from Baltimore,
                which they did not leave till this morning.</p>
					</div>
				</div>
    
    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-16">
        <head>16 October 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-10-16"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
        </bibl>
        
        <div type="docbody">
            <p><pb type="ms" n="415"/><dateline>16. VI.</dateline> Young <persRef ref="essex-unknown">Essex</persRef> was here this morning, I believe two hours; and to
                no earthly purpose but that of consuming my time. I have not the address to dismiss
                such persons with courtesy, nor the temper to turn them off with rudeness. <persRef ref="scott-john">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Scott</persRef> the delegate from the Missouri territory likewise came
                in. He remained here several weeks after the close of the last Session of Congress;
                and is already upon the ground in preparation for the next— I had a visit also from
                <persRef ref="swift-joseph">General Swift</persRef>. At the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> I met <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford</persRef> the
                Secretary of the Treasury. Something further was said with regard to the temporary
                filling of the Navy Department— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford observed that there
                were precedents for both the modes of filling it, by the Head of another Department,
                or by the Chief Clerk; and he appeared to think unfavourably of Homans; at least he
                thought after <persRef ref="blagrove-unknown">Blagrove’s</persRef> exposure of him last winter, he ought to have deposited the
                whole balance of Public monies in his hands, immediately in the Bank— I was again
                but a short time at the Office— <persRef ref="frye-nathaniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persRef> and <persRef ref="frye-carolina">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                    Frye</persRef>, with <persRef ref="hellen-johnson">Johnson</persRef> and <persRef ref="hellen-thomas">Thomas Hellen</persRef> and <persRef ref="buchanan-robert">Robert Buchanan</persRef>, and <persRef key="smith-william-steuben">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persRef>
                and <persRef key="smith-catherine-johnson">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> W. S. Smith</persRef>, spent the Evening with us, and we had a
                party of Loto with the Children.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-17">
					<head>17 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-17"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Adams Family Residences</note>
					    <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
					    <note type="subject">Mexican Independence (1810–1821)</note>
					    <note type="subject">Native Americans</note>
					    <note type="subject">Privateering</note>
					    <note type="subject">South American Wars of Independence</note>
					    <note type="subject">War of 1812 </note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
					    <p><dateline>17. V:</dateline> <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun</persRef> the Secretary at War called upon me this
					        Morning with a <persRef ref="ware-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ware</persRef> of the State of Mississippi, who had been
					        mentioned to me by <persRef ref="vaughan-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John Vaughan</persRef> and <persRef ref="brown-unknown">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                Brown</persRef> whom we met in the street at Philadelphia last Tuesday Morning, and whom
                Vaughan introduced to me. They were under the impression that Ware himself had seen
                at San Antonio, records of antient grants of Land by the French Government within
                the Province of Texas. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Vaughan therefore had promised to ask
                Ware to call upon me when he should come to Washington—but it proved, not that he
                had seen these records himself, but that Americans who were at San Antonio in the
                year 1813. had told him they had seen them there— The records and the town of San
                Antonio itself have been since burnt, when retaken by the Royalists.— <persRef ref="graham-john">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> John Graham</persRef> called on me at the Office, and mentioned to me,
                that the Report of the late Commissioners to South-America, was to be drawn up by
					        <persRef ref="rodney-caesar">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Rodney</persRef>, and would contain rather a statement of facts
                collected by the Commissioners, and observed by them than any opinions of their own—
                To this I readily assented— He said he had written to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Rodney
                before I last left the City, that the <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef> and all the Administration would
                probably be here by the 15<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>of this Month; and that it would
                be expected that the Report of the Commissioners would then be ready. M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Rodney had answered him that he would have it ready by the
                time; but within these few days had written him again that he had been unexpectedly
                called away upon business of his own, which would delay for a short time the
                completion of the Report— I told M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Graham that if it was sent
                in by the end of the Month it would be in time; but it could not without
                inconvenience be longer postponed, as Congress are to convene on the 16<hi
                    rend="superscript">th. </hi>of next Month, and the manner in which the subject will be
                mentioned by the President in his message, will depend in some measure upon the
                Report.— I had mentioned yesterday Young <persRef ref="essex-unknown">Essex</persRef> to the President as soliciting a
                Warrant of Midshipman; and as he belongs to the State of Kentucky, from which the
                proportion of Officers in the Navy is very small, the President directed that a
                warrant should issue for him immediately; as well as for a young man named <persRef ref="telfair-unknown">Telfair</persRef>,
                of Virginia recommended by <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford</persRef>. I called at the Navy
					        Department, and spoke to <persRef ref="homans-benjamin">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Homans</persRef> about the warrants. He found
                Telfair’s name on the list of Applicants. Essex’s application was entirely new. He
                said he would have the Warrants made out immediately but there was no person yet
                authorized to countersign them— <persRef ref="swartwout-robert">Col<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> Swartwout</persRef> was yesterday
                commissioned as Navy Agent at New-York— He had called upon me the day before to ask
                for my influence in obtaining the appointment. I told him that being perfectly
                disposed to render him any service in my power, I should be happy if he should
                obtain the appointment; but as it was of the resort of another Department my general
                rule was merely to make known to the President such applications as were made
                through me <pb type="ms" n="416"/>together with the recommendations by which they were
                supported, leaving him to judge of them himself. I should feel myself peculiarly
                obliged to observe that course in the present case, having been very earnestly
                solicited at my passage through New-York to interest myself in behalf of another
                person, a <persRef ref="rutgers-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Rutgers</persRef>— Col<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> Swartwout
                professed to be entirely satisfied with this— I received last Evening a Note from
                the <persRef ref="correa-joseph">Abbe Correa</persRef>, the Portuguese Minister, complaining of an attempt to fit out an
                armed vessel in the Patuxent to cruize against Portuguese subjects and property,
                under Commissions from <persRef ref="artigas-jose">Artigas</persRef>— I met the Abbé as I was going to the Office and
                appointed to see him at 2 O’Clock, when he came. I told him that the only way in
                which the Executive could interpose was by directing a prosecution of the persons
                chargeable with a violation of the Laws, and that if he would give the names of such
                persons and of the witnesses who would establish the proof against them, the
					        <persRef ref="glenn-elias">Attorney for the District of Maryland</persRef> would be directed to commence a prosecution.
                He asked whether the President was not authorized by the Law of the last Session of
                Congress to employ the army and navy of the United States to suppress such
                armaments. I said he was, but that he could not take the facts for granted— A
                judicial conviction appeared to be the only proof upon which he could resort to
                measures of that character— He said he could have no confidence in any judicial
                prosecution— What reliance for instance could he place for instance in the verdict
                of a jury selected by the <persRef ref="stevenson-john">Sheriff of Baltimore</persRef>, who was himself concerned in the
                fitting out of these privateers. I told him the Sheriff of Baltimore would have
                nothing to do with the selection of the Juries, the trial being before the Courts of
                the United States, and not those of the State. He said it was very hard, that such
                things must be doing almost under the very eyes of this Government; and that there
                should be no remedy for Portugal, whose <persRef ref="john-vi">king</persRef> had always been so friendly towards the
                United States. That privateering Commissions from Artigas were mere absurdities, as
                he had possession of no Seaport; and that there might just as well issue Commissions
                for privateering, from Harper’s ferry, or from the Seminole Indians— That he was
                fully persuaded of the just and honourable intentions of the American Government;
                but that “we had a most unmanageable crew—” I answered him that I trusted he did not
                intend by that remark to cast a reflection upon the nature of our Institutions, but
                that at all events our people were quite as manageable for every good purpose, as
                the people of any other Nation, not excepting that of Portugal and Brazil. That we
                wished to take no part in the war carried on between the Portuguese Government and
                that of Artigas; but that there could be no analogy between Artigas and the Seminole
                Indians— He disclaimed any intention of reflecting upon our Institutions, and
                professed on the contrary great respect for them; but he recurred to the kindness
                which his king had always manifested to the United States. I mentioned to him the
                case of the privateer General Armstrong at Fayal, during our late War with England—
                He said that Ghost was always brought up against him— He had written about it to his
                Court, when I mentioned it to him before and had received all the papers that had
                passed between them, and the British Government concerning it. Fayal was an open
                road; incapable of resistance; and great damage was done upon the occasion of this
                transaction, to the houses of the inhabitants on shore. The British Government had
                offered to indemnify all those inhabitants, but his Court had refused to accept that
                indemnity, without satisfaction’s being given to the complaint on the part of the
                United States also. This was all they could do— I said the result however was that
                no satisfaction had been given to the United States. The Abbe finally concluded by
                saying that he wished me to answer his note so that he might make his report to his
                own Government— I told him there were some other subjects on which I should be glad
                to converse with him, and he said he would call at my house to-morrow— <persRef key="bagot-charles">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot</persRef>, and the <persRef ref="goupydequabeck-alexander">Viscount de Quabeck</persRef>, the new Chargé d’Affaires
                from the Netherlands sent notes requesting interviews; for which I appointed twelve
                and two O’Clock next Monday. On returning home to dinner, I found <persRef ref="bailey-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bailey</persRef>, and the <persRef ref="lavillehalio-courson">Chevalier Courson de la Villehalio</persRef>, Captain of the
                French Frigate la Duchesse de Berri, now at New-York. I found quite unexpectedly
                that this Officer was an old acquaintance—he reminded me of having seen me at the
                University of Cambridge, and of having with a party of French Officers dined with me
                at my <persRef ref="adams-john">father’s</persRef> house, in September 1788. he belonged to a French squadron then in
					        Boston harbour commanded by a <persRef ref="devintimille-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> de Vintimille</persRef>— I recollected
                the circumstance distinctly <pb type="ms" n="417"/>but not the person of M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Courson. He has mistaken also the year, which was 1788. He thinks it
                1787— I went after dinner with <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef> and we spent the
					        Evening at <persRef ref="frye-nathaniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Frye’s</persRef>.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-18">
					<head>18 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-18"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Recreation</note>
					    <note type="subject">Religion</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
					    <p><dateline>18. VI:15.</dateline> Morning call from <persRef ref="brent-daniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Daniel Brent</persRef>. There was an
					        advertisement in the newspapers that <persRef ref="hurley-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hurley</persRef> a celebrated
                preacher from Philadelphia, was to preach this morning at the Roman Catholic Church;
                and we went with M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Brent to hear him— But an apology was made
					        for him from indisposition, and <persRef ref="matthews-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Matthews</persRef> the regular priest,
                preached in his stead. Walked from the Church, with <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persRef> and
					        <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-ann">Madame de Neuville</persRef> and the <persRef ref="lavillehalio-courson">Chevalier Courson</persRef>, who paid a visit to <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript"
					            >rs</hi> Adams</persRef>— <persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</persRef> and <persRef ref="onis-clementina;heredia-narcissa">his daughters</persRef> came in soon
                after. They all arrived here yesterday—the de Neuville’s, from a visit to <persRef ref="madison-james">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Madison</persRef>, in Virginia—and the Onis’s from Baltimore. I had a
					        long visit also from <persRef ref="cardelli-pietro">Cardelli</persRef>, who is very anxious to take the President’s Bust; and
					        from the <persRef ref="correa-joseph">Abbè Correa</persRef>, who goes for Philadelphia to-morrow, to return at the end of
                the week— I walked an hour after dinner and was writing the remainder of the
                Evening.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-19">
					<head>19 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-19"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Bank of the United States</note>
					    <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
					    <note type="subject">South American Wars of Independence</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
					    <p><dateline>19. VI:</dateline> <persRef ref="scott-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Scott</persRef> the delegate from the Missouri territory came to
                enquire what was the result of a letter that he had written to me last week against
                the reappointment of <persRef ref="lucas-john">judge Lucas</persRef> as one of the judges of the territory. His
                commission he stated had expired, and he accuses him of being a man of violent
                temper and passions. I told Scott that his Letter should be laid before the
                <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef>; but he might think it a very harsh measure to omit the reappointment of
                judge Lucas; as under the circumstances it would be equivalent to a removal from
                office. I suggested also that as party Spirit in the Missouri territory was extreme,
                it would have the appearance of taking part in it, to withhold the reappointment
                unless there was some remonstrance against it from the People themselves— He said at
                all Events as the People would probably be authorised to form a Constitution as a
                State at the next Session of Congress, Lucas would not hold his Commission long, for
                when the People should once have the power of manifesting their opinion of Lucas, he
                had no doubt what it would be— Call at the President’s— He spoke again of the
                appointment of a Secretary of the Navy. Said he should offer it to <persRef ref="rodgers-john">Commodore Rogers</persRef>,
                who probably would decline accepting it. He had already declined it, when offered to
                him by <persRef ref="madison-james">President Madison</persRef>—and next to him, he thought he should offer it to the
					        Chief-Justice of New York <persRef ref="thompson-smith">Thompson</persRef>; whom he did not personally know—but whose
                reputation stood very high, and who was represented as having kept entirely aloof
                from all the intrigues of the New-York parties— I had mentioned to the President the
                late Governor of the State of Ohio, <persRef ref="worthington-thomas">Worthington</persRef>, as a suitable candidate from the
                Western Country, and as having once been a seafaring man— The President said he was
                not personally acquainted with him—but he had been mentioned to him as a man of
                indirect ways, upon whose steadiness no reliance was to be placed— He preferred men
                of a strait forward character. I observed to him this day that as the <persRef ref="tompkins-daniel">Vice-President</persRef>
                was from New-York, Pennsylvania might have the stronger claim to a member of the
                administration. He assented to the remark; but if Rodgers does not accept Thompson
                will be the man— The President said that for the temporary appointment, as <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun’s</persRef> Office was immediately opposite to that of the
                Secretary of the Navy, he had requested him to perform the duties in the short
                interval till the appointment. I had thought of recommending this arrangement
                myself. At the Office I had interviews with <persRef key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot</persRef>, and with
					        the <persRef ref="goupydequabeck-alexander">Viscount de Quabeck</persRef>, who came in while Bagot was with me. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                Bagot was appointed for, and came at twelve O’Clock. I had directed that two should
                be the hour appointed for the Viscount. One was by mistake the time fixed, and when
                he came he was admitted. It was however merely a visit of form; and he told me he
                could not apply to be presented to the President, until the arrival of his trunks
                from Philadelphia, which were coming round by water, and which contained his Uniform
                dress— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot told me that he came to redeem the pledge of
					        <persRef ref="castlereagh-robert">Lord Castlereagh’s</persRef> promise given last November; to communicate frankly what was
                doing by the European allies in relation to Spain and South America. That the only
                reason why this had not been <pb type="ms" n="418"/>done before, was because nothing had been
                matured; nothing agreed upon; nothing prepared even to an extent which was worth
                communicating—lately however some advance in the business had been made, and he had
                brought me several papers to read, of which he was not authorized to give or allow
                copies to be taken, but which were communicated in the most entire confidence. The
                first was a circular note, from Lord Castlereagh to the five allied Powers dated in
                August 1817. and founded upon the previous application from Spain, soliciting the
                mediation of the allies, between her and her Colonies— It proposes that they should
                undertake the Mediation, on condition that Spain should agree to three principles to
                form the basis of it 1. A general amnesty to the insurgents 2. That the South
                Americans should be admissible to Offices and honours equally with the Spaniards. 3.
                That the Colonies should enjoy a free commerce with other Nations; subject to
                certain suitable preferences in favour of Spain. This is the paper referred to in
                the Russian Answer of November; the original application from Spain for the
                Mediation does not yet appear. The next paper exhibited by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
					        Bagot was a Note from the <persRef ref="decarvajalvargas-joseph">Duke of San Carlos</persRef> the Spanish Ambassador, in England
                dated in June last— Accepting the bases proposed in the British Note, but couching
                the promise of commercial freedom in more indefinite terms and intimating an
                expectation that the allies would guarantee the issue of the Mediation. The first
                British Note had in the most explicit manner disclaimed every intention of resorting
                to force against the Colonies, in any event of the Negotiation— The reply from Lord
                Castlereagh to this Note of the Duke of San Carlos (which was also a circular, the
					        <persRef ref="nunez-fernan">Duke of Fernan-Nuñez</persRef>, having presented one of precisely the same tenour at Paris,
                which was there published, and is now circulating in all our Newspapers) after
                guarding against the Spanish insinuation of a guarantee, by repeating the firm
                determination, in no event whatever to employ force against the Colonies, calls upon
                Spain to speak out in explicit terms, and declare what she proposes in reference to
                the commercial freedom to be allowed to the Colonies after their return to her
                Government— With this Note is a copy of Lord Castlereagh’s despatch to Sir Henry
                Wellesley, the British Ambassador at Madrid, directing him to present it— The
                despatch is dated in August last, and intimates that towards the close of that
                Month, Lord Castlereagh, expected to go to the Congress of Sovereigns at Aix la
                Chapelle; instructing also <persRef ref="wellesley-henry">Sir Henry Wellesley</persRef> to urge the Spanish Government, to
                have a Plenipotentiary there with a plan fully prepared for the arrangement with the
                Colonies. This Congress at Aix La Chapelle has since been postponed to the last week
                in September— The Spanish Note of June last professes also the disposition of Spain
                to take such measures on the subject as her Allies may advise— I asked M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot, if Lord Castlereagh said anything to him of the
                Protests by the deputies from Buenos Ayres, and from New-Grenada, against the
                interference of the Allies—he said no. I asked him if he would allow me to take
                these papers to the President for his perusal, with my promise and word of honour
                that no copies should be taken, and that the papers should be immediately afterwards
                returned to him. He declined letting the papers go from him, but offered to go with
                me to the President’s, and remain there while he should be reading the papers. This
                sort of confidential distrust is usual with the British Government; and I once had a
                sample of it from <persRef ref="rumiantsev-nikolai">Count Romanzoff</persRef>. It is so grossly indelicate, that between
                individuals it could scarcely be viewed otherwise than as an insult. indeed
                Romanzoff’s caution went no further than to decline giving a copy of what he allowed
                me to read. The permission to read, with the refusal to allow papers to be taken for
                perusal out of the presence of the confiding party, is altogether English. I
                declined accepting M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagots offer, but requested him to present
                my thanks to Lord Castlereagh for this confidential communication. With regard to
                the expedient, proposed to be attempted by the allies, it was perhaps due to their
                political connections and engagements with Spain, but I thought it not likely to
                prove successful; nor could I imagine the British Government expected it would be
                successful. It was a step prepared in the descent from power, of Spain, to break her
                fall. It might be fair and just to Spain to give her the benefit of the experiment;
                but after its failure, as I thought it must undoubtedly fail, it would be equally
                fair and just to Spain to put an end to all her expectations, and to that horrible
                war she is carrying on, by recognizing the principal Independent South American
                Governments— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot assented entirely to these opinions. He
                left me after two O’Clock— <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford</persRef> had requested a meeting
                of the Commissioners of the sinking fund at two, at his office; but it was three
                before I got there; and <persRef ref="wirt-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wirt</persRef> the Attorney General immediately
                afterwards came in— It was a question upon a transaction with the Bank of the United
                States. They had given him notice that they should sell about 400,000 dollars of
                United States Stocks; being all that they have left, unless taken within fifteen
                days for Account of the United States. A Section of their Act of Incorporation
                restricts them from <pb type="ms" n="419"/>selling Stock in the United States, without giving
                this previous notice of fifteen days to the Secretary of the Treasury, that he may
                have the option of taking it for public account at certain rates below the present
                market price— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford said that from the present state of
                the Treasury, it would not be convenient to take the Stock; but there was another
                point upon which he had made up his mind, and upon which the Directors of the Bank
                differed from him— They had got the opinion of three Lawyers to support them; but he
                had last year compelled them to purchase near two Millions of Stock to replace as
                much which they had sold after notice given by him of his intention to redeem it.
                They had made the purchase at a cost of 54000 dollars— His position was this—that
                the Stock subscribed to the Bank of the United States, being made by the Act of
                incorporation, redeemable by them at their pleasure, although upon the face of it
                redeemable as Stock, only at certain periods; if it should be sold by the Bank to
                individuals it would still be redeemable at the pleasure of the United States, and
                upon the same terms as if it had remained in the possession of the Bank— Upon this
                point my opinion differed from that of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford. I considered
                the provisions in the Act of incorporation, not as changing the nature of the Stock,
                but merely as restrictions upon the Bank with regard to Sales— M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Wirt was undecided, but inclined to the opinion of M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Crawford. It was proposed that M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wirt should write
					        to take the opinion of <persRef ref="marshall-john">Chief Justice Marshall</persRef>. I urged M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                Crawford to waive the question by taking the whole of the stock for the public; but
                he was afraid of draining so much the Treasury. He finally resolved however to take
                the 3. per Cent Stocks of which there were about the amount of 90000 dollars, and
                which were the only portion of the whole, the redeemability of which, upon the terms
                prescribed to the Bank, it was of any import to the public to have retained— Morning
                and Evening employed in writing.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-20">
					<head>20 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-20"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Impressment</note>
					    <note type="subject">Slave Trade</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
						<p><dateline>20. VI:</dateline> At the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef>. He desired me to give notice to the other members of the
                administration, for a meeting at his house to-morrow at Noon; to consider of the
                case of <persRef ref="hall-unknown3">Captain Hall</persRef>; and also, of instructions to be given to Mess<hi rend="superscript"
                    >rs:</hi> <persRef ref="gallatin-albert">Gallatin</persRef> and <persRef ref="rush-richard">Rush</persRef>, upon the subject of certain proposals relating to
                impressment, and to measures for promoting the abolition of the Slave-trade— I
                reported to the President the Conversation I had yesterday with <persRef key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Bagot</persRef>, and his proposal to accompany me to the President’s house that he
                might have the opportunity to peruse the papers—he approved of my having declined
                this offer; and directed me to assure M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot that he was well
                satisfied with the communication as made to me, and received it as a friendly mark
                of confidence from the British Government— I called at <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                Calhoun’s</persRef> Office to give him the notice of the Meeting to-morrow. He asked me to
                have a warrant or Commission made out for him to perform the duties of Secretary of
                the Navy— On looking into the Precedents, and the Laws I found that although the
                President is authorised to assign for an interval of six Months the duties of the
                Secretaries of State, the Treasury and of War, to other Officers, yet that there is
                no such provision for the supplying a vacancy in the Navy Department, which was
                created, after the Law relating to the other Departments had been enacted. I
                mentioned this to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun, that the question might be taken
						    into consideration— I had a morning visit from <persRef ref="swift-joseph">General Swift</persRef>— Spent the Evening with
                    <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef>, and <persRef ref="hellen-mary">Mary Hellen</persRef>, at <persRef key="smith-william-steuben">W. S. Smith’s</persRef>.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-21">
					<head>21 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-21"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Dueling</note>
					    <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
					    <note type="subject">Impressment</note>
					    <note type="subject">Slave Trade</note>
					    <note type="subject">U.S. Constitution</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
					    <p><dateline>21. VI:</dateline> Somewhat unwell last Night, and all this day. Morning visits to the <persRef ref="goupydequabeck-alexander">Viscount
					        de Quabeck</persRef>, the Charge d’Affaires from the Netherlands with whom I found <persRef ref="bourqueney-francois">Bourqueney</persRef>,
					        and to the <persRef ref="lavillehalio-courson">Chevalier Courson</persRef>, who lodges at the <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">French Minister de Neuville’s</persRef>. I
					        asked Quabeck what news he had from <persRef ref="tencate-j">ten Cate</persRef> and his projected duel. He shewed me a
                Letter from him at New-York, complaining that he had been taken ill with a fever,
                and detained two or three days at Elizabeth-town, but had finally
                <pb type="ms" n="420"/>reached New-York, and was seeking for his man, to fight him; but had
                not been able to find him. He also desires Quabeck to apply to <persRef ref="wirt-william">M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Wirt</persRef> the Attorney General, and enquire how long a public Minister is
                allowed his privilege, after his recall; and says he thinks there is a law in this
                Country, allowing it for two Months— Quabeck said he thought the usual allowance in
                Europe was <hi rend="strikethrough">two Months</hi> six weeks— I told him I knew of
                no precise law upon the subject anywhere— I suppose the usage every where was a
                reasonable time; of the extent of which the judicial tribunals in every individual
                case would decide. Quabeck then told me the origin and progress, of ten Cate’s
                quarrel with <persRef ref="willink-unknown">Willink</persRef>, to its present Stage of an imminent duel. It began by an
                overdraft of ten Cate’s upon a Bank in Philadelphia—to refund which he gave a Bill
                of Exchange upon Amsterdam which came back protested— Willink then paid the Bill,
                and endorsed the payment, “for the honour of the Government of the Netherlands,” at
                which ten Cate took offence, and wrote Willink a Letter expressing his
                dissatisfaction. Willink answered by a Letter so violent and outrageous, that it was
                impossible ten Cate could avoid calling him to account for it— But he was afraid as
                ten Cate was enquiring how long his privilege continued, that he might be arrested
                for debt by Willink who yet holds the protested Bill of Exchange against him. I
                requested the Viscount to write immediately to ten Cate, dissuading him from the
                pursuit of his duel, on the very ground of his privilege, as his adversary having no
                privilege, it was impossible for them to meet upon equal terms. He promised me that
                he would write accordingly. I asked him if ten Cate had said any thing to him of a
                sum of money which he had borrowed of me, and for which he had given a draft upon
                the Minister of foreign affairs, the <persRef ref="nagell-unknown">Baron de Nagell</persRef>— He said no— I then told him
                the whole transaction, upon which he said he was sure it would finish the ruin of
                ten Cate; who certainly had no authority to draw upon the Baron de Nagell— That
                Minister he said “sautera haut comme cela” holding his hand two foot above the
                floor, when he should have the Bill presented to him; and he was very much afraid
                would not accept the Bill, until the circumstances under which it was given shall be
                explained to him— I told him that as M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> ten Cate’s pecuniary
                embarrassment was well known, when I took his Bill, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Everett,
                who was going out as our Charge d’Affaires to the Netherlands, had been instructed
                to give the proper explanations, to Baron Nagell, if they should be found necessary—
					        <persRef ref="everett-alexander">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Everett</persRef> was to have embarked immediately afterwards and
                was indeed the bearer of one of the Bills— He had however been detained by the
                private Circumstances of his family, but was now on the point of embarking— I told
                him that before I supplied ten Cate with the money I had required of him a written
                declaration that he had no reason to expect or believe that his Government would
                hesitate or decline to accept his Bill; which he had accordingly given. Quabeck said
                that if he wrote that to his Government, ten Cate’s case would be more completely
                irredeemable than it now is; but that he was already “en disgrace complette.” I said
                I should not wish to have the circumstances mentioned unless it should be necessary
                to account for my having furnished him the money. He said the sum 3000 dollars,
                amounted to nine Months of ten Cate’s Salary, and he knew he had been paid up to the
                last Stuiver, though he believed his Government were now satisfied that the Salary
                was insufficient— ten Cate had made himself very generally liked and esteemed here,
                and there had been no apparent extravagance in his expence’s— It was inconceivable
                how he had got himself into such a situation— I said finally that I had supplied him
                the money as much out of regard to his Government as to himself—there were several
                examples of its having been done to accommodate other foreign public agents; and I
                had advanced it, after consulting the only one of my colleagues who was here at the
                time— But as the money that I had advanced belonged to the public, I should in the
                end be personally responsible for it, if the Bill should not be paid— M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> ten Cate, to account for the largeness of the sum, which he
                had asked for, told me that he had orders from his Government to make certain
                purchases for them— He had even requested an addition of eight hundred dollars to
                the largest sum first mentioned by him, which I had declined to supply him. Quabeck
                said he had no doubt that when these explanations were given the money would be
                paid, but he had never heard a syllable of any order given by his Government to ten
                Cate, to make any purchases for them.— I called at M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> de
                Neuville’s and paid a visit to the Chevalier de Courson, whom we had invited to dine
                with us next Saturday; he is however obliged to leave the City for New-York
                to-morrow; and is going immediately to Martinique. I then Stopped at M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Wirts Office, and gave him notice of the meeting at the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef>
                house, which I had forgotten to do yesterday. He immediately went with me; and we
                found <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford</persRef> already at the President’s— <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Calhoun</persRef> came in a few minutes after us. There were three subjects upon
                which the President consulted us. 1. Respecting, instructions to be given to Mess<hi
                    rend="superscript">rs:</hi> <persRef ref="gallatin-albert">Gallatin</persRef> and <persRef ref="rush-richard">Rush</persRef>, relating to proposals from the British
                Government, on the subject <pb type="ms" n="421"/>of impressment, and of the abolition of the
					        Slave trade. 2. On the question whether <persRef ref="rodgers-john">Commodore Rogers</persRef>, to whom the President has
                offered the appointment of Secretary of the Navy, can be with propriety allowed to
                accept it, and at the same time retain his rank and Commission in the Navy. 3. On
                the proceedings of two Courts Martial, upon the case of <persRef ref="hall-unknown3">Captain Hall</persRef>— The first was
                postponed to a future day for the want of some despatches from M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Rush, which I am to look up. With regard to the second the unanimous
                opinion was that Commodore Rodgers ought not to hold the two Offices of Secretary of
                the Navy, and of Captain in the Service, together. The accumulation of permanent
                Offices in the same person being contrary to the Spirit of the Constitution, and to
                the disposition of the People— The case of Captain Hall involves several important
                principles, and was thoroughly discussed. He was tried last January by a Court
                Martial, at Baltimore, upon a charge by <persRef ref="clarke-satterlee">Major Satterlee Clark</persRef> of having cheated him
                at cards—playing Loo, all night long and till after daylight in the Morning— It was
                in evidence before the Court-Martial that both the parties were drunk—Clark,
                slightly, and Hall, so that he did not know what he was doing— The evidence as to
                the intention of cheating was therefore totally deficient—yet the Court-Martial
                found Hall guilty, and sentenced him to be cashiered. He offered evidence to his
                general character, for sobriety; and aversion to gaming, which the Court rejected—
                He offered evidence that there had been a quarrel between Clark and him the same
                night; to discredit his testimony— The Court rejected it— Under these Circumstances
                the President disapproved the Sentence of the Court; and directed a new trial, by
                another Court-Martial; which met at Plattsburg in June last— The 87<hi rend="superscript"
                    >th:</hi> Article of War, provides that no Officer shall be tried a second time,
					        for the same Offence— <persRef ref="storrow-samuel">Storrow</persRef> the judge Advocate before the second Court-Martial
                made a speech to convince them that they could not try or arraign Hall, because he
                had been tried once before— They decided accordingly, though Hall was ready and
                desirous to be tried, and even attempted to object against the judge Advocate on
                account of his opposition to the trial— They refused to arraign Hall, and adjourned
                the Court without day. The President thereupon took the written opinion of the
                Attorney General; which is that notwithstanding the 87<hi rend="superscript">th.
                </hi>Article of War, an Officer may be tried a second time, for his own <hi
                    rend="italic">benefit</hi>; after a conviction, though not after an acquittal—
                The question was, what should be done—whether to send back the case to the same
                second Court-Martial; with the written opinion of the Attorney-General; and a
                peremptory <hi rend="italic">order</hi> to them to try Hall—or to send it to a third
                Court-Martial; or to refer the subject at once to Congress for an explanatory Law. I
                found the opinion of all the administration fully made up; and had unfortunately
                only doubts to suggest in which no other member of the Administration participated.
                My doubts were 1. whether the decision of the second Court-Martial, was not well
                founded; and that they could in fact not legally try Hall. 2. Whether the order to
                try him was an ordinary Military order, which they were bound to obey without
                enquiring into its legality 3. Whether they were bound by an order from the
                Executive, relating to the nature of the Evidence which they must admit or reject.
                4. Whether the President can lawfully constitute one Court-Martial, as a Court of
                appeal from the decision of another. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun was so clear
                upon all these points, that he thought there was no room for any doubt. The
                President and Attorney General, had made up their Minds, with equal decision— M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford though occasionally a little staggered, could not
                raise doubts sufficient to support mine; so that I had really not stubbornness
                enough to persevere in them— I acquiesced in the alternative of sending back the
                case to the second Court Martial with the opinion of the Attorney General, which I
                told him, I thought controvertible— I suggested the question however whether it
                would be expedient to have the same judge Advocate, upon the reference back, and
                whether another could be appointed— Before the decision upon this point was taken,
                dinner was announced; the President having last Evening sent us invitations to
                remain and dine with him— There was no other company; but <persRef ref="monroe-elizabeth">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                    Monroe</persRef>, and a nephew of her’s, a young <persRef ref="gouverneur-samuel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gouverneur</persRef>— I came
                home early in the Evening, still somewhat unwell.</p>
					</div>
				</div>
    
    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-22">
        <head>22 October 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-10-22"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
        </bibl>
        
        <div type="docbody">
            <p><pb type="ms" n="422"/><dateline>22. V:30.</dateline> Employed the morning till breakfast in journalizing— I called
                upon <persRef ref="gibson-george">Col<hi rend="superscript">l:</hi> Gibson</persRef> who is at the head of the new Commissary’s
                department; to recommend to him for Clerks two persons—one <persRef ref="mitchel-john">John Mitchell</persRef> the late
                Consul at Martinique, and the other a <persRef ref="smith-john4">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John Smith</persRef>, who was
                last year strongly recommended to me, and who now calls on me to recommend him in my
                turn— I had already called yesterday at Col<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> Gibson’s lodgings,
                but he was then gone to the Race grounds; the last three days having been those of
                the Autumnal Washington Races— Gibson says that both Mitchell and Smith will be
                appointed Clerks in his Office— At the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> I mentioned the difficulty with
                regard to printing the Journal of the Convention, in its present incomplete
                condition. He advised me to write to <persRef ref="madison-james">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Madison</persRef> concerning it;
                which I did. <persRef ref="bulfinch-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bulfinch’s</persRef> eldest <persRef ref="bulfinch-thomas">Son</persRef>, who is reading Law with
                    <persRef ref="wirt-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wirt</persRef>, came to solicit patronage; to be employed as a
                clerk in one of the public Offices— I promised to speak to <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    Calhoun</persRef> in his favour— After dinner, I returned the visit of <persRef ref="johnson-henry">Judge H. Johnson</persRef> of
                Louisiana, at his lodgings.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-23">
					<head>23 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-23"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
					    <note type="subject">Privateering</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
						<p><dateline>23. VI:</dateline> The <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef> took a ride on Horseback to his house at Highland, near Aldie;
						    Loudoun County, Virginia. At the Office, I wrote a Letter to <persRef ref="poinsett-joel">J. R. Poinsett</persRef>, which
						    had been some time since directed by the President and answered the <persRef ref="correa-joseph">Abbè Correa’s</persRef>
                complaint against the fitting out of a vessel in the Patuxent to cruize against
                Portuguese subjects and property; and a Note, received from the <persRef ref="onis-luis">Spanish Minister
                Onis</persRef> informing me that he is ready to exchange the Ratifications of the Convention
                of 1802. but proposing as he has received new Instructions to make proposals for a
                further and definitive arrangement of all the differences between the two Countries,
                to postpone the exchange of Ratifications, until we can make the attempt to agree
                upon the more comprehensive adjustment of the subjects in discussion— <persRef ref="graham-john">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> John Graham</persRef> made the translation of this Note and sent it to
                me this day; upon which I answered it, agreeing to postpone the exchange of the
                Ratifications of the Convention, and inviting an immediate communication of M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis’s new proposals. <persRef ref="pleasonton-stephen">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Pleasonton</persRef> called
                at the Office, and brought me several papers of vindication, and of recommendation
                of <persRef ref="kirkpatrick-thomas">T. Kirkpatrick</persRef> late Consul of the United States at Malaga, who was displaced on
                account of his failure as a merchant, with heavy complaints against him by several
                Citizens of the United States— He now sends these testimonials in his favour, and
                desires to be informed of the reasons for which he was dismissed from Office— <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef> attended this Evening a Ball, at <persRef ref="peter-thomas">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                Thomas Peter’s</persRef> at Georgetown— I spent it at home, writing.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-24">
					<head>24 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-24"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Adams Family Relations</note>
					    <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
					    <note type="subject">Native Americans</note>
					    <note type="subject">Westward Exploration and Expansion/Westward Migration/Manifest Destiny</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
						<p><dateline>24. VI:</dateline> The morning was cold; and thereby abridged my writing. Going to my Office, I
						    met <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun</persRef> who asked me to enquire of <persRef key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                Bagot</persRef> whether he had any authority to agree to a temporary line between the British
                territories and ours to the Northwest; and said he was establishing a line of Posts
                in that direction to cover our frontier, and prevent the British traders from
                crossing the line to trade with the Indians within our boundaries. I called
                afterwards at Calhoun’s Office, where he shewed me upon the map, the positions where
                the new Posts are to be established— I was engaged all the remainder of the Morning,
                in reading over the despatches from <persRef ref="rush-richard">R. Rush</persRef>, received since I left the City in
                August— They lay open a field for much labour, and most assiduous industry to me.
                May I not be found wanting, to my duties, or to my Country! There was a Letter from
						    <persRef ref="welsh-harriet">Harriet Welsh</persRef> to my <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef> received, mentioning that my <persRef ref="adams-abigail">Mother</persRef> was unwell; and that
                she, Harriet was going out to pass some time at Quincy on that account— A Postscript
                stated that my <persRef ref="adams-george;adams-john2;adams-charles2">Sons</persRef> had just returned from Quincy, where they were doing well partly
                relieved me from the apprehensions excited by the Letter— We had a diplomatic
                company to dinner— <persRef ref="bagot-charles;bagot-mary">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Bagot</persRef> Messrs
						    <persRef ref="antrobus-gibbs">Antrobus</persRef>, <persRef ref="hughes-unknown2">Hughes</persRef>, <persRef ref="baker-anthony">Baker</persRef> and <persRef ref="crawford-william-harris">Crawford</persRef>. <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persRef> and <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-ann">M<hi rend="superscript"
						        >rs</hi> Hyde de Neuville</persRef>, and <persRef ref="bourqueney-francois">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bourqueney</persRef>, <persRef ref="onis-luis;onis-clementina">M<hi
						            rend="superscript">r</hi> and Miss de Onis</persRef>, <persRef ref="heredia-narcissa">Madame dè Heredia</persRef>, and Mess<hi rend="superscript"
						                >rs: </hi><persRef ref="pizarro-martinez">Pizarro-Martinez</persRef>, <persRef ref="laserna-mateo">la Serna</persRef> and <persRef ref="stoughton-francis">Stoughton</persRef>, the <persRef ref="goupydequabeck-alexander">Viscount de Quabeck</persRef>, and
						    <persRef ref="johnson-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Johnson</persRef>, the Senator from Louisiana— The <persRef ref="lavillehalio-courson">chevalier de
						        Courson</persRef>, left the City on Thursday— Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs. </hi><persRef ref="demun-unknown">de Mun</persRef> and <persRef ref="thierry-unknown
						            ">Thierry</persRef>
						    of the French, and <persRef ref="noeli-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Noëli</persRef> of the Spanish legations sent
						    excuses. <persRef ref="zamorana-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Zamorano</persRef> was absent— The party would have been
                agreeable, but that M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams <pb type="ms" n="423"/>was suffering all the
                time with a severe head-ache, and immediately after the company left us was very
                sick— Quabeck told me that he had received a letter from <persRef ref="tencate-j">ten Cate</persRef> at Philadelphia,
						    whither he had returned from New-York; and had not found <persRef ref="willink-unknown">Willink</persRef>— He has taken
                passage in a vessel bound to Antwerp, and is to embark immediately. I asked Quabeck
                to call at my office on Monday or Tuesday, and told him I would shew him my
                Correspondence with ten Cate relating to the advance of money made to him— He said
                he would call, but that he had already written to his Government mentioning the
                circumstances which I had stated to him. I asked M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot
                whether he had authority to agree to a temporary North western line: he said he had
                not— I told him that we were establishing a line of military Posts in the
                neighbourhood of <persRef ref="selkirk-thomas">Lord Selkirk’s</persRef> Settlements— He said he had heard so. He also spoke
                to me about the sum of money recovered in a district Court of the United States, by
                a Canadian British Subject, and with which the Clerk of the Court, <persRef ref="rudd-tharon">Tharon Rudd</persRef>,
                absconded— I could say nothing further on the subject than I had heretofore told
                him— He said he should write to me about it again.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-25">
					<head>25 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-25"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
					    <note type="subject">Recreation</note>
					    <note type="subject">Religion</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
						<p><dateline>25. VII:</dateline> <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef> continues quite unwell, and was confined the
                whole of this day to her bed. I attended again at the Roman Catholic Church, and
                heard <persRef ref="hurley-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hurley</persRef> preach. His text was Psalms 118.24. “This is
                the day which the Lord hath made: let us rejoice and be glad therein.” He spoke
                without Notes; but with great fluency and elegant language— His theme was the
                institution of the Sabbath— There was little reasoning in his discourse, and not
                much learning. But there was some pleasing declamation upon the power and the
                goodness of God, and some sober doctrine upon the duty of keeping the Sabbath day
                holy. His text might have justified a Roman Catholic preacher, in urging that
                innocent pleasures and amusements are not incompatible with the sanctity of the day;
                but he drew no such doctrine from it— On the contrary he censured severely those who
                are in the habit of devoting the day to frivolous diversions. The Roman Catholics in
                this Country keep the Sunday with as much gravity as any protestant sect— M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Hurley who is a very handsome man, appeared somewhat too
                studious of his attire; and there was too much vehemence in his manner, for the
                temperate character of his text— Immediately after he had finished his Sermon he
                went into the vestry, stripped off his Stole and Surplice, and passed again through
                the church and went away, while the ordinary Priest, <persRef ref="matthews-william">Matthews</persRef>, was in the midst of
                the service administering the Communion— When I returned home from Church I found
                that <persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</persRef> had left two Notes at my house; one containing
                complaints respecting the Government of Amelia Island, and the other with
                propositions for the Negotiation of a Treaty— This second is a note of 18 pages,
                containing a History of the Spanish Settlements in Mexico over again— I had a
                Morning visit from <persRef ref="middleton-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Middleton</persRef>, who appears to be mortified at
                the issue of the Election for the next Congress at Charleston; the district now
                represented by him. He told me that <persRef ref="clay-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Clay</persRef>, the Speaker was now
						    here; going on, to-morrow, for Boston. <persRef ref="cardelli-pietro">Cardelli</persRef> was here and brought the bust; but I
                did not see him. I took a solitary walk of two hours before dinner; and wore out the
                Evening as I had the morning in reading the newspapers— So that I wrote nothing the
                whole day.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-26">
					<head>26 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-26"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Adams Family Relations</note>
					    <note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
					    
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
						<p><dateline>26. V:30.</dateline> Resumed partially the writing of Morn and Eve; which has absorbed so much
						    of my time since my return home— Calling at the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef>, I found <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Calhoun</persRef> there. The President returned last Evening from his ride to
						    Highland. I read to him the Propositions contained in the Note of <persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Onis</persRef>; with which he was much dissatisfied; considering them not only as
                altogether inadmissible, but as merely another experiment upon the Patience and long
                suffering of this Government. He said it was time to bring Onis to a point, and if
                he would not agree to reasonable terms to break off the Negotiation. I afterwards
                gave the Propositions to <persRef ref="graham-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John Graham</persRef> for a translation. The
						    President told me that <persRef ref="rodgers-john">Commodore Rodgers</persRef> had declined the appointment of Secretary
                of the Navy; preferring his present station as President <pb type="ms" n="424"/>of the Navy
                Board; with which he retains his rank as a Captain in the Navy— The President said
                he should now determine to offer the place, either to <persRef ref="snyder-simon">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Snyder</persRef>,
						    or to the Chief Justice of New-York; <persRef ref="thompson-smith">Thompson</persRef>: as he appeared to incline strongly in
                favour of the latter, I presented to him all the considerations which operate in
                favour of the other— He said he would determine in the course of the day— There was
                a Letter came from my Son <persRef ref="adams-john2">John</persRef> to my <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef> dated the 22<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> and
						    saying that <persRef ref="adams-abigail">my Mother</persRef> was very dangerously ill. My wife was so much recovered, as to
                be with us at dinner— I wrote all the Evening.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-27">
					<head>27 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-27"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Adams Family Relations</note>
					    <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
					    <note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
					    <p><dateline>27. VI:30.</dateline> At the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef>. He was desirous of having the reply to <persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Onis’s</persRef> Propositions, prepared, and presented for Consideration at a
					        Cabinet Meeting this day; but that was impossible— <persRef ref="graham-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John
					            Graham</persRef> brought me the translation; and told me that <persRef ref="pleasonton-stephen">Pleasonton</persRef> had informed him <persRef ref="rodney-caesar">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Rodney</persRef> had been prevented from coming to Washington, by a fit
                of the fever and ague; but that he would be here this day or to-morrow. I called at
					        <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun’s</persRef> Office; as he is now acting as Secretary of the
                Navy; to enquire if there was a frigate or Sloop of War, which can be sent to the
                Havanna to demand the liberation of a number of Americans now in confinement
                there—among whom is a <persRef ref="robinson-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> William Davis Robinson</persRef>. He has made
                many applications for the interference of this Government to obtain his release; and
                since my return here <persRef ref="fairfax-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Fairfax</persRef>, and young <persRef ref="mitchel-unknown">Mitchell</persRef> have been to
                me, time after time with the same request— It was concluded to send the John Adams,
                now at New-York, and which <persRef ref="homans-benjamin">Homans</persRef> says will be ready, by the first week in December.
					        I obtained a warrant for the <persRef ref="gay-charles">Son</persRef> of <persRef ref="gay-ebenezer">Eben<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Gay</persRef> of Hingham, as
					        Midshipman; to go in her; as he had requested me by Letter to do. The <persRef ref="goupydequabeck-alexander">Viscount de
					            Quabeck</persRef> called upon me at two O’Clock, and I shewed him my Correspondence with <persRef ref="tencate-j">ten
                Cate</persRef>, on the Subject of the advance of money which I made to him. He says that the
                more he hears of ten Cate’s affairs, the worse they appear; and he shewed me a
                Letter from <persRef ref="zimmerman-unknown">Zimmermann</persRef> the Dutch commercial Agent at New-York stating that when he
                left that City there were two or three Writs out against him to arrest him there;
                and that he would be exposed to as many at Philadelphia— He said that the vessel in
                which ten Cate had taken his passage for Antwerp, cleared out on the 22<hi
                    rend="superscript">d.</hi> or 23<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> and he hoped was now gone—
                Quabeck told me that among the visits that he had paid when he was here before were
                two to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun and <persRef ref="wirt-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wirt</persRef>; and as they
                were the only ones that had not been returned he did not know, whether those
                gentlemen knew of his visits; and he enquired whether it would be proper for him to
                pay them visits again. I told him I thought not— But I would ascertain whether those
                Gentlemen had received his Cards, and would let him know— <persRef ref="lear-benjamin">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    Lear</persRef> came to me with a young Spaniard named <persRef ref="ealo-f">F. X. de Ealo</persRef>, to solicit the
                appointment of American Consul at Bilboa; and he brought several recommendatory
                Certificates— <persRef ref="scott-alexander">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Alexander Scott</persRef> of Georgetown, came, with
					        Letters of introduction, from <persRef ref="pope-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John Pope</persRef> of Kentucky, and from
					        <persRef ref="mason-john">General Mason</persRef> of Georgetown. Two Letters from <persRef ref="welsh-harriet">Harriet Welsh</persRef> to my <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef> were
                received; both written at Quincy last Thursday. My ever dear and most affectionate
                <persRef ref="adams-abigail">Mother</persRef>, was lying, with a bilious fever, and almost without hope of her recovery.
                The second Letter written in the Evening gives a glimpse of encouragement. God
                almighty grant that she may survive, and be restored to perfect health. I wrote all
                this Evening, and redeemed the arrears of this Journal.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-28">
					<head>28 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-28"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Adams Family Finances</note>
					    <note type="subject">Adams Family Relations</note>
					    <note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
					    <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
					    <note type="subject">Recreation</note>
					    <note type="subject">Treaty of Ghent</note>
					    <note type="subject">War of 1812</note>
					    <note type="subject">Westward Exploration and Expansion/Westward Migration/Manifest Destiny</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
						<p><dateline>28. V:</dateline> Finished the draft of a Note in answer to <persRef ref="onis-luis">Onis’s</persRef> Propositions. Took it to the
                <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> who directed a meeting of the members of the administration at his house
						    at one O’Clock. At the Office, I was visited, by a M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                <hi rend="strikethrough">Alexander Scott of Georgetown, who brought me Letters of
						    recommendation</hi> <persRef ref="hoyt-samuel">Hoyt</persRef>, who was introduced to me by <persRef ref="bailey-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                Bailey</persRef>; originally a Bostonian, now settled at Marietta, in the State of Ohio, where
                he is Postmaster; and about to remove to Gibson in the State of Mississippi, where
                he is to have the same Office. <persRef ref="porter-david">Commodore Porter</persRef> mentioned to me a claim of his upon
                the Government of Chili, for a prize vessel taken by him during the late War, and
                taken from him by them. He wished that <persRef ref="downes-john">Captain Downe</persRef> of the Macedonian who is going
                into the South Sea might be instructed to prosecute this demand for him— It was past
                one O’Clock when I was going to the President’s, but was detained half an hour by
                    <persRef key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot</persRef>, who came in much agitated with a letter which he
						    had just received from <persRef ref="barclay-thomas">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Barclay</persRef>, the British Commissioner
                under the fifth Article of the Treaty of Ghent. It appears that in running their
                    45<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>parallel Latitude, they find by the observations of
                the Astronomers on both sides, that the existing line touching upon Lake Champlain,
                is <pb type="ms" n="425"/>about three quarters of a Mile too far North, and that the new line
						    will bring two Forts, lately built by us, within the British Territory. <persRef ref="hassler-ferdinand">Hassler</persRef>, the
                American Astronomer, is so much alarmed at this result, that he is afraid there will
                be a riot among the people there to overthrow the forts and break all their
                instruments; and to prevent them from proceeding upon their business. He
                communicated his terror to <persRef ref="tiack-unknown">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Tyack</persRef>, the British Astronomer
                (they are both Germans) and he to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Barclay the British
                Commissioner, who wrote off immediately to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot, requesting
                him to apply for a reinforcement of troops for their protection. I told Bagot I
                thought it was nothing but a maggot in the brain of Hassler, and that there was no
                danger whatever. But I promised to mention it to the President, and inform him of
                the result— I found <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">Crawford</persRef> and <persRef ref="calhoun-john">Calhoun</persRef> with the President, and told him of M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot’s communication— Notice of the fact that the
                Astronomical Observations are likely to deprive us of our two new forts had been
                received yesterday; from <persRef ref="totten-joseph">Col<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> Totten</persRef>, by a Letter from Hassler,
                but the President and Calhoun laughed at the idea of the apprehended rebellion
                against the Astronomers in Vermont. We passed to the consideration of the reply to
                Onis’s Propositions— The President himself inclined to make it merely a verbal
                communication, and to give no written answer unless Onis would declare that he was
                authorized to conclude a Treaty upon our ultimatum— It was however finally agreed
                that it should be in writing— I read Onis’s propositions and my draft of an answer
                to them. several alterations were proposed—one to the boundary line that I had drawn
                up—Crawford wanted instead of the red river, the chain of mountains to the South of
                it— A blank was to be filled for the time after which the grants of Land are to be
                held null and void— 1802. 1805. 1808 and 1811. were successively mentioned and
                discussed without coming to any decision. But the great difficulty was with regard
                to the reunciations of claims for indemnities— It was concluded that some exceptions
                must be reserved, and I was directed to prepare an additional paragraph to that
                effect— Meeting adjourned about four. I received a Letter from <persRef ref="waterhouse-benjamin">D<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Waterhouse</persRef> of the 21<hi rend="superscript">st: </hi>and one to my <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef> from
						    <persRef ref="welsh-harriet">Harriet Welsh</persRef> of the 23<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> concerning my beloved <persRef ref="adams-abigail">Mother</persRef>. The
                first very discouraging— Harriet’s more cheering, and I fervently pray, of truer
                forecast. I had also a Letter from <persRef ref="everett-alexander">A. H. Everett</persRef>, with Bills, discharging his debt
                to me. Took half an hours walk alone after dinner; and spent the remainder of the
                Evening in writing.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-29">
					<head>29 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-29"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Adams Family Finances</note>
					    <note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
					    <note type="subject">Bank of the United States</note>
					    <note type="subject">Commerce</note>
					    <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
					    <note type="subject">Impressment</note>
					    <note type="subject">Recreation</note>
					    <note type="subject">Slave Trade</note>
					    <note type="subject">War of 1812</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
						<p><dateline>29. VI:</dateline> Called at the Branch Bank, with three Bills of the Boston Branch which they
						    declined taking; but <persRef ref="smith-richard">Smith</persRef> the Cashier took them, and said I should be credited for
						    them to-morrow. <persRef ref="davidson-james2">Davidson</persRef> the teller hinted to me that Smith would obtain a premium
                upon them of at least one per Cent, and pocket it himself. At the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef>—I had
                prepared an additional paragraph for my Letter to <persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</persRef>, but
                it did not yet altogether suit the President’s views— He told me that he now thought
                it of much less consequence than it was a year ago, whether we made any adjustment
                with Spain at all— And that he thought Onis’s instructions now were such that he
                would either sign no Treaty at all; or he would sign one upon our own terms. I left
                my draft with him. He has begun that of his Message, and read me two paragraphs, one
                respecting the commercial Negotiation, now on foot with England— The other
                concerning our relations with Spain. The latter was unfinished. He directed a
                Cabinet Meeting at one O’Clock, upon the Instructions to be given to Mess<hi
                    rend="superscript">rs: </hi><persRef ref="gallatin-albert">Gallatin</persRef> and <persRef ref="rush-richard">Rush</persRef>, concerning Impressment and the Slave
                trade. At one we met accordingly, and discussed the question upon impressment till
                four without coming to any decision. Another Meeting was appointed for twelve
                O’Clock to-morrow. Rush according to his Instructions made two successive proposals
                to the British Government, upon impressment— One the 18<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>of
                April, and the other the 30<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>of June last. The first was to
                restrict reciprocally the naturalization of Sailors; the other was totally to
                exclude each other’s Seamen, from the respective Services whether in public or in
                merchant <pb type="ms" n="426"/>vessels—with a positive stipulation against the impressment of
                men in any case. The British Government in the first instance rejected both; but
                afterwards on the 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of August <persRef ref="castlereagh-robert">Castlereagh</persRef> intimated to Rush,
                as a suggestion of his own, upon which he had not consulted the other members of the
                Cabinet, that the second proposition might be accepted with two Modifications; one
                that either party may withdraw from the engagement of the stipulation after three or
                six Months notice, as in the agreement concerning armaments on the Lakes— The other,
                that if a British Officer after entering an American Vessel for purposes admitted to
                be lawful, should find a Seaman there whom he should suspect to be English, he
                should be authorized to make a record or procès verbal of that fact that it may be
                brought to the knowledge of the American Government, though not to take the man. The
                deliberation of this day was whether Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs. </hi>Gallatin and Rush,
                should be instructed to agree to these modifications or not. Strong objections were
                urged against them both, particularly by <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Calhoun</persRef>— <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford</persRef> inclined to accede to them both; and the President
                inclined to the same. <persRef ref="wirt-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wirt</persRef> without expressing himself very
                decidedly, thought like the President— My own greatest objections were against the
                proposal as made by ourselves; to which I have always been utterly averse—thinking
                it an illiberal engagement—contrary to the free, generous and humane character of
                our institutions, unjustly restrictive upon the rights both of our own and of
                British Seamen, and having a tendency to excite the most violent animosities in
                their minds against one another and especially among the British Seamen against us—
                I thought it would be now peculiarly offensive and injurious to our commercial
                interests—doubted whether any such stipulation would be ratified by the Senate; was
                confident it would give universal dissatisfaction to the merchants, and in the Event
                of War, would be found impracticable in execution—as however we have made the
                proposal, we must abide by it, if accepted; but its own character may justly make us
                scrupulous against accepting any modifications which render it still more
                unexceptionable— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun opposed the first of Lord
                Castlereagh’s suggested modifications as leaving it in the power of the British
                Government, to make the stipulation itself nugatory to us, at the very moment, when
                it would begin to operate in our favour; and because by consenting that the compact
                should thus be cancelled at pleasure, we should be understood to have given an
                indirect assent to the resumption of the British practice. I concurred in this
                opinion which was strenuously contested by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford and M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Wirt, the President leaning a little the same way. M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford contended that the only object of these modifications
                on the part of the British Ministers was to make the stipulation itself palatable to
                their own people. That no British Ministers would dare to contract such an
                engagement, without reserving to themselves some such apology to conciliate the
                public opinion of their own Country— But that if the agreement should once be made
                they would never use the privilege of giving notice that it should be cancelled. The
                practice being once abandoned they would never incur the risk of resuming it— M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun was also against acceding to the second proposed
                modification, which would allow a British Officer to muster and pass under
                inspection the crew of every American vessel boarded by him— It would give rise to
                altercations, and expose the American Master to the insolence of the British
                Officer, scarcely less galling than the injury of impressment itself. Calhoun added
                that the result of the late War had been to raise the tone of feeling in this
                Nation— That the success of the menacing attitude assumed with Spain, in the case of
						    <persRef ref="meade-richard">R. W. Meade</persRef> had raised it still higher. That any concession by the Administration,
                which should tend to lower that tone of feeling, would give great dissatisfaction to
                the Nation, and would be used as a weapon against the Administration— Crawford said
                he had mentioned the proposed modifications to <persRef ref="clay-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Clay</persRef> last
                Saturday, and he thought well of them— Aye, said Calhoun; but what will the
                Kentucky, and western Country newspapers say of them? — This question occasioned a
                general laugh, in which Crawford, heartily <pb type="ms" n="427"/>joined. We all knew that
                Clay would think well of any thing, which might excite dissatisfaction with the
                Administration. It was past four O’Clock when the meeting was adjourned till
                to-morrow. Calhoun took me home in his Carriage; and I walked half an hour before
                dinner. <persRef ref="hellen-johnson">Johnson Hellen</persRef> came to spend some days with us. I wasted the Evening, by an
                invincible drowsiness and repugnance to writing. I got over it between nine and ten,
                and wrote about half an hour.</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-30">
					<head>30 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-30"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Adams Family Finances</note>
					    <note type="subject">Adams Family Relations</note>
					    <note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
					    <note type="subject">Anglo-American Treaty of 1818</note>
					    <note type="subject">Bank of the United States</note>
					    <note type="subject">Commerce</note>
					    <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
					    <note type="subject">Impressment</note>
					    <note type="subject">Slave Trade</note>
					    <note type="subject">U.S. Constitution</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
						<p><dateline>30. VI:</dateline> I called again at the Bank of the United States, (Branch) where the amount of
						    the Bills which I presented yesterday was entered to my credit; <persRef ref="davidson-james2">Davidson</persRef> the teller
						    repeating the hint he had given me yesterday. I received however from <persRef ref="cruft-edward">Edward Cruft</persRef>
                at Boston a Letter enclosing two drafts, making the precise amount of the credit I
                had at the Branch Bank Boston, without any premium or advance. I was only a few
                minutes at my Office— The adjourned Cabinet Meeting was held at the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> from
                Noon till four, and resumed after dinner till nine in the Evening— We all dined
                there except <persRef ref="wirt-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wirt</persRef>, who at dinner time went home, and did not
						    return in the Evening. The question upon <persRef ref="castlereagh-robert">Lord Castlereagh’s</persRef> proposed modifications
                to our proposal for abolishing impressment from our vessels on high seas, was again
                resumed, and argued with much earnestness. <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">Crawford</persRef> and Wirt adhering to their
                opinions; <persRef ref="calhoun-john">Calhoun</persRef> and I to ours— The President, ultimately found a middle term upon
                which he concluded after expressing his regret that he was obliged to decide between
                us, equally divided in opinion as we were— He determined to reject the second
                modification; first because it implied that the boarding Officer should have the
                power of mustering the crew of the American vessel and passing them individually
                under his inspection; and secondly because it implied a suspicion that we should not
                faithfully and sincerely carry our own Laws into execution. He would do nothing to
                countenance such a distrust. He also should decline acceding to the proposal that
                the whole agreement might be cancelled, at the option of either party, giving three
                or six Months notice; but would offer to limit the duration of the Article to a
                shorter period than the remainder of the Convention— For he was convinced that if
                the British Government once brought themselves to contract the engagement, not to
                take men from our ships, though it should be only for a year, they would never
                resort to the practice again— They had never before yielded so far, as in this
                proposal. They had until now been inflexible in adherence to the principle of their
                pretended right to take men from our ships, and it would be the whole point gained
                on our part, if we should once obtain though for ever so short a time an abandonment
                by them of the principle. It would come too so soon after the conclusion of the late
                War, that in the opinion of our people it would be considered as having resulted
                from it. There was a deep anxiety in their minds, from an apprehension that it would
                again give rise to War. The British Ministry could in fact not abandon their
                pretended right without some reservation to conciliate the pride, the interest and
                the feelings of their nation to the sacrifice— I then suggested the expediency of
                proposing that it should be concluded as a separate Article, to be acted upon by our
                Senate distinctly from the remainder of the Convention, which I thought would itself
                meet with much difficulty in passing through the Senate, unless there should be
                additional Articles, admitting us to the West India trade— I had found upon
                conversation with <persRef ref="king-rufus">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> King</persRef> when I passed through New-York, that
                he was averse to the renewal of the Convention in its present form; and his
                influence in the Senate was so considerable, and his knowledge upon commercial
                subjects so extensive that I thought his opposition alone would operate strongly
                against the Ratification— The stipulation to exclude all British Seamen from our
                ships, which would have an immediate and certain injurious effect upon our commerce,
                for the distant, possible, but very uncertain boon of exemption from impressment in
                the next maritime War, in which Great-Britain shall be engaged, and we neutral, will
                be so far from satisfying our people, <pb type="ms" n="428"/>that the general impression will
                be that we have been overreached in Negotiation, and probably the ratification in
                the Senate will fail. The President readily agreed that the stipulation if agreed to
                should be by a separate Article; and directed that the limitation of its duration to
                be proposed should be four years— And to avoid the immediate shock to our Commerce
                by the exclusion of British Seamen from our service, that it should commence from
                the first of October 1820.— The next subject taken up, was the proposal from Lord
                Castlereagh, that we should join in the measures recently concerted by Treaties
                concluded with Spain Portugal and the Netherlands for abolishing the Slave trade—
                The general character of these Treaties is, that the commanders of armed vessels of
                each of those Nations, should be authorized to enter and search the merchant vessels
                of the other, for slaves and when they find any, to carry the vessel into the
                nearest settlement of either of the two Nations, where they shall be tried by a
                mixed Court, consisting of a judge from each of the two Nations and two Arbitrators
                also one from each Nation, one of whom to be drawn by lot in each case upon which
                the two judges should be of different opinions— These mixed Courts to be authorized
                to condemn all slave-trading vessels of either of the two Nations, according to the
                penalties of their respective Laws— In the Treaty with the Netherlands there are
                some limitations, as to the Seas where this right of search in time of Peace is to
                be exercised, but there is one Article formally admitting that vessels under convoy
                may be searched as well as others. Lord Castlereagh by a Note to <persRef ref="rush-richard">M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Rush</persRef> communicates copies of these Treaties, inviting the United States,
                to join in similar stipulations and expressing the conviction, that the abolition of
                the Slave-trade cannot be effectually accomplished, but by granting this power to
                the Officers of one Nation, to enter and search the merchant-vessels of another. The
                opinion was unanimous, that this proposal ought not to be acceded to 1. M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Wirt thought there was no Constitutional authority, in the
                Government of the United States, to establish a Court partly consisting of
                foreigners, to sit without the bounds of the United States; and not amenable to
                impeachment, for corruption. and he cited the Constitution Article 3. Sec: l. I
                thought there was sufficient authority by the Constitution, and likened it to the
                joint Commissions which we have had by Treaties with G. Britain and Spain; and to
                the Courts of Admiralty which it has been proposed to establish at Naples, if we
                could have obtained the consent of that Government. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wirt
                pointed out distinctions between the two cases—between Courts constituted under the
                laws of Nations, and Courts to carry into effect our municipal and penal Statutes.
                But as the power of making Treaties, is without limitation in the Constitution, and
                Treaties are declared to be the Supreme Law of the Land I still hold to the opinion
                that there is no Constitutional difficulty in the way. 2. Another objection was that
                we could not establish these Courts with reciprocity, as we have no possessions on
                the Coast of Africa. 3. That we have suffered so much from the practice of foreign
                Officers to search our vessels in time of War, particularly by its connection with a
                British doctrine that after an Officer has entered for one purpose he may proceed to
                search for another, that we ought to be specially cautious not to admit of the right
                of search in time of peace. 4. That it is still more obnoxious, as coupled with the
                provision that even vessels under convoy, shall be subjected to it.— But in
                declining the proposition the President directed that an offer should be made to
                stipulate in general terms that further Laws should be made, if it should be found
                necessary for carrying into effectual execution those already enacted for the
                prohibition of the traffic by our Citizens—and that a copy of the act of Congress of
                the last Session to that effect should be communicated to the British Government—
                Upon these general ideas I was directed to draw up a Letter of Instructions, and it
                was suggested that we should also promise that Instructions shall be given to the
                Commanders of all our armed vessels to take and bring in for trial, any
                Slave-trading vessel under our flag, which they shall meet with upon the high Seas—
                But upon question made, it did not appear that the President is now authorized to
                give such orders, though he was by the Act of 1807. Finally we recurred to the reply
                to be given to <persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis’s</persRef> last proposals for a Treaty— What
                claims of the Citizens of the United States, should we undertake to assume? how
                should they be limited? Should the lands in the territories to be ceded, be pledged
                as the fund from which the payment of the claims shall be made, or shall they be
                generally assumed to a specified <pb type="ms" n="429"/>amount? To ascertain the validity of
                the claims and their amount, should a Commission be instituted joint American and
                Spanish; or American alone, the United States giving a discharge in full to Spain
                for all the claims? These questions were all amply discussed, and I was directed to
                make a further addition to my draft of a Note to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis— It was
                resolved to give a discharge for all claims which have been till the date of the
                Treaty presented at the department of State, or to the <persRef ref="erving-george">American Minister in Spain</persRef>—
                That the United States will pay them to the amount of five Millions of Dollars; and
                that a Commission shall be appointed, of three persons, all American, to pass, upon
                the claims— About nine in the Evening the meeting finished, and we walked home— I
                had received by the Mail two Letters relating to the state of my dear <persRef ref="adams-abigail">Mother</persRef>, both
						    dated last Monday— One from <persRef ref="welsh-harriet">Harriet Welsh</persRef>—only three lines; closing with “We have
						    yet hopes— Another Letter on Wednesday”— The other from <persRef ref="degrand-peter">De Grand</persRef>; who had been out
                to Quincy the day before— He says, [“]your Mother is quite sick—your venerable
						    <persRef ref="adams-john">father</persRef> bears it with a considerable degree of fortitude”— These are ominous words— I
                am endeavouring to prepare my mind for submission to the divine Will— Might this
                cup, Oh! God, but pass from me!—</p>
            
</div>
</div>

				<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-31">
					<head>31 October 1818</head>
					<bibl>
						<author>JQA</author>
						<date type="creation" when="1818-10-31"/>
						<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
					    <note type="subject">Adams Family Finances</note>
					    <note type="subject">Adams Family Relations</note>
					    <note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
					    <note type="subject">Privateering</note>
					    <note type="subject">Recreation</note>
					</bibl>

					<div type="docbody">
						
					    <p><dateline>31. VI:15.</dateline> <persRef ref="brent-daniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Daniel Brent</persRef> was here this morning; and a man who
					        calls himself <persRef ref="estifano-joseph">Estifano</persRef>, Captain of a privateer under a Commission of Buenos-Ayres,
                called the General San Martin; but by his Speech he is evidently an American of our
                own Country. His crew ran away with his vessel from a West-India Island, and took
                her into Savannah, where she was seized and libell’d in the Admiralty Court at his
                own request; he now wants her released, and had written me two Letters to that
                effect— He came this morning, first to my house, and afterwards to the Office; I
                found upon enquiry that the order for the seizure of the vessel had been sent from
                the Treasury, and to that Department referred M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Estifano— I was
                at the Metropolis Bank, filled up my Stock there, and took a Certificate for it as
                filled up. At the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> and read to him the additional paragraphs that I had
                prepared in the draft of my Letter to <persRef ref="onis-luis">Onis</persRef>, according to the determinations of last
                Evening— I had mistaken one of the points, and after calling upon <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Calhoun</persRef>, whose recollection agreed with that of the President, I struck
                it out. I gave the draft then to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Brent to be copied off this
                Evening if possible and sent to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis. The President read me a
					        paper he is preparing to send to <persRef ref="hall-unknown3">Captain Hall’s</persRef> second Court Martial, together with
                the opinion of the <persRef ref="wirt-william">Attorney General</persRef>— He assigns various reasons for disapproving
                their decision, and the first is that the order to try Hall was a military order,
                which the Court were bound to obey, and they were not competent to disclaim their
                own jurisdiction. Another that the trial by the first Court-Martial, having been
                disapproved by the President was no trial at all: and therefore that the reference
                to the second Court Martial, was not trying him a second time for the same offence—
                I remarked to the President that <persRef ref="storrow-samuel">Storrow</persRef> in his Speech to the second Court-Martial,
                and that Court itself had assumed the direct contrary to this first reason, as a
                principle—namely that the judicial character of a Court-Martial, necessarily
                absolves its members quo-adhoc from the military principle of unqualified obedience—
                The abstract argument, and the argument of analogy from the powers of other judicial
                Courts, seemed to be with them— If there was express authority on the other side, it
                would be decisive— I was not sufficiently versed in the writers upon Court-Martials
                to know how it was. He said he thought it was a rule settled by express authority as
                well as by general practice; but he did not recollect any particular case in which
                it was settled— I said as to the other reason, the difficulty appeared to me to
                be—that if a sentence of conviction, when disapproved by the President was no trial
                at all, I could not see how a sentence of acquittal, if disapproved should be a
                trial— The argument of nullity applies as much to an acquittal disapproved as to a
                conviction disapproved; and if to an acquittal, then the 87<hi rend="superscript">th.
                </hi>Article of War is so far nugatory that an Officer might be acquitted ten times
                over by as many <pb type="ms" n="430"/>successive Courts-Martial, and yet be said never to
                have had any trial at all. The President said that in practice, a sentence of
                acquittal is never disapproved; and if the President should abuse his power for the
                oppression of any individual he would be impeachable for it— I said that perhaps it
                would be more prudent to avoid the collision with the pride and temper of Officers
                whose opinions were already committed, to send the case to a third Court Martial,
                different from either of the others, and if they should ultimately take the same
                ground as the last, it might be referred to Congress for an amendment, or
                explanation of the Law— He said he would consider whether he should not do that at
                once; or if not, whether he should not institute a special board of Officers to
                report upon the questions— I told him there could be no possible doubt of the
                purity, humanity and equity of the motives, which had dictated the course pursued in
                this individual case. But the principles involved in it were important and serious.
                I disapproved the tone and Spirit of Storrow’s speech; but I separated them from the
                argument in it; and I thought it desirable to pursue a course which should avoid
                such a collision with the Officers of the Court as would drive them to resign; or
                make it necessary to break them— He said he wished much to avoid that collision; as
                he had a good opinion of the Officers; particularly of <persRef ref="eustis-unknown">Eustis</persRef> and <persRef ref="atkinson-henry">Atkinson</persRef> with whom
                he was personally acquainted— But something must be done for Hall, who though a
                hightempered and violent man had behaved very well during the War—had been strongly
                recommended by <persRef ref="gaines-edmund">General Gaine’s</persRef>, and was thought to have been persecuted by the
					        partizans of <persRef ref="brown-jacob">General Brown</persRef> in the Army, because he had been an Aid de Camp of
					        <persRef ref="ripley-eleazer">Ripley’s</persRef>— I staid this day, but a short time at the Office— I received a letter from
					        my Son <persRef ref="adams-charles2">Charles</persRef> with a Postscript from <persRef ref="adams-john2">John</persRef> dated last Monday telling me but too
					        plainly what <persRef ref="welsh-harriet">Harriet Welsh</persRef> and <persRef ref="degrand-peter">De Grand</persRef> left me to infer. It is this day but one
                month since I left my <persRef ref="adams-abigail">Mother</persRef> in good health— At this moment I have probably no
					        Mother on earth! Gracious God! support my <persRef ref="adams-john">father</persRef> in this deep and irreparable
                affliction! Support and comfort her children! and prepare us all to rejoin her
                Society in the abodes of the blest!— I came home early, and took an hour’s walk,
                filled with painful, and bitter reflections— <persRef key="smith-catherine-johnson">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> W. S. Smith</persRef>
                dined with us, and I spent the Evening in writing.</p>
					    
					</div>
				</div>
    
    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-10-xx">
        <head>Day</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-10-xx"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
        </bibl>
        
        <div type="docbody">
            <!-- This is a summary entry without a date.-->
            
            <p><dateline rend="italic">Day.</dateline> The first half of the month I was travelling from Boston
                to Washington— Since my return I have risen, about six O’Clock—write two or three
                hours till breakfast time—and afterwards till eleven or twelve— Then pass an hour at
                the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef>—two or three at the Office, and come home to dine at five. Write or
                read about two hours after dinner, and about ten retire to bed— My writing has been
                chiefly in my Journal.</p>
        
</div>
</div>
</div>