<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.masshist.org/publications/pub/schema/djqa-prep-2016.rng" type="xml"?>
        <?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="DJQA-authorViewMaybe.css"?>
<div type="month" volume="31" startingOnPage="076">
	<bibl n="metadata">
		<date from="1819-04-01" to="1819-04-30"/>
	</bibl>
	<!-- D/JQA/31.293 -->
	<!-- April 1819. -->
	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-01">
		<head>1 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-01"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams Family Finances</note>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
			<note type="subject">War of 1812</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">
<dateline type="heading">April 1819.</dateline>
			<p><dateline>1. VI. Thursday.</dateline> <persRef ref="forbes-john">J. M. Forbes</persRef> came into the Office this
				morning, to supply the place of <persRef ref="purviance-john">Purviance</persRef> during his absence. I have offered him the
				situation, for the want of something better and more suitable for him— <persRef ref="lewis-unknown">Commodore
				Lewis</persRef>, as he is called, came to the Office to enquire what had been the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef>
				determination upon the question of his accounts— I communicated it to him,
				unpalatable as I knew it must be to him— This giving of negative answers, for the
				President, is among the most painful parts of my duties. I told him that the
				President had read and considered his Letter, but did not feel warranted in
				departing from the principles, on which I had told him his allowance for
				compensation must be placed— He said that was surprizing to him as he had once
				engaged his passage, &amp; been on the point of embarking when he received from the
				Government an order, not then to proceed— I assured him this was a fact entirely
				new, and had not been stated before. I advised him to make a statement of it to the
				President, and to support it by evidence, in which case I was sure the President
				would reconsider his decision. With this he departed in no wise satisfied. <persRef ref="myers-john">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> John Myers</persRef> of Baltimore called at the Office and told
				me that he wished to be considered a candidate for an appointment as one of the
				Commissioners under the Treaty; with Spain— He is the son of <persRef ref="myers-moses">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Myers</persRef> a merchant of Norfolk in Virginia, whom I first knew at Amsterdam
				in Spring of the year 1783. The next time that I met him was as a fellow traveller
				from New York to Boston, in September 1801. when his son this same John Myers, then
				as he says a boy of fourteen, was with him— He reminded me of this incident and of
				their having at the same period dined in company with me at <persRef ref="smith-william">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> William Smith’s</persRef>. I well recollected having at that time met his father,
				but not that he had been with him— But on recurring to my Journal of the time, I
				find his statement correct. He says he was in the army during the late War, and has
				now a commercial establishment at Baltimore in connection with that of his father at
				Norfolk— <persRef key="smith-william-steuben">W. S. Smith</persRef> came to consult me further upon his affairs, and the situation
				of his father’s Estate and debts—an inextricable snarl— My eyes still threaten an
				inflammation so that I was not able to write this Evening.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-02">
		<head>2 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-02"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Colonization Movements</note>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Press</note>
			<note type="subject">Slave Trade</note>
			<note type="subject">Slavery</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>2. VI:</dateline> Going to my Office this morning I met <persRef ref="wirt-william">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Wirt</persRef> the Attorney General, who told me he was coming
				there to meet <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Crawford</persRef> and me at one O’Clock, and
				they accordingly came. We first examined a question which has arisen, under the
				Slave trade Act of the last Session of Congress. It authorizes the President to send
				to Africa the Slaves that may be taken by our armed vessels, and brought into the
				United States, captured in vessels attempting to introduce them in contravention to
				any of the Slave-Acts and also to appoint an agent or agents in Africa to receive
				such Slaves— Crawford had seen in the Augusta Chronicle, a Georgia Newspaper, an
				advertisement of thirty or forty slaves imported contrary to the Laws, to be sold
				for the benefit of the State, according to the provisions of the Acts of Congress
				and of the State of Georgia before the Law of Congress of the last Session— Crawford
				thought that this last Act was retrospective; and that under it, the President might
				send to Africa the Slaves thus advertised for sale, although they were imported
				before the passage of the Act— The <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef> before he left the City directed me to
				write accordingly to the <persRef ref="rabun-william">Governor</persRef> and the <persRef ref="habersham-richard">District Attorney of Georgia</persRef>— But being
				upon examination of the Act myself convinced that this course of proceeding would
				not be warranted by it, I postponed writing the Letter and this day submitted the
				act and the question to joint consideration. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wirt had
				doubts whether the Act would <pb type="ms" n="77"/>operate retrospectively in this
				case or not. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford finally came to the conclusion
				that it would not; and chiefly upon the suggestion that it would conflict with a
				vested right of the State— And he finally determined to apply to the colonization
				Society, to take the affair into their hands; as he thought they were authorised to
				do by a late Law of the State of Georgia. As to the suspended Articles of the
				Convention with Great-Britain, Crawford brought with him the statements of our trade
				with the British West-Indies in the years 1816. 17. and 18. the results of which are
				not materially different from those of the years 1802. 3. and 4. sent by <persRef ref="gallatin-albert">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Gallatin</persRef>— After much discussion, without any settled
				diversity of opinion, we agreed that I should instruct <persRef ref="rush-richard">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Rush</persRef> to propose to accept the limitation of both the lists of Articles
				as proposed by the British Plenipotentiaries; upon condition that the duties upon
				imported Articles shall not be higher upon importations direct from the United
				States, than upon those made indirectly through the North-American Colonies. We do
				not expect that these terms will be accepted by the British Government; but they
				will manifest our continued solicitude for an amicable arrangement, and they are the
				only terms to which we can safely agree— Crawford said that the effect of our
				counteracting system, could not be fairly tried, until we should cut off the
				intercourse with Bermuda, and the Bahamas, which he thought should have been done
				last Winter. <persRef ref="bailey-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bailey</persRef> spent part of the Evening with
				us. I am yet unable to write by Candle-light.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-03">
		<head>3 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-03"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams Family Residences</note>
			<note type="subject">Dueling</note>
			<note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
			<note type="subject">Press</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>3. VI:</dateline> <persRef ref="anderson-joseph">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Anderson</persRef>, the Comptroller
				of the Treasury called on me this morning; concerning an Account of postage for <persRef ref="thornton-william">D<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Thornton</persRef> Superintendent of the Patent-Office— This
				Office, is made by Law totally dependent upon the Department of State. But the D<hi
					rend="superscript">r.</hi> among his projects for making it a separate
				Department, has encouraged persons having business relating to Patents to correspond
				directly with himself, and address their Letters to him. The consequence is they are
				charged with postage; for which he makes out an Account— The Comptroller declines
				passing it, unless certified in writing by the Secretary of State. This is a new
				scruple of the comptroller’s, owing as he says to the great increase of the accounts
				of late— I have declined giving the certificates unless the Letters are sent to the
				Department to be duly entered— The Doctor finding his Account cannot pass, now
				declines taking out from the Post-Office the Letters addressed to him, and there is
				now a large accumulation of them. M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Anderson came to
				tell me that the Doctor was very troublesome about these Letters, and he knew not
				what to do with him. I said the Letters must all be sent to the Department, and
				opened there: upon which I would authorize the Postage to be paid. <persRef ref="myers-john">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> John Myers</persRef> of Baltimore called again at the Office,
				being about to return home— I received a Letter from <persRef ref="adams-thomas">my brother</persRef> at Quincy; he has
				removed with his family into my father’s house; to reside with him— He says my
				<persRef ref="adams-john">father</persRef> is unwell, and I am under great concern for his health; since his
				irreparable, and inexpressible bereavement— <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">My wife</persRef> had a large tea-party this
				Evening; but as there was scarcely any music, and no other occupation, it was dull—
				<persRef ref="gales-joseph">Gales</persRef>, the Editor of the National Intelligencer spoke of a pamphlet circulated by
				<persRef ref="scott-winfield">General Scott</persRef>, containing his correspondence with <persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General Jackson</persRef>, which sprung from
				an anonymous Letter received by Jackson, whence a quarrel has arisen between them.
				The day before the President went away, <persRef ref="calhoun-john">Calhoun</persRef> had received a Letter from Scott,
				signifying to him his intention to effect the publishing this correspondence in a
				pamphlet in defiance or by an evasion of an order from the War Department of 21.
				February 1818 which prohibited newspaper publications of quarrels between Officers
				of the Army. Scott had sometime before written to Calhoun, manifesting the same
				intention, and complaining that it was provoked by Jackson, who had shewn about
				among his friends incomplete copies of the Correspondence, suppressing one of
				Scott’s Letters. Calhoun had answered, dissuading the publication, and Scott had
				replied, persevering in his determination. I received by this day’s mail, a copy of
				the printed pamphlet, and many others were received here— In the management of this
				controversy, Jackson maintains the Achillean temper—“Impiger, Iracundus,
				inexorabilis acer,”—as if he had sat to <persRef ref="homer">Homer</persRef> for his picture— Scott exhibits an
				unnatural mixture of the Soldier and the <unclear>a</unclear>ttorney—quibbling about Law, and his
				rights as a Citizen—taking ground for refusing to fight Jackson in a duel, and
				shrinking from it when taken— Pleading religious scruples, and then explaining that
				he was joking. Promising not to fight Jackson, and then withdrawing his promise, as
				being made without consideration— First avowing that he had spoken of an order of
				Jackson’s, as mutinous; then making a <pb type="ms" n="78"/>County Court argument in
				a very disrespectful Letter to Jackson, to prove it so; and on receiving a reply
				like a rattling peal of thunder, affecting to lay it aside for ten days without
				thinking of it before answering it; and threatening Jackson with bitter pleasantry
				for charging Scott with having slandered him behind his back, when he had never been
				in his presence— These verbal subterfuges, and this casuistical Sophistry form the
				whole characteristic of Scott’s Letters and Comments— He complains bitterly that the
				contest between him and his adversary is unequal— That Jackson has superior weight
				both before the Government and the Country. That he has a more numerous staff to
				copy and circulate his Letters; and that he Scott cannot even procure franks to
				relieve him from the expence of Postage— Yet as if he had not enemy enough in
				Jackson, he hurls de gaieté de coeur, a feeble lance of surmizes and suspicions, at
				<persRef ref="clinton-dewitt">de Witt Clinton</persRef>, whom he suspects of having produced the quarrel, by an anonymous
				Letter to Jackson— The whole pamphlet is weak and inconsiderate.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-04">
		<head>4 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-04"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Panic of 1819</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>4. VI:</dateline> I walked over to Georgetown, and called upon <persRef ref="brown-katherine">M<hi
					rend="superscript">rs</hi> Katherine Brown</persRef> from whom I received a few days since
				a Letter, recommending her <persRef ref="brown-unknown2">Son</persRef> for an Office as a Clerk in any of the Departments—
				There was an intimation in the Letter that she thought I had not treated her kindly;
				which must have arisen solely from my having neglected to visit her since I have
				resided in Washington— It has been unintentional, but the reproach was not without
				foundation— She was among the friends of my early youth, towards whom I ought not
				now to have so long omitted the courtesies of social life; by an occasional visit.
				She has however been more than once invited by <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">my wife</persRef> to evening parties at our
				house— I this day found her residence, at Georgetown— She was at dinner, with her
				<persRef ref="unknown10">mother</persRef>, and another person— To avoid interrupting them I told her I would with
				pleasure serve her Son, and promised to call again and see her before long—
				Returning homeward, I stopped at <persRef ref="frye-nathaniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Frye’s</persRef>, where M<hi
					rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams soon afterwards came in with <persRef ref="hellen-mary">Mary Hellen</persRef>. Frye
				spoke to me of certain transactions between <persRef ref="johnson-richard">Col<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> R. M.
				Johnson</persRef> late member of Congress from Kentucky, which I heard with surprize and
				sorrow— A letter from <persRef ref="pope-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John Pope</persRef> of Frankfort to M<hi
					rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams had given me the first hint of Johnsons
				pecuniary embarrassments and enormous speculations— From Frye’s account Johnson did
				obtain last year money irregularly from the Paymaster General <persRef ref="brent-robert">Robert Brent</persRef>; and
				attempted to do the same of Frye this year, but without success. Johnson has been
				many years one of the most distinguished members from Kentucky, and was expected to
				be the next Governor of that State— These transactions when known, must demolish
				him— I came home with M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams, and found a Mail so
				voluminous that the reading of the Letters and despatches absorbed all the remnant
				of the day— First blossoms appearing.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-05">
		<head>5 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-05"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Bank of the United States</note>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Louisiana Purchase</note>
			<note type="subject">Panic of 1819</note>
			<note type="subject">U.S. Constitution</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>5. VI:</dateline> <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford</persRef> sent me a Message
				this morning, requesting me to call at his Office— He there read me Letters from
				<persRef ref="cheves-langdon">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Cheves</persRef>, President of the Bank of the United
				States, and from <persRef ref="smith-samuel2">General S. Smith</persRef> of Baltimore, representing the distressed state of
				the Bank, and of the commerce of the Country generally— The Bank is so drained of
				its specie, that it is hardly conceivable they can go to the month of June without
				stopping payment. The measure which Cheves now represents as indispensable is the
				refusal to receive in payments for public account the Bills of the several Branches
				of the Bank at any other Branch than that from which they issued. This rule was
				adopted last August in respect to payments on private account, but has not hitherto
				been assumed for the public payments. Crawford said that if it should be adopted,
				the public must also refuse to receive the bills of one branch at another in payment
				of the duties, and he had some doubts whether this could be done legally— He thought
				at least there was danger that the merchants whose bands should become due, might
				tender payment in the bills of distant branches, and then wait the Event of a
				lawsuit; which would embarrass and delay the receipts of the revenue with great
				inconvenience to the Public. I thought the Law would warrant the refusal to receive
				such Bills, by the Government, but as to the Bank itself it is not a question of
				expediency or even of legality— They cannot make the payments for the Bills of one
				Branch at another, nor can they without calling in two thirds of the Bills that they
				have in circulation, even every branch pay its own Bills. The state of our currency,
				circulation and exchange, connected with Constitutional questions, and the wide
				spread corruption of the numberless State Banks throughout the Union, is perilous in
				the highest degree, and threatens to terminate in a national convulsion— Smith’s
				Letter was to urge the necessity of omitting the payment this year of the instalment
				of the Louisiana debt; which as it must be made in specie proves to be among the
				most distressing drains that have been suffered.— Smith who as a merchant is deeply
				involved <pb type="ms" n="79"/>in all these difficulties, an enormous speculator in
				Stock of the United States Bank; and an exporter of Specie to India by the
				half-million at a time, writes to Crawford to alarm him for the army establishment,
				which he urges will certainly be reduced at the next Session of Congress; an event
				which is highly probable— I spoke to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford on the
				subject of the suit against <persRef ref="copeland-unknown">Copeland</persRef>, concerning which <persRef ref="degrand-peter">Degrand</persRef> has written to me,
				and I called upon the Comptroller, <persRef ref="anderson-joseph">Anderson</persRef> and shewed him Degrand’s last Letter to
				me on the subject— I received another heavy mail; with numerous despatches and
				Letters. But have so far recovered my eye-sight that I am able again to write in the
				Evening.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-06">
		<head>6 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-06"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams Family Finances</note>
			<note type="subject">Native Americans</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
			<note type="subject">Seminole Wars</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>6. V:45.</dateline> At the Office this morning, I had visitors; a <persRef ref="leamy-john">M<hi
				rend="superscript">r</hi> Leamy</persRef> of Philadelphia, son to one of the <persRef ref="leamy-unknown">owners</persRef> of a
				vessel taken nearly two years since by the Venezuelan <persRef ref="brion-luis">Admiral Brion</persRef>; and for the
				reclamation of which <persRef ref="irvine-baptis">B. Irvine</persRef> was sent out. He came to enquire what prospect there
				was of success, but I could not give him any encouragement. The claim, upon Irvine’s
				Reports is absolutely desperate; and although Irvine upon leaving Angostura, to
				return to the United States renewed the claim, there was no prospect that it would
				be admitted, and I told M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Leamy, that the only
				remaining resource of the owners of the vessel would be an application to Congress.
					<persRef key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot</persRef> came to read me an extract of a Letter that
				he had received from the British naval commanding Officer in the West-Indies, as
				informing him of an act of piracy committed by a picaroon from S<hi
					rend="superscript">t.</hi> Domingo, upon an American Vessel. Bagot told me also
				that he had received a Letter from <persRef ref="castlereagh-robert">Lord Castlereagh</persRef>, with instructions precisely
				coinciding with what I had mentioned to him as having been reported by <persRef ref="rush-richard">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Rush</persRef>, to have passed at an interview between him and
				that Minister, in relation to the execution of <persRef ref="arbuthnot-alexander">Arbuthnott</persRef> and <persRef ref="ambrister-robert">Armbrister</persRef>. M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot informed me that he intended in a week or ten
				days to leave the City; expecting to embark at Annapolis, and that a day or two
				before his departure he should come and present <persRef ref="antrobus-gibbs">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
					Antrobus</persRef> as the Charge d’Affaires during his absence. <persRef ref="lee-william">W. Lee</persRef> came to shew me a
				Letter from <persRef ref="hunt-s">S. Hunt</persRef> dated at Liverpool; mentioning my Letter to <persRef ref="erving-george">G. W. Erving</persRef> of 28.
				November, which was published in the London Courier of 27. January— This Evening, we
				had visitors at the house, <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hyde de Neuville</persRef> with
				<persRef ref="bourqueney-francois">Bourqueney</persRef>; and <persRef ref="forbes-john">Forbes</persRef> with <persRef ref="appleton-john">J. J. Appleton</persRef>— I was called away to settle an affair
				with <persRef ref="hickey-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hickey</persRef> an Agent of <persRef ref="boyd-george">George Boyd</persRef>—who married my
				<persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife’s</persRef> Sister <persRef ref="boyd-harriet">Harriet</persRef>— Boyd had an Office as first Clerk for Pensions, in the War
				Department— Last Fall, he resigned that place—sold his house to his
				Successor<space>    </space><persRef ref="edwards-james">Edwards</persRef>; removed his family into Virginia; and in the Winter received
				an Appointment, as Agent for Indian affairs at Michillimackinac. But he had
				exhausted his funds so that he could not proceed to his Post without raising a
				supply— He had received, in part payment for his house a Note for upwards of 900
				Dollars, payable, without interest 3. March 1820. signed by Edwards, and endorsed by
				<persRef ref="caldwell-elias">E. B. Caldwell</persRef>, and <persRef ref="seaton-william">W.<space>    </space>Seaton</persRef>. To raise the money, Boyd had sent this Note to
				Hickey to dispose of it, at a discount of twenty per Cent. Hickey after taking great
				pains without success had given it up in despair— George Boyds eldest Son <persRef ref="boyd-john">John</persRef> was
				here, returning to his father from a School in Pennsylvania— I was informed that
				unless Boyd could raise this money he would not be able to repair to his Post and
				must resign his Place— I therefore sent for Hickey, and took the note deducting from
				its amounts the simple interest at the rate of six per Cent a year, till the 3<hi
					rend="superscript">d.</hi> of March next— While I was transacting this business
				below, the visitors above took leave.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-07">
		<head>7 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-07"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>7. VI:30.</dateline> <persRef ref="boyd-john">John Boyd</persRef> went off at six this morning to return to
				his <persRef ref="boyd-george">father</persRef>— <persRef ref="rodgers-john">Commodore Rogers</persRef> came to the Office, and mentioned complaints received
				of piratical depredations committed upon many of our Citizens and their property;
				and we had some conversation with regard to the armed vessels which may be employed
				for the protection of our Commerce— And then falling upon other general topics.
				Rogers mentioned that the Portrait of <persRef ref="ferdinand-vii">Ferdinand the seventh</persRef> in <persRef ref="onis-luis">Onis’s</persRef> drawing room,
				resembled Onis himself so much that it had often been taken for him. He said he had
				always thought it strongly like him; and could account for it, since he had been
				told by a Spaniard that Onis was reputed to be a natural Son of <persRef ref="charles-iii">Charles the
					Third</persRef>—Ferdinand’s Grandfather— <persRef ref="edwards-e">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> E. Edwards</persRef> came to
				enquire about some Letter from a patentee to <persRef ref="thornton-william">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Thornton</persRef>, lying unopened at the Post-Office, because <pb type="ms" n="80"/>the
				Postage has not been paid upon it— The Letter he said contained money, and the
				patentee having received no answer was afraid it had miscarried and had written to
				him of enquire about it— I told Edwards that he must write to his friend the
				patentee and inform him that he must pay the Postage upon his Letter, for not having
				addressed it as he should have done to the Secretary of State— Just as I was about
				leaving the Office, to return home the Messenger <persRef ref="joseph">Joseph</persRef><space>    </space>told me there was a fire
				at the seven buildings— I immediately went there, and found the fire was at some
				wooden or frame houses back of those buildings and in the next Street. Three or four
				small houses were already nearly burnt down; and the wind blowing fresh in the
				direction from the adjoining houses, the fire extended no further— There was a great
				want of good Engines, and of water—few pumps in the neighbourhood; and two or three
				of them exhausted— It was passed seven O’Clock, when I got home to dinner— My <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef>
				was ill this Evening.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-08">
		<head>8 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-08"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Louisiana Purchase</note>
			<note type="subject">Press</note>
			<note type="subject">Religion</note>
			<note type="subject">South American Wars of Independence</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>8. V:30.</dateline> <persRef ref="brent-daniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> D. Brent</persRef> and <persRef ref="forbes-john">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Forbes</persRef> were absent from the Office. The Portuguese
				Minister, Abbé or Chevalier <persRef ref="correa-joseph">Correa de Serra</persRef>, came to the Office and took leave for
				the Summer— He is going to spend the first part of it, at Philadelphia. He had some
				time since recommended to me to read <persRef ref="romans-barnard">Barnard Romans’s</persRef> Book upon Florida, which he
				says is in the Library of Congress: and he had somewhat mysteriously hinted to me,
				that he had an observation of some importance to make to me on the subject. He this
				day told me it was that by two excellent Sea Ports in Islands on the Coast of
				Florida, one of which was Biscayne, opposite the Bahama Islands, and the other
				Tabona, opposite to the Havanna, and to the extreme point of East Florida the United
				States would have the complete military command of the Passes into the Gulph of
				Mexico; and consequently of the whole gulph itself— We found Biscayno upon the maps
				at the Office; but Tabona was not laid down upon them by name— The Abbe told me
				there was a very large map of Florida, taken by order of the <persRef ref="hill-wills">Earl of Hillsborough</persRef>,
				while it was in possession of the English— He added that Europe would not so much as
				have a suspicion of the acquisition of Power, obtained by the United States in this
				late Treaty with Spain— In his opinion it was the complement both to the Treaty of
				recognized Independence of 1782. and to the Treaty, purchasing Louisiana, of France
				in 1803— The Abbe Correa is a man of extensive and general Literature; of profound
				Science, of brilliant wit, and of inexhaustible powers of Conversation— He is so
				much of a philosopher, as to have incurred the vindictive pursuit of the
				Inquisition, and to have obtained the Friendship and Patronage of my old friend
				<persRef ref="barca-antonio">Araujo</persRef>, the late Count de Barca, by whom he was appointed to the mission here. He is
				insinuating and fascinating in his manners and deportment, and though 68 years of
				age, as lively as if he were but twenty-five— His temper however is not remarkable
				for equanimity— It is quick, sensitive, fractious, hasty, and when excited,
				obstinate— Yet he is timid, and easily cast down— An attack upon him last Spring in
				some of our newspapers, drove him almost into a fit of melancholy madness; and he
				hurried off to Norfolk where lived the only physician in whom he had confidence— He
				lived that Winter with <persRef ref="walsh-robert">Robert Walsh</persRef>, and the general rumour is that they parted not
				so good friends as they had met. The Abbes diplomatic ability consists principally
				in affecting to be any thing but a diplomat— He introduces himself as a familiar
				acquaintance to talk literature and philosophy; as a domestic inmate to gossip over
				a cup of tea— <persRef key="monroe-james">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Monroe</persRef> saw through this; but having no
				relish for literature and philosophy; and no time to listen and laugh at jokes, he
				always kept the abbe, as it was and is his principle to keep all the foreign
				Ministers—at arms length. <persRef ref="madison-james">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Madison</persRef> and <persRef ref="jefferson-thomas">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Jefferson</persRef> always received and encouraged the abbe’s
				social visits, and I have done the same; always avoiding any distinction between him
				and any others of the foreign Ministers— There is one difference in the
				correspondence of all the foreign Ministers here from that which is usual in Europe—
				They write Letters instead of Notes—in the first person instead of the third— The
				effect of this difference upon style is greater than any one not habituated to both
				modes could imagine— The third person “The Undersigned,” is stiff, cold, formal and
				dignified— It is negotiation in Court dress, Bag wig, sword by side, chapeau de
				bras, white silk Stockings, and Patent shoe-buckles. Letters in the first person are
				Negotiation in Frock Coat Pantaloons, Half-Boots and a round Hat. Another difference
				is that we here always use our own language. <persRef ref="onis-luis">Onis</persRef> in return always writes even to
				the most trivial note of Compliment, in Spanish— <persRef key="bagot-charles">Bagot</persRef> of course writes in English,
				and the other foreign Ministers excepting Correa, write in French— He always writes
				in English, and writing it, though well for a foreigner very incorrectly, if as may
				very probably happen, any part of his correspondence should be communicated to
				Congress and published, it will subject him to mortification— I was employed great
				part of this <pb type="ms" n="81"/>day in revising for publication in the National
				Intelligencer, a translation made by <persRef ref="brent-robert">Robert Brent jun<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi></persRef>
				of a Spanish Royal Order of 14. January last, prescribing capital punishment without
				remission, against all foreigners taken in arms, with the South-American Insurgents,
				or furnishing to them warlike supplies— An order upon which comment will be
				necessary. There was a fire again in the day-time, which was burning at the
				Navy-yard, as I came home; and by which three or four houses on the New-Jersey
				avenue were burnt— My <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef> continued quite unwell the whole day—</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-09">
		<head>9 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-09"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
			<note type="subject">Seminole Wars</note>
			<note type="subject">South American Wars of Independence</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>9. VI:15.</dateline> Good-Friday. The <persRef ref="onis-luis">Chevalier de Onis</persRef> the Spanish
				Minister came and took leave at my house. He is going to spend a fortnight or three
				weeks at Philadelphia: thence to New-York, and embarks in May with his family
				intending to return to Spain. I told him that I had heard there were Americans
				interested in the annulled grants to <persRef ref="alagon-unknown">Alagon</persRef>, <persRef ref="punonrostro">Puñon-Rostro</persRef> and <persRef ref="vargas-pedro">Vargas</persRef>— He said he
				believed <persRef ref="hackley-richard">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hackley</persRef> and <persRef ref="meade-richard">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Meade</persRef> were interested. They had applied to the Duke of Alagon to purchase one third
				of his grants, but he had refused selling—they had been more successful with the
				others— I asked him whether he had any reason to suppose the <persRef ref="casairujo-carlos">Marquis of Casa Yrujo</persRef>
				was interested in the grants— He said he did not know— He should not be surprized if
				he had— The Marquis he knew had an old grant in West-Florida—the part of which we
				are already in possession; but his grant was of 1804 or 1805. For myself said Onis,
				I never would have any thing to do with them— A denial again, more explicit even
				than the last— I suspend my judgment. I spoke of the <persRef ref="ferdinand-vii">King’s</persRef> order of 14 January.
				declaring death irremissible for the punishment of foreigners joining the
				South-American Insurgents; and told him I hoped he would get it revoked. He said he
				should be glad if he could— Not that there could be any question as to the
				correctness of the principle— But he never was a friend to the multiplication of
				sanguinary punishments; and he thought it in this case too late. There were few very
				few who could suffer under it; and it might provoke to retaliation. He said he had
				Letters from Madrid to the 15<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>of February, which
				mentioned nothing of the removal actual or intended of Casa Yrujo. He spoke of the
				Death of <persRef ref="charles-iv">Charles the fourth</persRef>, which happened only a fortnight after that of his <persRef ref="marialouisa">wife</persRef>—
				His grief at the loss of her brought on a fit of the Gout which killed him— A most
				extraordinary example said Onis, of the ascendancy which a wicked and worthless
				woman can acquire and maintain over a weak good hearted man— That woman, said Onis,
				and her <persRef ref="godoy-manuel">Prince of the Peace</persRef>, were the cause of all the misfortunes of Spain. They
				brought things to such a pass that the king actually, voluntarily, and most
				sincerely abdicated the crown; and yet she afterwards prevailed upon him to sign a
				declaration that this abdication had been extorted from him by compulsion— Onis goes
				to Spain to take his daughter <persRef ref="heredia-narcissa">Madame de Heredia</persRef> to her <persRef ref="heredia-unknown">husband</persRef>; for according to the
				Spanish custom she was married by proxy and has never seen her husband since she has
				borne his name— He was formerly here as a Secretary to the Legation, but went to
				Spain before the marriage, and has never returned. Onis says he has also private
				affairs of his own that will require his attention perhaps for a year, after which
				he will return here, unless he should be placed elsewhere— I part from Onis with
				regret, though he has more of diplomatic <hi rend="italic">trickery</hi> in his
				character than any other of the foreign Ministers now here— My transactions with him
				have been infinitely more important than with any of the others; more important
				indeed than any others in which I ever was engaged— The review of them is an
				inexhaustible source of gratitude, mingled with some portion of self-humiliation—
				Onis spoke again to day of the conduct of the Spanish commanding Officers in
				Florida; and said that he gave up entirely <persRef ref="luengo-francisco">Luengo</persRef>, who had certainly been culpable;
				but <persRef ref="masot-jose">Mazot</persRef>, the Governor of Pensacola, he thought had done nothing more than his
				duty, and would have deserved to be shot if he had not resisted <persRef ref="jackson-andrew">Jackson</persRef>, as he did—
				And he was sorry to say the poor man had been so much overcome by his misfortunes
				that he had lost his senses and gone mad. The troops who took possession of
				Pensacola on the 8<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>of February last were commanded by
				a Major General.— Onis leaves the City on Sunday Morning— As I was going to my
				Office I met <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hyde de Neuville</persRef>; and reminded him of
				his promise to shew me the Memorial of the <persRef ref="desousaholstein-pedro">Portuguese Minister</persRef> to the Congress at
				Aix La Chapelle, upon the piracies, he renewed his promise to bring it to me— <persRef ref="thornton-william">D<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Thornton</persRef> came to me at the Office again about the
				postage of his Letters— I proposed to him to give notice in the Newspapers that all
				Letters relating to Patents must be directed to the <pb type="ms" n="82"/>Secretary
				of State; but he thought that would have the appearance to the Public of a want of
				Confidence in him on my part; and besides would not apply to the Letters already at
				the Post-Office— I finally agreed that he should take the Letters from the Office;
				open them; send all those relating to public business to me, to be entered on the
				Register of Letters received; after which they should be sent back to him and the
				postage paid— The whole of this affair is an example how petty abuses imperceptibly
				creep into public institutions— There were this day three fires in the City. One,
				early in the Morning, almost next door to <persRef ref="frye-nathaniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Frye’s</persRef>—the
				Second again at the Navy-yard about Noon, and the third at the Corner of F. and
					13<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>Streets where four large brick dwelling houses
				were consumed— I was at the last before returning home to dinner; all these fires
				first caught in Stables, and have excited a general alarm of having been kindled by
				incendiaries. Not one of the dwelling houses in F. Street would have been burnt, but
				for their shingle roofs— <persRef ref="anderson-joseph">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Anderson</persRef> and <persRef ref="anderson-alexander">two of</persRef> <persRef ref="anderson-william">his Sons</persRef>
				got into a troublesome quarrel, with <persRef ref="coyle-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Coyle</persRef>, President
				of a Fire Company. <persRef ref="smith-william-steuben;smith-catherine-johnson">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript"
					>rs</hi> W. S. Smith</persRef> spent the Evening here.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-10">
		<head>10 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-10"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>10. VII:</dateline> I have had almost every day this week, such a multitude
				of Letters and despatches by the Mail, that it has consumed all my Office hours to
				read them— <persRef ref="young-moses">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Young</persRef> one of the Clerks in the Office
				applies for leave of absence for some weeks to go upon private business of his own
				to Augusta in Georgia— This morning I made a draught of a Letter to <persRef ref="glenn-elias">E. Glenn</persRef>,
				District Attorney at Baltimore, upon the piratical vessels fitted out there— As I
				was going home to dinner I overtook and walked with <persRef ref="thornton-william">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
					Thornton</persRef>, who was going to attend a Town Meeting at <persRef ref="davis-unknown">Davis’s</persRef> Hotel— It was held on
				account of these frequent fires; and several Resolutions of precaution were adopted—
				One particularly for establishing a nightly Patrol— It is remarkable that at the
				same time that these fires have been happening here; there have been several at
				Philadelphia; and one at Norfolk by which upwards of fifty houses were burnt. <persRef ref="hellen-thomas">Thomas
					Hellen</persRef>, and <persRef ref="buchanan-robert">Robert Buchanan</persRef> dined with us and <persRef ref="frye-nathaniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Frye</persRef>
				was here in the Evening.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-11">
		<head>11 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-11"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams Family Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>11. VI.</dateline> Easter-Sunday— “On our firm resolves, thin
				audible and noiseless foot of Time, steals unperceived.” This remark is continually
				obtruded upon me— I took a firm resolve, on resuming the interrupted thread of this
				Journal, on the 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of last Month, to write an Evening
				page and morning page of it, until its arrears should be redeemed— Only three
				fourths of this resolution have hitherto been accomplished— Visitors at home,
				evening engagements abroad, newspaper reading, inflammations of the eyes, and
				involuntary drowsiness have absorbed many of the Evening hours; and in the Morning,
				Newspapers again, reading and assorting them, and above all an instinctive idleness,
				an obstinate do-nothing habit wasting hours of leisure, as if for the sake of being
				always hurried, have consumed at least half the time which I devoted by anticipation
				to this work. Thus last Evening I did not write a line, and this morning before I
				had finished my page, came the hour for paying a visit which has been long delayed.
				I went with my <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef> to see <persRef ref="clark-susanna">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Susan B. Clarke</persRef>, my
				brother <persRef ref="adams-charles">Charles’s</persRef> eldest daughter, who less than two years since married<space>    </space><persRef ref="clark-charles">Clarke</persRef>,
				a Lieutenant in the Navy. He went in the Franklin to the Mediterranean; but being in
				a consumption returned to this Country last December, and came with his wife to the
				house of a <persRef ref="french-m">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> French</persRef>, a cousin of his, a widow, living
				about four miles beyond Georgetown— He has been almost ever since his arrival
				confined to his bed, with no prospect of recovery. We found his wife, <persRef ref="unknown11">his Sister</persRef>,
				and M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> French much distressed, the symptoms of his
				disease having, the last two days become extremely severe, and boding an almost
				immediate dissolution. M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> French said they did not
				expect he would live over the day. A <persRef ref="luffborough-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Luffborough</persRef>, an
				elderly woman residing in the neighbourhood was with them, and they had sent this
				morning for <persRef key="smith-william-steuben">W. S. Smith</persRef> to come and be with him in his last Moments— As we returned
				home, M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams went to see <persRef key="smith-catherine-johnson">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>rs</hi> W. S. Smith</persRef>, who is herself quite unwell; and I walked home. The day
				was rainy, notwithstanding which there was another fire; and a house partly burnt
				down upon the Capitol Hill. Great part of this Evening was employed in writing.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-12">
		<head>12 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-12"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>12. VI:15.</dateline> My Son <persRef ref="adams-george">George’s</persRef> Birth-day. He was born with the
				century, and this day completes his eighteenth and commences his nineteenth year. As
				I was going out this morning I met at my door <persRef ref="bourqueney-francois">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Bourqueney</persRef>, one of the young Men attached to the French Legation, who came to inform
				me that he was going immediately to France, as a Messenger with despatches from <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Hyde de Neuville</persRef>, and to offer to take mine— He turned
				and walked with me as far as M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> de Neuville’s house, on
				the way to my Office. De Neuville afterwards himself come to the Office, and brought
				me the Note of <persRef ref="desousaholstein-pedro">Count Palmella</persRef> the Portuguese Minister, to the Congress at Aix la
				Chapelle, on the piratical privateers. He left it with me, and gave me permission to
				have a copy of it taken— I read to him the Letter that I had written to <persRef ref="glenn-elias">Glenn</persRef> the
				district Attorney at Baltimore, directing him to examine the Evidence, and commence
				Prosecutions in every case where it will be sufficient for conviction. He declared
				himself entirely satisfied with this, but asked me to write him an answer to his
				notes on the captures of French property, that he might transmit to his Government.
					<pb type="ms" n="83"/>He intimated to me that one of his principal motives for
				despatching Bourqueney now to France was to give his Government further and more
				complete expositions relative to the eight Article of our late Treaty with Spain;
				and to induce them to interpose by direct influence upon Spain to prevent her making
				any question upon that Article, in relation to the grants— Particularly to state
				with detail the Evidence, which he has repeatedly told me, that he had from Onis
				during the negotiation, that the Spanish Government itself knew, the grants were
				null and void. And he told me he should be glad, if I would write to <persRef ref="gallatin-albert">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Gallatin</persRef> concerning it; that if necessary he might
				consult with the French Government about it— I promised him that I would. De
				Neuville’s great earnestness upon this affair may be ascribed to various motives,
				some highly honourable and generous—other more partaking of those virtues that begin
				at home— 1. To a sense of pure Justice and unsullied honour— Knowing the professed
				intention and clear understanding on both sides, that no error committed, or
				deception attempted by Onis should have any possible effect to defeat it. 2. To
				vindicate his own integrity in the transaction; that Article having been most
				particularly discussed between him and me; and the principles settled between us;
				that bona-fide settlers should not be molested even though with grants not entirely
				regular, but that no fraudulent grants should be confirmed. 3. To strengthen his
				interest with his own Government, by interesting that of the United States in his
				favour; which he cannot fail to do, by bearing testimony decisively for them upon a
				point of considerable importance— 4. To make a merit hereafter for himself or his
				Government, of the part he takes in this affair, as having rendered essential
				service to the United States, and acquiring claims to favour in return. and 5.
				Finally, to make himself important, and have an agency in the transaction which may
				add to his individual or political consequence— There is very probably a mixture of
				all these ingredients in his impulses, and I am willing to believe that the pure and
				disinterested portion of them predominate in a scale adjusted by the standard of
				their comparative excellence— De Neuville is not a profound or gigantic Genius; but
				he is a fair and honourable man. He says he does not expect to go for France,
				himself, before July— <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef> spent the Evening with
				her <persRef key="smith-catherine-johnson">Sister Smith</persRef>, at <persRef ref="fletcher-noah">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Fletcher’s</persRef>, opposite <persRef ref="calhoun-john">Calhoun’s</persRef>;
				where they now reside. M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Smith is yet unwell, and
				<persRef key="smith-william-steuben">Smith</persRef> remains at <persRef ref="french-m">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> French’s</persRef> with <persRef ref="clark-charles">Clarke</persRef>— M<hi
					rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams sent <persRef ref="giusta-antoine">Antoine</persRef> there this Evening, to enquire if
				he could be of any service—but he was not wanted and came back late— There was
				another alarm of fire this day.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-13">
		<head>13 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-13"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Dueling</note>
			<note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
			<note type="subject">Press</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
			<note type="subject">Religion</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>13. VI:</dateline> <persRef ref="hay-george">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> George Hay</persRef> came to the
				Office, and brought with him a copy of the correspondence between <persRef ref="scott-winfield">General Scott</persRef> and
				the <persRef ref="calhoun-john">Secretary at War</persRef>, immediately before Scott’s publication of his correspondence
				with <persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General Jackson</persRef>. M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Hay said the <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef> had
				been greatly concerned at this publication—chiefly from regard for Scott himself;
				and an apprehension that it would injure his reputation. The very day before he left
				this City, the President had written a private Letter to General Scott, earnestly
				dissuading him from the publication; but it was too late— And as it was probable the
				President on his present tour would meet with General Jackson; the question had
				occurred to him, whether he ought to make any difference in his treatment of
				Jackson, in consequence of any thing contained in the publication— He had requested
				him to give him his opinion, and to call upon me for mine— I told him that I saw
				nothing in Scott’s publication which ought to affect the President’s public conduct
				towards Jackson— I thought Scott had put himself in the wrong; by the publication— I
				was sorry for it, having a personal regard for Scott, and high sense of his public
				services. But I thought he had treated the Secretary of War, and even the President
				with little delicacy to say the least, by the publication, and by the Comments of
				which it in part consists. I thought the principle unsound that he had assumed—that
				although holding a Commission as a Military Officer, he had the same right as any
				private citizen, to utter his opinions of praise or blame upon the measures of his
				superior Officer, of the War Department and of the President— His charge too against
				the <persRef ref="clinton-dewitt">Governor of New-York</persRef>, avowedly upon mere suspicion, and by his own statement,
				resting upon evidence excessively slender, was altogether unjustifiable, and by
				Clinton’s flat and positive denial, puts Scott himself in the most awkward
				predicament possible—that of having himself violated the confidence of private
				conversation at a dinner table, which was one of the most odious features of what he
				suspected in Clinton— For if Clinton had no concern with or knowledge <pb type="ms"
					n="84"/>of the anonymous Letter, it is Scott himself who betrays the private
				Conversation of Clinton, and most unjustifiably brings him into a collision, or into
				the necessity of giving an explanation to Jackson— Clinton’s declaration upon this
				point is evidently equivocal and embarrassed— Instead of admitting or denying what
				Scott declares him to have said he says it is not <hi rend="italic">probable</hi> he
				can recollect the Conversation; but is confident he said nothing disrespectful of
				Jackson. This is shuffling and evasive— What had probability or improbability to do
				with the question whether M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Clinton did, or did not
				recollect the conversation alleged by Scott—to Clinton himself it was not a question
				of probability, but of consciousness. But what right had Scott to divulge the
				Conversation?— Altogether it appeared to me that Scott had made out for himself a
				very bad case— If Jackson, by shewing about the Correspondence in Manuscript, had
				violated the order of 21. February 1818. (which it was my opinion he had not) the
				only notice the President could take of it was, to have him arrested and tried by a
				Court Martial— If he did not think that proper, I thought he should take no public
				notice to him of any thing appearing from Scott’s publication— M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Hay said this entirely concurred with what he had
				already written to the President. He thought Scott had irretrievably disgraced
				himself. Both Clinton and <persRef ref="pell-unknown">Pell</persRef> had treated him with inexpressible contempt yet he
				could not call out either of them; and if he did neither of them would be obliged to
				fight him— The truth was, Scott’s vanity was leading him to his ruin. He could not
				bear to see Jackson engrossing so much of the public notice, not only of this
				Country, but of the world. He was determined to be talked about too— His attack upon
				Clinton was unaccountable. It was strange he had not perceived, that he was making
				himself chargeable with the very offence of which he so lightly accused Clinton— He
				had been very ill advised— Clinton’s Declaration was indeed greatly liable to
				criticism— It was no Declaration at-all— He says he <hi rend="italic">thinks
					proper</hi> to declare, but does not declare. However, as the President was very
				anxious on this subject, he wished I would write him a line by to-morrow’s mail, and
				give him my opinion concerning it— I promised him I would. <persRef ref="homans-benjamin">B. Homans</persRef> the chief Clerk
				of the Navy Department, came to ask permission to send to <persRef ref="prince-james">Ja<hi rend="superscript"
					>s.</hi> Prince</persRef> Marshal for the District of Massachusetts a copy of the Petition
				for a reprieve to the Pirates lately executed at Boston— It seems the Petitioners,
				some of whom are clergymen, complain that the Marshal denied them access to the men;
				and they have complained of it to the Public in a late number of the Panoplist, a
				periodical religious publication. Homans says the reason why they were excluded was
				that the men were Roman Catholics, and were at their own request attended by a
				Priest of their own persuasion— However I told Homans that I could not permit the
				copy of the Petition to go from the Department—because it was addressed to the
				President, and not to me—and because it contained no complaint against the Marshal,
				nor any allusion to his having denied the Petitioners access to the Prisoners. It
				was merely a Petition for a reprieve, upon religious motives—highly respectable in
				themselves, though as I had thought on that occasion injudiciously applied—
				<persRef ref="bourqueney-francois">Bourqueney</persRef> came and took leave— He goes at five to-morrow Morning, to embark at
				New-York. I wrote a hasty despatch to <persRef ref="gallatin-albert">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gallatin</persRef> to
				send by him, and taking a Press Copy, had the draught itself sent; there being not
				time to have the copy made this Evening. I passed the Evening with <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi
					rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef> and <persRef ref="hellen-mary">Mary Hellen</persRef> at <persRef key="smith-catherine-johnson">M<hi rend="superscript"
						>rs</hi> Smith’s</persRef>. She received as we went in a Note from <persRef ref="huntt-henry">D<hi rend="superscript"
							>r</hi> Huntt</persRef> informing her that Smith would remain at <persRef ref="french-m">M<hi rend="superscript"
								>rs</hi> French’s</persRef>; as <persRef ref="clark-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Clarke</persRef> would probably not
				live over the Night.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-14">
		<head>14 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-14"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">American Revolution</note>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Emancipation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
			<note type="subject">Impressment</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
			<note type="subject">Seminole Wars</note>
			<note type="subject">Slave Trade</note>
			<note type="subject">Slavery</note>
			<note type="subject">South American Wars of Independence</note>
			<note type="subject">U.S. Constitution</note>
			<note type="subject">War of 1812</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>14. V:45.</dateline> Wrote to the <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef>; which occupied all the
				Morning, and again broke in upon the execution of my Resolution to redeem the
				arrears of my Journal. At the Office, I received a note requesting my attendance,
				and that of my family to-morrow morning at eleven O’Clock, at the funeral of <persRef ref="clark-charles">T. C.
					Clarke</persRef>, He died at eight, this Morning. <persRef ref="scott-alexander">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Alexander
				Scott</persRef> of Georgetown came and spent half an hour at the Office. I did not very
				distinctly understand what he came for, and found his Conversation dull— He
				certainly found mine very much so. <persRef key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot</persRef> the British
				Minister came and took leave and presented <persRef ref="antrobus-gibbs">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford
				Antrobus</persRef> as Chargé d’Affaires during his absence— Bagot goes the day after to-morrow
				to Annapolis, with his family; expecting there the Forth Frigate, in which they are
				to embark for England. As this was in all probability the last time I shall ever see
				him, and as he is returning immediately to his Government, I took the opportunity to
				have a long conversation with him, reviewing all the principal subjects of
				discussion between the two Governments which yet remain unsettled. Antrobus soon
				left us— There were two or three affairs of individuals upon which M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot has made representations, and upon which he has
				not received definitive answers. The chief of them is upon a claim of a British
				Subject named <persRef ref="clarke-george2">George Clarke</persRef>, for certain Lands in the State of Vermont; by virtue of
				a grant from the <persRef ref="clarke-george">Governor of New-York</persRef> in the year 1739. The claim involves the old
				controversy between New-York, New-Hampshire and Vermont. Clarke’s grant was annulled
				by the final compromise between the States of New-York and Vermont. He now claims
				restitution or indemnity, under the 6<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>Article of the
				Treaty of Peace of 1783. and the 9<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>of the Treaty of
				1794. I told M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot that the subject would be fully
				considered, but I apprehended that neither of the Treaties had <pb type="ms" n="85"
				/>any bearing upon it— The Article in the Treaty of Peace, referring only to Estates
				confiscated or sequestered during the revolutionary War, for political causes; and
				that in the Treaty of 1794. only to the titles of those who then held lands in the
				United States— Neither of which cases, applied to the claim of Clarke. He said all
				he had to ask was that the claim should be fairly examined, and an answer upon it
				given— On affairs of more general interest I asked him if he had received
				instructions to make any representations here on the piratical depredations of
				privateers fitted out in our Ports, and sailing under South-American flags— He had
				none; and no despatches from <persRef ref="castlereagh-robert">Lord Castlereagh</persRef>, since January. I then mentioned to
				him the <persRef ref="desousaholstein-pedro">Portuguese Memorial</persRef> to the Congress at Aix-La-Chapelle; and the final entry
				upon the Protocol; that representations should be made to this Government, by the
				Ministers of the Powers having Ministers at Washington— I told him that these
				Representations had been made by the <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">French Minister</persRef>; and were expected from the
				<persRef ref="greuhm-frederick">Prussian Minister</persRef>; and from the <persRef ref="poletica-pierre">Russian Minister</persRef> when he arrives. As it was probable
				instructions from England to him to the same effect were on the way, and might cross
				him on his passage, I could advert to the facts, that the substance of the
				neutrality Act of 3. March 1817. had been re-enacted and made permanent in 1818. and
				that an additional Act against Piracy had been made at the late Session of Congress.
				I wished him to refer to these, in reporting to his Government as proofs of the
				earnestness with which we were desirous of applying all suitable means for the
				suppression of this irregular privateering from our Ports— He said he would not fail
				to do it, and had an entire conviction that such were the views of the American
				Government. It was indeed apparent that those Pirates annoyed the commerce of the
				United States, as much as that of other Nations. I told him that this subject
				naturally led to that of the contest between Spain and the South-Americans, which
				was connected with it, and I recurred to the difference of Views between the United
				States, and the European allied Powers with regard to the termination of that
				conflict. From <persRef ref="rush-richard">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Rush’s</persRef> report of a late interview,
				between Lord Castlereagh and him, it appears that the British Government still
				adhere to the expectation that the Spanish Sovereignty in South-America will be
				restored. Our view of the subject is different. We believe the Spanish power there
				to be extinct; and that it is not in human power to restore it— We have now no
				interest of our own to have this event precipitated; we acquiesce in the
				determination of the European allies, to wait some time longer for the Catastrophe—
				Spain has rejected the interposition of the allies which she had solicited, and now
				undertakes to reduce the Colonies herself. The event must ere long be seen— We think
				it impossible that Spain should recover her supremacy, and we think there is a moral
				obligation which at no distant day will make it the duty of other Nations to
				recognize Buenos Ayres, Venezuela, and Chili, as Independent States. The period when
				this obligation will become imperative may be more or less distant; but it is
				constantly approaching; and cannot now be remote. We have already been prepared for
				the acknowledgment of Buenos-Ayres—but we have avoided interfering with the policy
				of the allies, and we have proposed to all the Great Powers to make the Act of
				acknowledgment in concert with them— We have made known explicitly to them our
				principles— Circumstances may arise which we shall consider as decisive to induce
				the recognition of Buenos-Ayres; but if they should it will be only a formality, for
				the purpose of having regular agents there, and receiving them from them, but
				without intending to take their part in the War, and without stipulating or
				accepting any special favours to ourselves— He said he thought with me it was very
				probable they would ultimately prevail in the struggle for Independence, against
				Spain; but whether they would be competent to establish permanent Governments for
				themselves, he thought more doubtful. He should however exactly report my
				observations to his Government— I then said there was another subject upon which I
				was glad to have some explanation with him at this time— I meant, the Slave trade—
				Lord Castlereagh had communicated through M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Rush the
				Treaties concluded with Spain, and the Netherlands by which the armed Vessels of
				either power, were authorised to cruize for search and capture the Slave-trading
				vessels under the flag of the other, and take them for adjudication before a joint
				Court composed of Judges of both Nations, holding their Courts in the Colonies or
				Possessions of both in Africa. And Lord Castlereagh had proposed that the United
				States should enter into similar engagements with Great-Britain— These, M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Rush <pb type="ms" n="86"/>had been instructed to
				decline, for two reasons, each of which would have been decisive if alone— One was
				that the United States, having no Colony or Possession in Africa had no territory
				where the joint Court could hold their Sessions; and the other that the Constitution
				of the United States admitted no appointment of judges who would not be amenable to
				impeachment by the House of Representatives and before the Senate. There was a third
				reason which had been mentioned to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Rush, but which he
				had not been desired to urge, if the others should appear to be entirely
				satisfactory to the British Government, perhaps he had not mentioned it at all to
				Lord Castlereagh; to whom he had very fully disclosed the others. But by a late
				despatch from him I had learnt that <persRef ref="wilberforce-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wilberforce</persRef> had
				been holding conferences with him, pressing the subject upon him with great
				earnestness, and complaining that our resistance to the principle of admitting the
				mutual right of search, by the armed vessels of either party, of the
				merchant-vessels of the other, had set the example to others, and encouraged France
				particularly to the same resistance— We took no exception to these discussions
				between our Minister and M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wilberforce, whom we
				understand to be by the common consent to the British Cabinet, himself a sort of
				Minister of State upon Slave-trade affairs— He had held such a conference with me; a
				day or two before I left London, to come home— He had then proposed to me this
				system of mutual search, and common Courts with great earnestness; and I then had
				explicitly stated to him what I apprehended would be an insurmountable objection
				against it to the United States— But as he now appeared to be reverting to the same
				project with increasing rather than diminished zeal, I thought it well to come
				directly to the point of our difficulty, by stating it in all its force to the
				British Cabinet— It was my opinion, and I could now give it as that of the President
				and of all his official advisers, that the United States ought on no consideration
				whatever to listen to any proposal for admitting a right of search in their merchant
				vessels, by the Commanders of foreign armed vessels, so long as the question remains
				open between them and Great-Britain, concerning impressment for men— As we had no
				wish to stir this question unnecessarily, or to awaken the feelings connected with
				it, when it can be avoided, we had scarcely mentioned it in regular communications
				to the British Government; but now and it might perhaps be best in this informal
				manner, I could assure him that this objection would be quite as insuperable as
				either of the others. But that it proceeded from no aversion in us to co-operate to
				the utmost extent of our Power in accomplishing the abolition of the Slave-trade,
				Congress had furnished a new and signal proof by an Act passed at the last Session,
				in addition to those already existing, and with which I presumed he was well
				acquainted. He said he had already noticed it in his despatches and transmitted a
				copy of it. That he could not be surprized at the reluctance which must be felt here
				against any engagement admitting a right of search in time of Peace, while that of
				impressment in time of War remained unsettled— He should faithfully report to his
				Government, the substance of all that I had said to him, and was himself impressed
				with an entire conviction of the sincerity and earnestness with which the Government
				of the United States were on their part pursuing the abolition of the traffic in
				Slaves. He then observed that he had received from Lord Castlereagh the Instruction
				which he had read to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Rush, in relation to the course
				which the British Government had determined to pursue concerning the execution by
				<persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General Jackson</persRef> of the two British Subjects <persRef ref="arbuthnot-alexander">Arbuthnott</persRef> and <persRef ref="ambrister-robert">Armbrister</persRef>— If I desired
				it, he would communicate that despatch to me; but the substance of it was precisely
				the same as I had mentioned to him that it had been reported by M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Rush, that it would add nothing to his communication;
				and the whole subject was so painful to him, that he should be happy to have nothing
				more to say about it, and to dismiss it forever— I told him that I should readily
				leave it at his discretion, whether to communicate Lord Castlereagh’s Instruction or
				not— In the last despatch I had received from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Rush,
				he had reported an interview, at which Lord Castlereagh had told him that the
				British Government would make no remonstrance against the Spanish Royal Order of 14.
				January last for putting to death all foreigners taken in arms with the insurgents
				or supplying them with munitions of War— He told Rush that France had been much
				affected by that order, but the British Government would take no notice of it— If
				their subjects would join the South-Americans, they must abide by all the
				consequences— Great-Britain would no more interfere for them, than for Arbuthnott
				and Armbrister. I told Bagot that there was a great distinction between the cases—
				The struggle between Spain and her Colonies, had been recognized by us as well as by
				Great-Britain, as a civil war—in which the Colonists had the <pb type="ms" n="87"
				/>usual rights of civilized belligerent Nations. They were not subject to the rules
				of Savage warfare, nor was it usual for foreigners taking part with them to be put
				to death. Besides which, there were great numbers of foreigners, thousands even of
				English; enlisted with the South-Americans— Executions, lose their effect of terror
				and example when inflicted upon great numbers, and without discrimination, and if
				this order should really be carried into effect against many of the English in
				South-America, it would be difficult for the British Government to avoid taking some
				notice of it— He said he supposed it was concluded that the order could not be
				carried into Execution—and besides, as the English who had joined the
				South-Americans were all of the Class of People who were the most inveterate
				opposers and enemies of their own Government at home, that Government could not be
				expected to take much interest in their favour— It was a foolish Order on the part
				of Spain; but the British Government was not bound to protect their Subjects, who
				engaged with the Insurgents— I finally told M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot,
				that as the President felt the highest gratification, at the general good
				Understanding now subsisting between the United States and Great-Britain, so I hoped
				he would give Lord Castlereagh the fullest assurance of our earnest desire to
				promote and cultivate that good understanding to the utmost. He said he should take
				the greatest pleasure in performing this duty, as he knew that nothing could be more
				gratifying to his own Government. He thanked me for the facilities which I had
				always given him, in transacting business; and we parted with the most friendly
				mutual expressions of personal cordiality, and mutual good wishes. M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot is a younger brother of <persRef ref="bagot-william">Lord Bagot</persRef>, a Peer of
				Great-Britain—and his <persRef ref="bagot-mary">wife</persRef> a very discreet, amiable and lovely woman, is daughter of
				<persRef ref="pole-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> William Wellesley Pole</persRef>, Master of the Mint, and
				brother to the <persRef ref="wellington-arthur">Duke of Wellington</persRef>— Bagot is about thirty five; tall well
				proportioned, and with a remarkably handsome face. Perfectly well-bred and of
				dignified and gentlemanly deportment— The principal feature of his character is
				discretion, one of the most indispensable qualities of a good negotiator, but
				neither his intellectual powers, nor his acquisitions are in any degree striking.
				His temper is serious, but cheerful. He has no depth of dissimulation, though enough
				to suppress his feelings when it is for his interest to conceal them. He has resided
				here three years, and though coming immediately after a War; in which the National
				feelings here were highly exasperated against his Country; has made himself
				universally acceptable. No English Minister has ever been so popular, and the
				mediocrity of his talents has been one of the principal causes of his success. This
				is so obvious that it has staggered my belief in the universality of the maxim, that
				men of greatest talents ought to be sought out for Diplomatic Missions— Bagot has
				been a better Minister, than a much abler man would have been. Better for the
				interest of England—better for the tranquility of this Country; better for the
				harmony between the two Nations; for his own quiet; and for the comfort of those
				with whom he has had official intercourse here. For a Negotiation that would require
				great energy of mind, activity of research or fertility of expedients such a man
				would not be competent; but to go through the ordinary routine of business; and the
				common intercourse of Society to neutralize fretful passions, and sooth prejudices;
				a man of good breeding, inoffensive manners and courteous deportment, is nearer to
				the true diplomatic standard, than one with the Genius of <persRef ref="shakespeare-william">Shakespear</persRef>, the learning
				of <persRef ref="bentley-william">Bentley</persRef>, the philosophical penetration of <persRef ref="berkeley-george">Berkley</persRef>, or the wit of <persRef ref="swift-jonathan">Swift</persRef>— Before I
				came home from my Office, <persRef ref="bowie-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bowie</persRef> of Georgetown called,
				and requested my attention to a claim of his upon the Government, which was before
				Congress at their last Session, and concerning which he had then called upon me.—
					<persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef> spent the Evening at her <persRef key="smith-catherine-johnson">Sister Smith’s</persRef>.
				The weather has been yesterday and this day at high Summer heat.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-15">
		<head>15 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-15"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams Family Finances</note>
			<note type="subject">Adams Family Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>15. VI:</dateline> I went with <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Adams</persRef>, at
				eleven O’Clock this morning and attended the funeral of <persRef ref="clark-charles">C. T. Clarke</persRef>, at his Cousin,
				<persRef ref="french-m">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> French’s</persRef> house. He was buried on the Estate,
				about two hundred yards distant from the house— The funeral service was read by <persRef ref="addison-thomas">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Addison</persRef>—very few persons were there—chiefly family
				relations— His <persRef ref="clark-unknown">brother</persRef>, and <persRef ref="clark-susanna">wife</persRef>. His <persRef ref="unknown11">Sister</persRef> <persRef ref="luffborough-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
					Luffborough</persRef>, <persRef ref="weems-unknown3">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Weems</persRef>; and three or four other
				persons—<persRef ref="finch-william">Lieutenant Finch</persRef>, and one other Officer of the Navy— After returning from
				the grave, the Will was read to the family relations— It was made the day before he
				died; and is in three or four lines, giving all his Estate, real, personal, and
				mixed to his wife; constituting her sole executrix, and guardian, to their infant
				daughter— We invited M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Clarke to go home with us, and
				take her <pb type="ms" n="88"/><persRef ref="clark-susan">child</persRef> with her; but she declined for the present. <persRef key="smith-william-steuben">W. S. Smith</persRef> returned to the City with us— I attended at my Office— <persRef ref="mckean-unknown2">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M’Kean</persRef> came and requested me to obtain an order for
				placing immediately in active service <persRef ref="buchanan-thomas">Thomas M’Kean Buchanan</persRef>, for whom a warrant as
				Midshipman was made out the last Autumn— I made a draft of a Note to the <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">French
				Minister Hyde de Neuville</persRef>, in answer to his notes complaining of the Pirates— M<hi
					rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Adams spent the Evening at <persRef key="smith-catherine-johnson">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>rs</hi> W. S. Smith’s</persRef>.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-16">
		<head>16 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-16"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams Family Finances</note>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>16. V:30.</dateline> I called at the Navy Department on the <persRef ref="homans-benjamin">Chief Clerk
				M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Homans</persRef>, to enquire for an order to place <persRef ref="buchanan-thomas">T. M.
				Buchanan</persRef> in active service. He told me that as there were many more Midshipmen than
				could be employed, the rule of the Department was when they were desirous of having
				their turn for service to order them to one of the places of Depot. And as the order
				is directed to them there, they must go to the place at their own expence to receive
				it. That as there is no immediate opportunity for employing midshipmen in active
				service, there being no vessel prepared for Sea, except the Congress Frigate, which
				is to take <persRef ref="graham-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Graham</persRef> to Rio de Janeiro, and thence
				proceed to the Indian Ocean, and has already more than her compliment of Officers,
				young M’Kean must either wait till the Constellation and the Peacock can be got
				ready, at Norfolk, which will be in five or six weeks; or go the Boston and go on
				board the Independence, where numbers of Midshipmen are stationed, and where a
				school is kept; under the direction of <persRef ref="bainbridge-william">Commodore Bainbridge</persRef>. I spoke to Homans
				concerning <persRef ref="clark-charles">Lieutenant Clarke’s</persRef> pay—of which <persRef ref="clark-susanna">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Clarke</persRef>
				says that two Quarters and half a month are due. He promised to enquire and let me
				know. <persRef ref="appleton-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> J. J. Appleton</persRef>, Secretary of the Legation to
				Rio de Janiero, came and took leave— He goes to morrow to Baltimore, to make
				preparations for M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Graham and for himself. They are to
				sail from Annapolis; but their necessary Sea-Stores and provisions must be procured
				at Baltimore. I asked M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Appleton to see <persRef ref="glenn-elias">Glenn</persRef> the
				District Attorney and converse with him upon the subject of the Letter I wrote him
				last week; and also to collect and report to me any other information concerning the
				Piratical privateers from that place. I commenced preparing Instructions for M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Graham, but the State of our Affairs with the
				Portuguese Government at Rio de Janeiro has been entangled in such a snarl by
				mismanagement and neglect that suitable Instructions cannot be given, without a
				review of our political and commercial relations both with Brazil and Portugal, for
				the last ten years. For this, it is impossible for me to find time— I have indeed
				found by experience that the preparation of Instructions for a Minister going out on
				a foreign Mission, is one of the most arduous, and difficult duties of a Secretary
				of State— It requires a knowledge of all the important political and commercial
				relations subsisting between the two Countries— A reference to all the transactions
				depending between them— A Speculative foresight of measures to be recommended to the
				Minister calculated to promote the Interests of his own Country, and its friendship
				and good understanding with that to which he is going— A mind fertile in expedients
				to suggest useful hints to the Minister— I have never yet prepared Instructions for
				a Minister, without feeling my deficiency in almost all these particulars— Without
				seeing how much more usefully I could discharge my duties to the public, with more
				profound and extensive knowledge; a quicker and clearer conception, and a more
				inventive imagination. Our relations with Portugal and Brazil, have not been well
				cultivated— Their importance has not been duly estimated— <persRef ref="sumter-thomas">The Minister</persRef> who has been
				there these ten years, was not a fortunate choice. His own temper is not happy— He
				has been repeatedly involved in quarrels of personal punctilio, even with the
				members of the Royal family. He is excessively argumentative, and spins out every
				thing into discussion, without ever bringing any thing to a close. Many occurrences
				excessively untoward have happened also, not imputable to him, but which have placed
				him in situations of great embarrassment while they implicated more or less the
				harmony between the two Countries. Then these Baltimore piracies, which the
				Government have not been able effectually to suppress; have exasperated both the
				People and Government against the United States; and some arbitrary seizures and
				oppressive imprisonments of American Citizens, on the other side have produced so
				much ill blood between the two Countries that it has festered into all but actual
				hostility. Such are the circumstances under which M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Graham is going out as Minister to Rio de Janeiro, and for which I am to prepare his
				Instructions. To cool down all this inflammation, to turn all this wormwood into
				balm, to reconcile the two Governments and Nations with each other, and to place
				their commercial relations with each other upon a footing of reciprocity and
				equality, are objects important to this Country, and ought to be those of M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Graham’s mission. To prepare his Instructions
				therefore I want much time and shall have very little— I found I could make no
				progress in them this day.</p>
		</div>
	</div>
	
	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-17">
		<head>17 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-17"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Press</note>
		</bibl>
		
		<div type="docbody">
			
			<p><pb type="ms" n="89"/><dateline>17. V:45.</dateline> There was a heavy thunder-shower this morning about
				an hour before day light— I had wasted the last Evening in reading newspapers, and
				expected to have this day a long Morning to write; but by seven O’Clock, <persRef ref="cardelli-pietro">Cardelli</persRef>
				came in, and kept me two hours or more in talking of his Affairs. He brought with
				him the Bust of the <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef> which he has just finished— It is a good likeness, and
				a work of real merit. He is now anxious to take the Busts of the late Presidents
				<persRef ref="jefferson-thomas">Jefferson</persRef>, and <persRef ref="madison-james">Madison</persRef>, and I promised to write to them and ask their consent to sit
				to him— His object is to have moulds of them made, and to take casts from them for
				sale. He is so impatient under the mortification of having been compelled to work
				for bread, upon the ornamental work, the friezes and cornices at the Capitol, that
				he had resolved now to abandon it altogether and rely upon the income from the sale
				of his Busts for his support. He had even drawn up in French an advertisement which
				he proposed to have published in the Newspapers, mentioning his having executed the
				Busts of the Secretary of State and the <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">French Minister</persRef>, and afterwards of the
				President; and then adding in all the naïveté of his feelings that if M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Cardelli had for sometime been sacrificed, and forced
				to work upon ornaments at the Capitol, these Busts would at least prove that M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Cardelli was an artist, who knew how to work. I
				advised him in the first place not to give up his ornamental work, which is a
				certainty, until he should have made it sure that his busts would give him a better
				support— To wait till he should find them realizing profit for him— As yet they gave
				him only expectations— We had a proverb that a bird in the hand is worth two in the
				bush. (He said the Italian proverb was, the egg of today is better than the hen of
				to-morrow) In the second place I advised him to say nothing in his advertisement
				about being sacrificed, and working upon ornaments. For it would make him dangerous
				enemies of some who are now his friends and may be made useful friends— I advised
				him to invite <persRef ref="lane-samuel">Col<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> Lane</persRef> to see his Bust of the
				President; and to invite the <persRef ref="gales-joseph">Editors of the National</persRef> <persRef ref="seaton-william">Intelligencer</persRef> and <persRef ref="elliot-jonathan">City Gazette</persRef>
				to look at it; and if they liked it, to mention it as an Editorial notice in their
				Papers— He said he thought he would follow my advice— He is very anxious too about
				the Property of his Busts; and very fearful they will be pirated from him by the
				moulding workmen. I told him it would perhaps be best for him not to publish them,
				until the next Session of Congress, when a Law may be proposed like the Act of
				Parliament which was obtained for <persRef ref="nollekens-joseph">Nollekens</persRef> in England extending the principles of
				copy-right to works of Sculpture. I cannot but admire the sentiment of honour and
				love of fame, displayed by this man, in his deep distress. The humiliation which he
				feels at being degraded from an artist to a workman of ornaments, and the impatience
				with which he longs to emerge from this condition so unworthy of his talents— At the
				Office, I compared the proof sheet of <persRef ref="binns-john">Binns’s</persRef> Copper-Plate Declaration of
				Independence; and wrote the Certificate which he has requested of the correctness of
				the fac-simile signatures— The original itself has suffered by the handling of the
				Engraver to take these fac-similes— <persRef key="smith-william-steuben">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persRef> and <persRef key="smith-catherine-johnson">M<hi
					rend="superscript">rs</hi> W. S. Smith</persRef> spent the Evening here; and <persRef ref="forbes-john">J. M. Forbes</persRef>—
				It was therefore another Evening lost to me for all purposes of writing.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-18">
		<head>18 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-18"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Bank of the United States</note>
			<note type="subject">Panic of 1819</note>
			<note type="subject">Recreation</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>18. VI:</dateline> I had this morning uninterrupted, and employed as much
				of it in writing as I can usually rescue from the waste of reading newspapers— At
				noon I walked to the Navy-Yard wharf, and had a glance again at the line of Battle
				ship Columbus; returning by the way of Greenleaf’s point and over the Tiber. The
				weather was sultry and I heard distant Thunder to the South. On returning from my
				walk, after reading the Letters by the Mail which were few, I resumed writing till
				the hour of dinner, and thus provided a substitute for the Evening task. <persRef key="smith-catherine-johnson">M<hi
					rend="superscript">rs.</hi> W. S. Smith</persRef> dined with us; and <persRef key="smith-william-steuben">Smith</persRef> and <persRef ref="bailey-john">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Bailey</persRef> spent part of the Evening here. The President
				of the Bank of the United States, <persRef ref="cheves-langdon">Langdon Cheves</persRef> arrived in the City the Evening
				before last, and this day left it upon his return to Philadelphia. His appearance
				here has given rise to various rumours and surmizes. Its real cause is the tottering
				situation of the Bank, which will very shortly be reduced to the alternative of
				calling in all its Notes and trading on those of other Banks, or of stopping
				payment.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-19">
		<head>19 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-19"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">American Revolution</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>19. V:45.</dateline> <persRef ref="cardelli-pietro">Cardelli</persRef> came this morning, and took away the Busts of
				the <persRef key="monroe-james">President </persRef>and the <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">French Minister</persRef>—and mine; with the intention of shewing them
				to <persRef ref="lane-samuel">Col<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> Lane</persRef>, the Commissioner of the Public Buildings.
				At the Office I was collecting the materials for preparing Instructions for <persRef ref="graham-john">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> John Graham</persRef>, when he came in himself, and <pb
					type="ms" n="90"/>I had a conversation with him of two hours; partly upon the
				public concerns of his mission, and partly upon his personal relations with it.
				Graham is in many respects well qualified for this Mission— He is prudent and
				industrious and having been chief Clerk in the Department of State, during the whole
				of <persRef ref="madison-james">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Madison’s</persRef> Administration has much experience of
				our diplomatic affairs generally. He appears however to have formed an idea of
				responsibility somewhat timid— He wished to have every thing prescribed to him in
				his Instructions with a minuteness and precision hardly attainable, and is quite
				alarmed, at the representation that I have made to him of the state of our relations
				with the Brazilian Government— He says he has had a conversation upon the subject
				with the <persRef ref="correa-joseph">Abbé Correa</persRef>, and he has apprehensions that Correa’s Reports to his own
				Government have a tendency to inflame their animosity against this Country, though
				he assured him of the contrary— I suppose that the Abbe does not intend they should,
				but they may have that effect by the statements of facts which his duty requires him
				to make— I told Graham that our difficulties with the Portuguese were owing partly
				to circumstances which may be remedied, and partly to causes originating with
				themselves and which we cannot remove— With regard to the privateers illegally
				fitted out in our Ports, we have taken and shall continue to take every measure in
				our power to suppress them— I mentioned the Letter I had written to the <persRef ref="glenn-elias">District
					Attorney at Baltimore</persRef>, and the request I had made to <persRef ref="appleton-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Appleton</persRef> to call upon him there and to collect and report information upon the
				subject. I gave him for his perusal the copy of the Memoir presented by <persRef ref="desousaholstein-pedro">Count
				Palmella</persRef> to the Congress at Aix La Chapelle; and the last Note of the Abbé Correa to
				me in both of which there is a demand that all armed vessels sailing under the flag
				and Commissions from <persRef ref="artigas-jose">Artigas</persRef> should be declared Pirates— I observed that the
				European allies had not complied with this request; neither could we; for reasons
				which I gave him at large, and which will be set forth in his Instructions— He said
				it was impossible he feared to give satisfaction to the Portuguese Government on
				this point— But we must give them sound reasons for the principles we assume; do
				them justice, wherein their complaints are well founded, but adhere to it also when
				it operates against them— We must trust to the healing virtue of Justice and
				friendly intentions, if these fail to restore harmony—the fault will not be ours;
				and more we cannot do— Graham spoke to me also about his personal concerns as
				connected with the Mission— The expences of the voyage, and the allowances for
				contingent expences there. This is a very troublesome part of the arrangements to be
				made with all the Ministers that go abroad. The account for contingencies has a
				perpetual tendency to increase— The general rule for the commencement of Salaries is
				from the time when the Minister leaves home to proceed upon his Mission. But the
				exceptions which are in fact taking place of the rule, allow the Salary to commence
				from the time of the Appointment— It has been so, in the cases of <persRef ref="rush-richard">Rush</persRef>, <persRef ref="campbell-george">Campbell</persRef> and
				<persRef ref="forsyth-john">Forsyth</persRef>; and Graham now claims the same— He says that he kept his establishment
				here, only from the expectation which had been given him of receiving this
				appointment; which was offered him at the time when he went to South America, and
				that he has scarcely ceased being in the public Service. He also claims an allowance
				for Office Rent— This allowance was first made to me at London where an Office was
				indispensable, and where I actually had one— It was consequently allowed to M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Rush— It is now claimed by <persRef ref="gallatin-albert">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Gallatin</persRef> at Paris, and M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Campbell at S<hi
					rend="superscript">t.</hi> Petersburg, on the ground that they appropriate a
				room in their houses for an Office, and that it makes them want a larger house, and
				pay higher rent than would otherwise be necessary. Graham says that at Rio de
				Janeiro, it is impossible to live in the City. There are no inhabitable houses
				there; <persRef ref="sumter-thomas">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sumter</persRef> lives two or three miles out of it, and
				has not a glass window in his house. They dined with him one day; and a shower of
				rain came and drove them from their Seats at the dinner table— Living in the
				Country, it will be necessary to have an Office in the City, and the expence of
				living, and of every thing at Rio de Janeiro is very exorbitant— He also enquired
				whether under the allowance for Newspapers, he could not charge for one or two
				English Newspapers— This I answered decidedly in the negative— And as to the other
				claims, told him they must wait for the decision of the President— He complained of
				the expences of the Voyage; and enquired if under the obligation of providing his
				own Stores, he could not make use of the common ships Stores, for his family— I said
				I believed not— He asked what the usual arrangement was, with respect to the
				Ministers Stores, with the Captains of the Public Ships— I told him I had never been
				in a public Ship since our Revolutionary War, but that when I went to Russia in
				1809. the Essex Frigate had been ordered round to Boston to take me, and <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">my</persRef> <persRef ref="adams-charles2">family</persRef>,
				though she did not reach Boston till the day after I had sailed. And on that
				occasion, he Graham himself had written to me that the usage was for the Captain of
				the ship to provide all the Stores, and for the Minister to pay the Captain the
				common price which a passage would cost in a merchant vessel— He said that if he had
				written me such a Letter, it must have been under Instructions— That they had
				endeavoured to introduce this as a usage, but it <pb type="ms" n="91"/>never had
				been so established— He had been desirous that <persRef ref="henley-john">Captain Henley</persRef> should provide his
				Stores for him, and had written requesting him to that effect; but he had declined—
				I asked him when he could be ready to go; as the frigate is now ready at Annapolis
				and waiting for him— He said he could be ready on Thursday; but would be glad to
				have two or three days longer for preparation. I told him I should probably not be
				ready with his Instructions before the last of the week, and asked him to call at
				the Office again on Thursday, when I should perhaps have an answer from Glenn— He
				promised to come, and said he would be glad if the Instructions should then be ready
				to read them over with me— He is but just recovering from the wound of the operation
				upon his thigh, and looks indifferently. M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams spent
				this Evening with her <persRef key="smith-catherine-johnson">Sister Smith</persRef>.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-20">
		<head>20 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-20"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Bank of the United States</note>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Louisiana Purchase</note>
			<note type="subject">Panic of 1819</note>
			<note type="subject">Steam Power</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>20. VI:</dateline> I received a Message this Morning from <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford</persRef>, requesting me to call at his Office as I
				should be going to mine— I called accordingly, and he mentioned to me that <persRef ref="cheves-langdon">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Cheves</persRef> the President of the United States Bank had
				been here— He came on Friday Evening, and left the City on Sunday to return. He had
				been here ostensibly to make some arrangement with the Bank of Columbia; but really
				for a consultation with him, upon the Affairs of the Bank. He brought the Resolution
				adopted unanimously by the Directors, on the 12<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>to
				decline receiving even for public payments the Bills of their Branches except at the
				places where they are made payable— But offering otherwise any facilities for making
				the necessary remittances from the branch to branch— Crawford said they had taken
				the legal opinions of <persRef ref="binny-horace">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Binney</persRef> at Philadelphia, and
				<persRef ref="pinkney-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Pinkney</persRef> at Baltimore; on the question whether<hi
					rend="italic">the</hi>
				<hi rend="italic">Government</hi> was bound to receive the payment of duties, the
				bills at one branch which are issued and on their face made payable at another— The
				opinion was that they were. Crawford added that his own opinion, and that of the
				<persRef ref="wirt-william">Attorney General, Wirt</persRef>, was the same— The question is upon the Act of Congress of
				10. April 1816. incorporating the Bank of the United States, the fourteenth Section.
				I had given a different opinion at the last Conversation with Crawford; and although
				very much staggered by that of four eminent lawyers to the contrary, I still cling
				to my own. But Crawford is apprehensive, not only that the refusal to receive the
				Bills, would excite clamours against the Government, but that the Merchants would
				tender the Bills, and if refused wait the issue of a lawsuit, which would delay the
				collection of the revenue, more than the present state of the Treasury can bear. But
				he said the Merchants East of Philadelphia, where only this pressure is felt were
				now in the habit of paying their bonds for duties in the Bills of distant branches,
				and then demanding Specie for debentures on the goods of the same importation. He
				thought he could stop this, by the 80<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>Section of the
				Collection Law of 2 March 1799. which authorizes the payment of the debentures, out
				of the proceeds of duties arising on the importation of the goods re-exported— He
				said even this would raise a clamour, and <persRef ref="jones-edward">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Jones</persRef> his
				chief Clerk, had advised him to say nothing about it, and leave it to be battled out
				between the Collectors and the Merchants— But even in that case the question would
				ultimately be referred to him by the Collector; and he should be obliged to decide
				it. He thought it therefore most candid and prudent to give at once his directions
				to the Collectors, and he read me the Letter he had written— He then observed that
					M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Cheves had been desirous of seeing me; but he
				Crawford had been unwell, and could not come with him to introduce him to me— And
				Cheves was obliged to go away on Sunday. The Bank were desirous of making a contract
				with the Spanish Government, for transporting specie for them from Mexico to Spain.
				They were disposed to appoint <persRef ref="forsyth-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth</persRef> as their agent
				to transact this business for them; and wished to know, whether, there would be any
				objection to it, on the part of this Government— I told him, I did not know that
				there could be any objection, if M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth would do the
				business without compensation— But if he was to be paid, it would be liable to two
				difficulties— It would give dissatisfaction to the Public, that a Minister of the
				United States should at the same time, be an agent of the Bank—and it would give
				discontent to our other Ministers in Europe, who would immediately compare their own
				scanty compensations with the double wages received by M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Forsyth— He said the idea of the Bank only was that Forsyth should make
				the proposal to the Spanish Government; and if they accepted it that the
				arrangements for the execution should be settled with the Chargé d’Affaires of Spain
				here— There was also another object that they had in view— They wanted to make an
				arrangement, for postponing the payment of the second half of the Louisiana
				Stock—which if accomplished must be <pb type="ms" n="92"/>done in the form of a
				loan— They had proposed to employ for that purpose, <persRef ref="sheldon-daniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Sheldon</persRef>, the Secretary of the Legation at Paris; and to request him to go to
				Amsterdam and London, to make the agreement with the Bankers at those places who
				hold or have the management of the Stock— But this of course implied that Sheldon
				should be paid a liberal compensation— I told him that I should be very sorry to
				deprive either Sheldon or Forsyth of any fair and honourable profit, but there
				appeared to me the same objections though not to the same extent in this case as in
				that of Forsyth. He said he thought I was right. That M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Cheves had proposed to him that <persRef ref="lowndes-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lowndes</persRef> who is gone
				to Europe, should be employed to negotiate this new Loan; but to that, he Crawford
				had objected. Lowndes was the Atlas upon whom alone the support of the Bank rested
				in Congress— He had been its only disinterested defender in the House of
				Representatives at the last Session— The attack upon the Bank would undoubtedly be
				renewed in the next Congress— It was essential therefore that Lowndes should remain
				unconnected by personal interest with the Bank; that the weight of his influence in
				its favour may remain unimpaired. I asked him what necessity there was for the Bank
				to employ any special agent for this transaction? why they could not do it by direct
				correspondence with the Bankers?— he said because it was so late, they would
				scarcely have time. I told him that I had acted myself on the principle of declining
				any compensation for a private agency, while I was abroad in the public service; and
				mentioned the case of <persRef ref="fulton-robert">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Fulton’s</persRef> application for a
				Steam-boat privilege in Russia— Crawford said he thought the principle correct;
				though M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> William Pinkney had been Agent for the State
				of Maryland, when he was a Commissioner in England— I said I saw no impropriety in
				that; as there could be no collision between the duties of the two Offices; and
				there was no disparity of consideration between them— But it was impossible to be in
				Europe at once a Public Minister, and an Exchange Broker, or private agent with
				percentage Commissions, without injury to the dignity and decorum of the public
				service— I had been told that M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Pinkney upon his last
				mission to Naples, was to have received from the merchants whose claims he was sent
				to assert, and negotiate for, a per Centage upon the whole amount that he might have
				obtained— So I had heard at the time of the Mission; I had then thought, and still
				think it improper— He said he thought it very improper; and had thought so when
				first informed of it— That the Mission to Naples was the first nomination rejected;
				and soon afterwards he called one morning upon <persRef ref="madison-james">President Madison</persRef>, who told him he
				was going to do something, the propriety of which he himself doubted—to re-nominate
				Pinkney for the mission to Naples— I suppose said Crawford you have some new and
				additional information— No— But some of the Senators who voted against the
				appointment, have changed their minds, and pressingly urge a new Nomination— The
				fact Crawford said was that the federal merchants at Baltimore interested in the
				claims had had a meeting; and sent a remonstrance to the Maryland Senators,
				informing them that the expence of maintaining the federal ascendancy in Baltimore
				and Maryland had fallen upon them, and that if their interests were sacrificed by
				the rejection of the Mission to Naples, they would no longer support that expence,
				and the federal party in Maryland must sink— Crawford said that when the vote on the
				second nomination of Pinkney was taken in Senate, <persRef ref="harper-robert-goodloe">Harper</persRef> then one of the Senators
				from Maryland was absent; but the vote was turned by <persRef ref="goldsborough-robert">Goldsborough</persRef>, the other
				Maryland Senator, and <persRef ref="fromentin-eligius">Fromentin</persRef> who though Senator from Louisiana, had long resided
				at Baltimore, and might almost be considered as belonging there— And so the
				appointment was made, which proved a worse than useless one in its result— From
				Crawford’s Office, I went to my own, and consumed all the Office hours in examining
				papers, to prepare Instructions for J. Graham; without writing a line— I was able
				however to write a couple of hours this Evening— A rare occurrence.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-21">
		<head>21 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-21"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams Family Finances</note>
			<note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>21. V:</dateline> <persRef ref="cardelli-pietro">Cardelli</persRef> came this morning to remind me of my promise to
				write to <persRef ref="jefferson-thomas">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Jefferson</persRef>, and <persRef ref="madison-james">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Madison</persRef>, requesting them to sit to him for their Busts; and to tell me
				that he had concluded to take my advice, and return to his work upon ornaments at
				the Capitol, until he shall have a certainty of profit from his more noble
				employment of taking Busts— But he said that after his death; nobody that should
				ever look at the flowers in the Cornices of the Capitol would say—there!—that’s the
				work of Cardelli. He said <persRef ref="lane-samuel">Col<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> Lane</persRef> was much satisfied
				with the Bust of the President and had taken it himself to <persRef ref="monroe-elizabeth">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>rs</hi> Monroe</persRef>, who was also well pleased with it— And M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Hay had asked him his price for Casts from the Bust. He had fixed the
				price at twelve dollars, which <persRef ref="hay-george">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hay</persRef> said was very
				cheap, and had told him that he would have many subscribers for them at that price,
				at Richmond— He complained that the <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">French Minister</persRef> had not treated him well, and
				would not understand the price of a single Bust must be a very different thing from
				that of the Casts taken from it.— I called and renewed one of my Notes at the
				Metropolis Bank— The rest of the day till five at my Office without interruption,
				and made some progress in drafting Instructions for <persRef ref="graham-john">J. Graham</persRef>— My <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef> received a
				Letter which gives us both great uneasiness from our son <persRef ref="adams-george">George</persRef>, who was at Quincy, by leave of absence from College <pb type="ms" n="93"/>for a stricture at his
				breast—proceeding as he says from over-application. He was better, and intending to
				return, as last Monday to Cambridge— My wife herself was this Evening very
				unwell.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-22">
		<head>22 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-22"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>22. V:30.</dateline> <persRef ref="hutchinson-israel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Israel Pemberton
				Hutchinson</persRef> our Consul at Lisbon, was waiting at my Office to see me; when I went
				there this morning— He has a leave of absence from his Post for six Months, and
				arrived a few days since, at Philadelphia. He brought me a Letter of Introduction
				from <persRef ref="dallas-george">T. M. Dallas</persRef>; while he was with me <persRef ref="graham-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> J. Graham</persRef>
				came in. Hutchinson gave me many particulars of information concerning the commerce
				between the United States and Portugal; particularly Lisbon— He says that
				Merchandize imported in Portuguese or in British Vessels pays duties of 15 per Cent
				ad valorem; but in American Vessels 24 per Cent to the public Treasury; besides
				three per Cent local duties and three per Cent to the House of Braganza— 30 per Cent
				in all, and precisely double what is paid by the Portuguese, and even by the
				English. All this is by the commercial Treaty with Great-Britain of 1810— Our
				commerce therefore stands no chance for competition with the English, in Articles
				which they as well as we produce. Yet we carry on there a large trade of wheat and
				flour, fish and Oil— The duty upon this last Article is so small that although we
				pay double what the english pay, it amounts to so little that we are enabled to
				stand the competition with them— The tariff is formed upon a value of the Article,
				estimated a century ago, and it reduces the duty of 15 per Cent, to a cent a Gallon,
				or thereabouts— But a new tariff is expected to come out very shortly; upon an
				estimate approaching the real value of the articles; in which case the double duties
				will annihilate our share of the commerce— This will be the more mortifying, because
				the demand for fish-oil is yearly increasing, from its being substituted instead of
				the olive-oil which the Country itself formerly produced— The Olive-trees are
				perishing with some disease— But the British are much disliked there, and the
				Officers are constantly endeavouring to evade the stipulations which exempt them
				from paying the double duties— Two years ago, the Americans, were in high favour
				among the Portuguese; but now they were all deeply embittered against us, by the
				losses they have suffered from the captures of the piratical privateers fitted out
				in our Ports— Several of these privateers have been for weeks together cruizing off
				the rock of Lisbon; sending in their Compliments to their acquaintance, and taking
				every Portuguese vessel they could catch— The situation of Portugal itself is very
				distressing in consequence of the removal of the Royal Family to Brazil; by which
				Portugal is now treated as a Colony; drained of her substance and resources for
				remittances to the <persRef ref="john-vi">King</persRef>, and of the incomes from the Estates of all the nobility,
				who followed his Court to this Hemisphere. The aggravation of the tonnage duties
				however which by the decree of 25. April last was to have commenced its operation
				from the first of November, did not then take effect; and had not when Hutchinson
				left Lisbon in February: being postponed in consequence of representations made by
				him and by the <persRef ref="ward-edward">English Charge d’Affaires</persRef>— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Graham
				remained with me after Hutchinson had withdrawn; and I read to him the Draft of
				Instructions as far as I had prepared them. And enlarged upon them in some
				particulars which it will be expedient to omit from them— I made the draft of a
				Letter to the <persRef ref="correa-joseph">Abbe Correa</persRef>; and wasted the whole Evening in the perusal of
				Newspapers.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-23">
		<head>23 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-23"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">African Americans</note>
			<note type="subject">Colonization Movements</note>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Slave Trade</note>
			<note type="subject">Slavery</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>23. V:30.</dateline> Paid a visit to <persRef ref="hutchinson-israel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Hutchinson </persRef>who lodges at <persRef ref="gibson-unknown">Gibson’s</persRef>. He spoke to me of the Settlement of his Accounts;
				and of the inconvenience of our system of providing for the relief of distressed
				American Seamen in foreign Ports; by exacting payment of three Months wages for
				every Seamen discharged from a vessel— It operated very unjustly he said; sometimes
				upon the owners and Master of the vessel who was obliged to discharge men, hired at
				very high wages; and sometimes upon the Seamen themselves—as the Masters to avoid
				the payment of the wages would drive them by ill-treatment to desert. The English
				system of providing for the same charge he thought was much better. It was by
				levying to trifling duty upon the vessels; and although trifling, it paid not only
				the expence of relieving the Seamen in distress, but also that of supporting a
				Church and a Clergyman— I requested him to throw these ideas upon paper, and address
				them to me in a Letter, which he promised— It is one of the Subjects, susceptible of
				much improvement for the public benefit, and to which my attention ought to be
				given— At the Office, a <persRef ref="maury-ruston">son</persRef> of <persRef ref="maury-james">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Maury</persRef> <pb type="ms"
					n="94"/>the Consul at Liverpool, came and was introduced to me—not the same <persRef ref="maury-matthew">who
				was here last Winter</persRef>; and who is now with <persRef ref="jefferson-thomas">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Jefferson</persRef>
				at Monticello; but a younger brother, just arrived from England. <persRef key="smith-william-steuben">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> W. S. Smith</persRef> came upon business from <persRef ref="clark-susanna">M<hi
						rend="superscript">rs</hi> Clark</persRef> whom he saw last Evening— <persRef ref="caldwell-elias">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> E. B. Caldwell</persRef> came to make enquiry, whether the
				President had left directions with me, concerning the employment of an Island
				belonging to <persRef ref="custis-george">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Custis</persRef>, near Norfolk, as a place of
				deposit for the coloured people, who under the act of Congress of the last Session
				are to be sent to Africa— It had not been mentioned to me by the <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef> at-all—
				Caldwell said the <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">Secretary of the Treasury</persRef> had referred him to me; and I referred
				him to the Departments of War and the Navy. With these interruptions, I had a heavy
				Mail of despatches and Letters; which consumed the time, so that I had scarcely an
				hour left for continuing the draft of Instructions, to <persRef ref="graham-john">J. Graham</persRef>— My <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef> spent the
				Evening abroad; at her sister <persRef ref="frye-carolina">Frye’s</persRef>. I wrote half a page; drowsily and with
				pain.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-24">
		<head>24 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-24"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Anti-Slavery Movements</note>
			<note type="subject">Bank of the United States</note>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Emancipation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Louisiana Purchase</note>
			<note type="subject">Panic of 1819</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
			<note type="subject">Science and Technology</note>
			<note type="subject">Slave Trade</note>
			<note type="subject">Slavery</note>
			<note type="subject">West, The</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>24. V:30.</dateline> Eclipse of the Sun, as he rose— I saw its beginning;
				but after a few minutes the Sun passed under a Cloud and the Eclipse was no longer
				perceptible. It was of about 4 1/2 digits and terminated about half past six
				O’Clock— I this morning completed the task of bringing up the arrears of Journal,
				which on the 11<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>of March were of a full Month— From
				this moment I take a new start. Called on <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford</persRef> at
				his Office. He had a Letter from <persRef ref="cheves-langdon">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Cheves</persRef> the President
				of the Bank since his return to Philadelphia. The Directors had resolved to employ
				<persRef ref="sheldon-daniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> D. Sheldon</persRef> to negotiate the reloan of the
				remaining Louisiana Stock— They passed the Resolution before receiving M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford’s Letter written in consequence of my last
				Conversation with him, stating that the propriety of appointing him for that agency
				was doubtful. He asked me now, as the appointment had been made, whether it would be
				necessary to insist upon its being revoked; or whether it might be allowed, on
				condition that only Sheldon’s expences in negotiating the business should be paid;
				or with the allowance of a further compensation— I told M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Crawford that I did not think it necessary to persist in objecting to
				the employment of Sheldon for this affair— The principal objection in my mind had
				been to the blending the character of a Public Minister of the United States, with
				that of an Exchange Broker for the Bank— It would not apply so strongly to the case
				of a Secretary of Legation, and in this instance I should withdraw it altogether; on
				the decisive consideration that the Government itself has an interest in the success
				of the negotiation— But it must be with the understanding that it will take Sheldon
				from his proper service only for a short time; and that he shall make an arrangement
				satisfactory to <persRef ref="gallatin-albert">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gallatin</persRef>, for supplying his place
				during his absence. On these conditions, I thought he might go; and besides the
				payment of his expences might receive a reasonable compensation from the Bank, for
				the service— I then returned to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford the Letter
				from the <persRef ref="mcculloch-james">Collector at Baltimore</persRef> to him, concerning the Spanish, king’s brig, brought
				into Baltimore by <persRef ref="danel-john">Daniels</persRef>, and which he had sent me; and I read to him the Letter
				from the <persRef ref="glenn-elias">District Attorney Glenn</persRef> to me, concerning the prosecution of these
				Baltimore Pirates. Glenn says that the vigilance and zeal of the subordinate
				custom-house Officers, and of the Captains of the Revenue Cutters might be usefully
				spirited and invigorated for the effectual suppression of this mischief. Crawford
				promised to give Instructions accordingly— I told him I had received another Letter
				from Baltimore, from <persRef ref="appleton-john">J. J. Appleton</persRef> with further information, upon the subject—and a
				Note from <persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</persRef>, the Spanish Minister; demanding the
				restoration of the King’s Brig— I thought this was a regular and correct
				application, but I had some difficulty as to the mode of proceeding proper for the
				case— Whether the <persRef ref="barnabau-juan">Spanish Consul</persRef> could libel the vessel as belonging to the <persRef ref="ferdinand-vii">king of
				Spain</persRef>— Or whether we could direct a seizure of her by the Government, for the
				purpose of restoring her to Spain— we considered this question, and concluded that
				the best course would be for the Spanish Consul to libel the vessel— Crawford
				observed it was unfortunate that the <persRef ref="wirt-william">Attorney General</persRef> was now absent— I asked M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford how the Treasury stood at this time; it being
				a period of great pecuniary pressure; and embarrassment. He said there were in the
				Months of February and March, great deficiency in the receipts from Norfolk in
				Virginia, but none considerable, from the other Sea Ports— But from the Western
				Country the receipts from the Sales of Lands had very greatly fallen off, and were
				dwindling down to nothing— The situation of the United States at this time in regard
				to their commerce, revenue, manufactures, agriculture, banking Institutions, and
				political economy generally is such that the most special attention to it is due
				from those who are in the public service and most especially from the members of the
				Administration— I deeply lament that my time is so much absorbed by other, and more
				immediate and indispensable duties that I have scarcely any left for thoroughly
				investigating this— In the midst of Peace, and of partial prosperity, we are
				approaching to a crisis which will <pb type="ms" n="95"/>shake the Union to its
				centre— I see violent and threatening symptoms of the disease, without knowing where
				to look for the remedy. I asked Crawford what foundation there was for certain
				reports very unfavourable to the reputation of <persRef ref="johnson-richard">Col<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> R.
				M. Johnson</persRef>, the late Representative from Kentucky— He said he had a Letter from a
				<persRef ref="benton-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Benton</persRef>, who was a thorough-going Man, which
				contained all the information that he had on the subject; and he gave it to me to
				take with me to read— He said he fully believed that Johnson was an honest, and well
				meaning man; but he was so excessively weak and credulous, that he suffered knaves
				and swindlers to work upon him till they destroyed all his moral perceptions; all
				capacity to discriminate between right and wrong; and made him do just what they
				pleased. He had thus suffered himself to be drawn into unwarrantable Banking
				Speculations by a man named <persRef ref="prentiss-unknown">Prentiss</persRef> from Boston or that neighbourhood; and one
				<persRef ref="smith-unknown4">Smith</persRef>, a nephew of the <persRef ref="smith-samuel3">late President of Princeton College</persRef>.— I took the papers with
				me and read them in the course of the day. My opinion of Johnson after reading them,
				is less charitable than that of Crawford— I neither think him so imbecil nor so
				honest; under the guise of a generous, warmhearted, affectionate man, he is a mere
				unprincipled speculator— Let me not lose the feeling of indulgence for human
				frailty. When these facts come once to be generally known, Johnson’s character and
				reputation will be blasted. It is indeed probably already ruined in his own State— I
				regret it, for from the part which he took in the House of Representatives the last
				Session, and the relations which it introduced between him and me, I had formed a
				more favourable opinion of him. As I was going to my office, I was overtaken by a
				person named <persRef ref="heron-unknown">Heron</persRef>, who followed me, with a Letter from <persRef ref="foster-alexander">A. W. Foster</persRef> of Greensburgh;
				and a model in brass and steal of a machine, invented by him, being an improvement
				on the mode of applying power to wheel machinery— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Foster has a high idea of the importance of his invention for which he wishes a
				patent here, and information how to obtain a patent in various European Countries. I
				advised M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Heron to deposit his model in the patent
				office, and to get a drawing of it to be made, and also there deposited— A <persRef ref="haw-john">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Haw</persRef>, residing in the neighbourhood of Georgetown, came
				with two Letters; one for his <persRef ref="haw-unknown">Son</persRef>, in South America, and the other for <persRef ref="forsyth-samuel">D<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth</persRef> an American, residing at Angostura— The son at
				the age of 19. had followed the Fortunes of <persRef ref="macgregor-gregor">M’Gregor</persRef>, and accompanied him to
				Amelia-Island— Left it soon after M’Gregor; went to Angostura; entered <persRef ref="bolivar-simon">Bolivar’s</persRef>
				army; and in January 1818. was appointed a Captain of Artillery. His father said he
				had received a Letter from him written at that time; and with a tear glistening in
				his eye, added he had never heard from him since; and feared he should never hear
				from him again— I could not tell him my feelings at this statement; lest they should
				aggravate his own—but I promised him to take care that the Letters should be
				forwarded to D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Forsyth— <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Hyde de Neuville</persRef>, the French Minister came to ask for an order to the Collector at
				Baltimore, for the restoration of certain French property, piratically captured, and
				libelled by the <persRef ref="angelucci-unknown">French Consul</persRef>— A parcel of the same property he said had been thus
				restored to the <persRef ref="unknown12">French Consul at Alexandria</persRef>; and M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Crawford thought it could be done in like manner at Baltimore—but de Neuville
				thought it would require a short Letter from me to the District Attorney, or to the
				Judge— I told him that according to our Institutions; it would be improper for any
				Member of the Executive administration, to write to the Judge; but if he would write
				me setting forth the facts, I would then, if there would be any propriety in the
				measure write to the district attorney concerning it— I returned him the copy of
				<persRef ref="desousaholstein-pedro">Count Palmella’s</persRef> Note which he had lent me, and of which he consented that I should
				furnish M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> J. Graham with a copy. He then referred to
				the Answer I had sent him to his proposal for declaring some half a dozen Piracies,
				additional to those already recognized by the Law of Nations— He was not altogether
				satisfied with my answer to it. He admitted however, that there might be some
				inconvenience in constituting for many new Capital Offences— He asked if I had any
				late news from France, and appeared to be quite uneasy at the accounts of the
				addition of fifty or sixty new members to the house of Peers— I had nothing recent
				from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gallatin, but lent De Neuville, all the latest
				newspapers that I had received from France. We had also some Conversation respecting
				the new <pb type="ms" n="96"/>Treaties of Great Britain with Spain, Portugal and the
				Netherlands, allowing a mutual right of search to armed vessels, and joint Courts
				for trying Slave traders. I told him I was glad that France and Russia at Aix La
				Chapelle had refused acceding to this principle of mutual search in time of Peace—
				But he thought it would not be inadmissible for the purpose of abolishing
				effectually the Slave-trade— He said he was sure there would be no Slaves in the
				United States in forty years from this time— There would be to be sure in Louisiana;
				but then Louisiana would not form a part of the United States— I said that Civil War
				would then be substituted, instead of the Union— We had a small party to dinner—
				<persRef ref="smith-william-steuben;smith-catherine-johnson">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> W. S. Smith</persRef>,
				<persRef ref="hutchinson-israel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> I. P. Hutchinson</persRef>, <persRef ref="maury-fontaine">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
					Maury</persRef>, and his <persRef ref="maury-ruston">nephew from Liverpool</persRef>, <persRef ref="forbes-john">Forbes</persRef>, <persRef ref="bailey-john">Bailey</persRef> and <persRef ref="forrest-richard">R. Forrest</persRef>, also <persRef ref="hellen-thomas">Tom Hellen</persRef>
				and <persRef ref="buchanan-robert">Robert Buchanan</persRef>, with whom <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef> went home after
				dinner.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-25">
		<head>25 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-25"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Recreation</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>25. V:30.</dateline> The day was not interrupted by Company, but its
				intended occupations were discomposed by three sets of Newspapers. Those of
				yesterday which were necessarily laid over to this Morning—two files of English
				Newspapers, and those brought by this day’s Mail. Despatches from <persRef ref="rush-richard">R. Rush</persRef> were also
				received; and two Letters from <persRef ref="smith-john">J. A. Smith</persRef>. The latest of 7. March— Rush’s despatch
				of 1. March acknowledges the receipt of my Letter to him of 1. February. This is an
				answer received from London in 84 days— I think the shortest time of such a return
				that has occurred within my experience— I walked Northward across the fields to the
				wood on the borders of the City, and gathered the first wild flowers of the Spring
				of which there were not more than half a dozen kinds— The Oaks and Elms of the
				forest are just putting forth their leaves. The journal of yesterday employed part
				of the morning; and all the Evening. <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef> spent it
				at <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-ann">Madame Hyde de Neuville’s.</persRef></p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-26">
		<head>26 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-26"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Science and Technology</note>
			<note type="subject">Steam Power</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>26. V:30.</dateline> <persRef ref="tyler-benjamin">Benjamin Owen Tyler</persRef> was here this morning— He is a
				sort of itinerant writing Master, and consanguineous with me. He writes a good hand,
				with the further talent of imitating very exactly the hand-writing of others. He has
				published a copy of the Declaration of Independence engraved with fac similes of the
				signatures. I propose to employ him to take an exact fac simile, of the whole
				Declaration, including the signatures; to be kept separate from the original, and as
				an accurate likeness of it, in case of any accident happening to it. I called at the
				Patent Office to make enquiry of the principle of an invention for which <persRef ref="foster-alexander">A. W.
					Foster</persRef> and a person named <persRef ref="hugus-unknown">Hugus</persRef> are taking a patent— Foster has written me a Letter
				in which he speaks of it as a desideratum in mechanics; expects that within five
				years it will be navigating the Wolga and the Caspian, and applies to me for
				information how he is to obtain Patents for it, all over Europe. I found <persRef ref="thornton-william">D<hi
					rend="superscript">r </hi>Thornton</persRef> making out a Patent for it, and describing it
				as a mode of obtaining rotary, by rectilinear motion— It is one of the innumerable
				progeny of the Steam engine; a machine almost as pregnant of Power, as the element
				by which it operates— <persRef ref="fulton-robert">Fulton’s</persRef> Steam-Boats have turned all the projecting heads in
				that direction— Fulton himself invented little or nothing; but with the aid of
				<persRef ref="livingston-robert">Chancellor Livingston’s</persRef> fortune, he made the inventions of others practically
				useful— Fulton’s patent privilege from Nature was enterprize, and Perseverance— He
				was doubtless ingenious too, but I believe not more so than many ordinary mechanics.
				This improvement of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Fosters, is a simplification of
				Fulton’s Machinery; but differs nothing in principle, and very little in mode from
				several other models of Patents to produce the same effect which the doctor shewed
				me. He also told me the whole Story of his own Steam-boat, which actually ran upon
				the Schuylkill several years before Fulton’s, but which failed of ultimate success,
				merely by his want of Perseverance and pecuniary means.— I went over the whole
				Office with the Doctor, and examined many of the Models— I thought how useful and
				profitable an occupation it might be for a young man with competent fortune, and
				having no other necessary pursuit in life, to take up this collection of models; to
				examine and make himself thoroughly master of the principles and of the peculiar
				invention, or new idea with its physical application, in each of them—then to
				classify them; to mark all those if any there be, which contain a new principle—to
				examine the differences in the modifications of the same principle—then to observe
				and compare them with reference to their ultimate <hi rend="italic"
				>results</hi>—what effect they produced upon the enjoyments or conveniences of human
				life—distinguishing those of which the <hi rend="italic">ends</hi> are comprehensive
				and important from those which terminate in trifles— A Steam-Engine, or a Corkscrew.
				Finally to make a History of these Inventions, with reference to the characters of
				the Inventors, and the character of the Nation—by whose citizens they were invented.
				It would lead to inferences, developing the moral and intellectual character of the
				Nation itself, and might with a good natural capacity, and <pb type="ms" n="97"
				/>industrious, sober and persevering habits lead to inventions and discoveries as
				useful and important as any of those accumulated in the Office— There might be
				danger unless he had a well ballasted mind of its making him a mere projector— Would
				it not be worth while among the public institutions of a Nation to have a school for
				the education of a certain number of civil Engineers?— Would it not be worth the
				while of a Secretary of State to reflect and examine, whether it is not among his
				duties to devise means of rendering this Patent Office more conducive to the Public
				service, and of more extensive usefulness?— This last question I am afraid I shall
				never solve— Every day starts new game to me, upon the field of my duties; but the
				hurry of the hour leaves me no time for the pursuit of it, and at the close of my
				Career I shall merely have gone helter skelter through the current business of the
				Office, and leave no permanent trace of my ever having been in it behind— <persRef ref="graham-john">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> John Graham</persRef> called upon me at the Office to enquire
				again when I should be ready with his Instructions— I said to-morrow. He urged again
				to have some part of the expences for his passage in the Frigate, paid by the
				Department— It is very difficult to resist these personal applications face to face—
				But great abuses have been creeping in to the pecuniary affairs of the Department;
				which have produced disorders in its accounts, and a consequent dissatisfaction in
				Congress. <persRef ref="monroe-james">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Monroe</persRef> and <persRef ref="madison-james">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Madison</persRef> while in the Department, made it a principle to leave all these questions
				unsettled— In this way there arose irregular allowances for the expences of
				Ministers having passages in Public Ships; and in the case of the Mission to
				South-America they were enormous. I have no other principle to recur to than that of
				allowing no expence for the passage, whatsoever. This brings me into a disagreeable
				collision with every Minister going abroad, and those who like Graham are here at
				hand, and come one day to ask if they cannot be allowed to use the Ship-bread, and
				the next to enquire whether we will not pay for the extra cups and saucers for the
				breakfast table, bring one into a state of ludicrous distress, for resources of
				polite modification to the monosyllable <hi rend="italic">NO</hi>— The <persRef ref="goupydequabeck-alexander">Viscount de
					Quaback</persRef> Chargé d’Affaires from the Netherlands came with his Cousin <persRef ref="goupydebeauvolers-unknown">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Goupil de Beauvolers</persRef>, who took leave; going
				immediately home to Bruxelles, upon important private family concerns. <persRef ref="sasse-unknown">Sasse</persRef> the
				Prussian Secretary of Legation is likewise recalled, and going immediately home—
				<persRef ref="smith-william-steuben;smith-catherine-johnson">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Smith</persRef> spent
				the Evening here—</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-27">
		<head>27 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-27"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Oregon Territory</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>27. V:30.</dateline> <persRef ref="sasse-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sasse</persRef> called this
				morning to take leave. He goes to morrow Morning for New-York, to embark in the Ship
				James Monroe, one of the new line of Liverpool Packets, to sail the 10<hi
					rend="superscript">th. </hi>of May— <persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</persRef> and his
				family are to go in the same vessel. I finished the draft of Instructions to <persRef ref="graham-john">J.
					Graham</persRef>, wrote a Letter of recall to <persRef ref="sumter-thomas">T. Sumter jun<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi></persRef> and
				a Letter to <persRef ref="ray-joseph">Joseph Ray</persRef>, late Consul at Pernambuco to inform him that his Commission
				has been revoked— After this last Letter had been copied, and was ready to be
				despatched, I found that I had already written a Letter of the same purport on the
					4<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>of December last— This is not the first
				instance in which I have after writing Letters on public business entirely forgotten
				it; and this defect of Memory proceeds from a want of method sufficiently accurate
				in the transaction of business— I no longer wonder at the forgetfulness of the same
				kind which I so often remarked in <persRef ref="castlereagh-robert">Lord Castlereagh</persRef>, and which I sometimes suspected
				was a remembrance to forget— I am now persuaded it was not— I observe the same thing
				often in the <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef>— An ordinary mind, absorbed in objects of great importance
				will not retain the recollection of others by which it has been transiently
				occupied; and it is not always the most unimportant objects that are forgotten— <persRef ref="cushing-nathanael">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Nathanael Cushing</persRef>, and Anchor-maker of Pembroke,
				Massachusetts came to the Office with a Letter of recommendation from <persRef ref="degrand-peter">Degrand</persRef>, who
				introduced him to me last September at Boston— He has obtained a contract for making
				three Anchors for the Columbus line of Battle ship, and says <persRef ref="rodgers-john">Commodore Rogers</persRef> told
				him that more would probably be wanted— Cushing goes to morrow Morning for Boston.
				<persRef ref="graham-john">John Graham</persRef> came to take leave, intending to leave the City to-morrow— I read to him
				the remainder of the draft of his Instructions, and had much conversation with him
				on points, upon which written Instructions were not expedient. Graham is a safe,
				intelligent and industrious man, acquainted with the French and Spanish Languages;
				of mild and conciliatory manners; and of much experience in our public
				affairs—having been Secretary of Legation to Spain when <persRef ref="pinckney-charles2">Charles Pinckney</persRef> was the <pb
					type="ms" n="98"/>Minister, in 1801. afterwards Secretary to the Territory of
				Orleans— During the whole period of <persRef ref="madison-james">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Madison’s</persRef>
				administration, he was chief Clerk in the Department of State; and has since been a
				Commissioner to South-America. His talents are rather solid than brilliant, and I
				have hopes that his amenity of deportment, and his Prudence, will restore the
				good-understanding with the Portuguese Government which has of late been so deeply
				affected. After he left me, I was reperusing the late Letters from <persRef ref="hill-henry">Henry Hill</persRef> the
				Consul at Rio de Janeiro with a view to answer them; when <persRef ref="maury-fontaine">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> F. Maury</persRef> came in with a budget of despatches just delivered to him by
				<persRef ref="biddle-james">Captain Biddle</persRef> of the Sloop of War Ontario— She arrived at Annapolis yesterday; last
				from Pernambuco, and Rio de Janeiro. There were despatches from M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Sumter of 3. March, and a Letter from Joseph Ray,
				still acting as Consul at Pernambuco, of 23. March. Letters also, of 3. December
				from Lima, and one from Captain Biddle himself, announcing that on the 19<hi
					rend="superscript">th</hi> of August last, he took possession in the name and on
				behalf of the United States, of both sides of the Mouth of Columbia River. These
				papers make it necessary that I should give further Instructions to John Graham, and
				will delay for a day or two longer the despatching of him— He and D. Brent were both
				at my house an hour or two this Evening. I came home so late that before we could
				sit down to dinner, <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-ann">Madame de Neuville</persRef> called for <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
					Adams</persRef>, who went with her and took tea at <persRef ref="middleton-mary">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
				Middleton’s</persRef>; and then returned and spent the remainder of the Evening, with M<hi
					rend="superscript">rs.</hi> De Neuville herself.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-28">
		<head>28 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-28"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Oregon Territory</note>
			<note type="subject">Science and Technology</note>
			<note type="subject">South American Wars of Independence</note>
			<note type="subject">Treaty of Ghent</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>28. V:30.</dateline> With a view to have a longer day at the Office, to
				draft the additional Instructions necessary for <persRef ref="graham-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
				Graham</persRef>, I went to my Office this morning at eleven O’Clock, nearly two hours earlier
				than usual. I had been there scarcely five minutes when <persRef ref="biddle-james">Captain Biddle</persRef> of the
				Ontario came in, and I had a conversation of two hours with him, in which he gave me
				a general account of his tour of service which has been of more than a year and a
				half. The main object of his expedition was to take possession of the Mouth of
				Columbia River which he accomplished. But he has been occasionally at Lima, in Peru,
				at Valparaiso in Chili, at Rio de Janeiro in Brazil; both going and returning, and
				at Pernambuco last; from which his passage to Annapolis was of 28 days— His report
				embraced a great variety of objects, relating to the establishment at the mouth of
				Columbia river; to the Condition of Peru, and Chili; and the state and prospects of
				our Commerce there. To his relations with the <persRef ref="lapezuela-joaquin">Vice-roy of Peru at Lima</persRef>, and with the
				revolutionary Government of Chili at Valparaiso; and particularly with <persRef ref="cochrane-thomas">Lord
				Cochrane</persRef>, whom he found acting there as their admiral; He found him troublesome, and
				thinks he will do the revolutionary party which has employed him more harm than
				good— To the ships Beaver and Canton, of New-York and Salem, seized by the Spanish
				Government at Talcahuana, and released by the Viceroy through the interposition of
				Captain Biddle, and <persRef ref="prevost-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Provost</persRef>— To the situation of <persRef ref="sumter-thomas">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Sumter</persRef> at Rio de Janeiro; his fruitless applications
				to the Government; and the state of the Consulate there; and to the ineffectual call
				of the Ontario, at Pernambuco to obtain the release of the American Seamen
				imprisoned there— Biddle has some apprehensions for the safety of M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Provost; who went with the British Sloop of War
				Blossom, <persRef ref="hickey-frederick">Captain Hickey</persRef> to receive a formal surrender of the Post there— Biddle
				himself was 112 days from Lima to Columbia river and returning. And when he last
				left Lima, the Blossom had already been gone 130 days for the same expedition.
				Captain Hickey intended to enter Columbia river, but there is a Bar at the mouth of
				it with only three fathoms and a half of water. Biddle did not attempt to pass it
				with his ship, and he thinks if Hickey did, some accident has happened to his
				vessel. <persRef ref="homans-benjamin">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Homans</persRef> brought me Captain Biddle’s detailed
				report to the Navy Department, which I had however no time to read this day. Biddle
				wishes to return with his Ship to discharge his Company at New York; but Homans says
				he must send her to Baltimore; because the Navy Department already spend so much
				money at New-York, and Boston; that they must distribute some portion of their
				employment and purchases, further South— Captain Biddle left me at half past one,
				and immediately afterwards came in <persRef ref="adams-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Adams</persRef>, late
				Astronomer to the Commission under the 6<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>and 7<hi
					rend="superscript">th. </hi>Articles of the Treaty of Ghent. <persRef ref="hawkins-samuel">Col<hi
					rend="superscript">l.</hi> Hawkins</persRef> the Agent of the United States under that
				Commission was here the greatest part of last Winter; intriguing against the
				Commissioner, <persRef ref="porter-peter">Peter Buel Porter</persRef>, he addressed a Letter of complaint against him
				directly to the President, who deposited it at the Department of State, and referred
				Hawkins to me— He came and had several conversations with me at the Department, and
				made a Statement against Porter, which he afterwards took back, and presented
				another in its stead— His <pb type="ms" n="99"/>complaints against Porter were
				two-fold—First of unhandsome, hostile, and deceitful conduct towards him personally;
				and secondly of absolute treachery to his public trust. The personal part had
				principally reference to Porter’s journey to this City last August; and to his
				Statements to me at that time against Hawkins (See this Diary volume 5. p. 388)
				Hawkins had got some intimation of Porter’s object in that journey, and called upon
				me to inform him what Porter’s charges against him had been. I told him the
				substance of them; and he bitterly complained that they were partly false; greatly
				misrepresented, and made with deep dissimulation of friendship for him by Porter
				immediately before he came on. Hawkins’s second charge against Porter amounted to
				nothing less than that he in collusion with <persRef ref="ogilvy-john">Col<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> Ogilvy</persRef>
				the British Commissioner, was betraying the rights of the United States— That he had
				agreed to accept the observed Latitude of 45. on the Spherical Hypothesis, instead
				of insisting upon the reduced Latitude, allowing for the oblate spheroidical form of
				the Earth— That Ogilvy the British Commissioner had attempted to corrupt Adams the
				Astronomer; and that <persRef ref="thompson-david">Thompson</persRef> the British Astronomer, had attempted to falsify
				Adams’s observations, by clandestinely removing one of his Posts— Of these last
				facts Hawkins produced a hearsay certificate from a <persRef ref="delafield-joseph">Major Delafield</persRef>, that they had
				been told him by Adams— The facts stated in the certificate were however so
				excessively weak as buttresses to a charge of attempted corruption and foul play,
				that I told Hawkins there must be an explanation of them by Adams himself. They were
				in themselves, at the utmost causes of slight suspicion—possibly tarnished with bad
				motives; but probably quite innocent. A copy of Hawkins’s second and final statement
				to the Department was by direction of the President sent to General Porter, with an
				invitation to him to answer it— His answer was received a few days since; and as
				regards the accusations against his own official conduct is quite satisfactory— It
				shews that the question between observed and geocentric Latitude is yet open, and
				that he has not agreed to any thing which can foreclose it— And he appeals to Adams
				himself against Delafield’s Certificate— Adams disclaims in the most positive and
				solemn manner, all suspicion either that Ogilvy ever attempted to corrupt him; or
				that Thompson removed his post with a bad intention. He says he may perhaps have
				mentioned to Delafield in conversation the two incidents of Ogilvy’s advising him to
				communicate confidentially concerning the Latitude, with <persRef ref="chipman-ward">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Chipman</persRef> the British Agent; and the removal of his post by Thompson, as
				proofs of the unceasing vigilance, and continual caution that it was his duty to
				observe— But that he was perfectly convinced that M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Ogilvy’s motive had been merely to promote harmony between the co-operators in the
				Commission, and that the removal of the post was an accident. He said he had the
				most entire confidence in the integrity of Col<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> Ogilvy
				and of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thompson, and was greatly mortified both that
				such a Construction had been put upon his words, as Major Delafield’s certificate
				imported, and that his name and conversation should thus have been used without his
				consent, and even without consulting him. He shewed me copies of General Porter’s
				Letter to him, and of his answer to the same effect. I suggested to him the
				propriety of his going before a Magistrate, and making the declaration upon Oath, in
				an Authentic form. Adams is a man, half-bred; with a scientific education, and no
				knowledge or experience of the world, awkward to excess in his manners, and stiff
				and conceited in his language— It is apparent from his own admissions that he did at
				least hint suspicions of the British Commissioner and Astronomer to Delafield— He
				wanted to magnify his own importance; to give an idea of his stupendous labours, and
				profound penetration.— To make the mysterious and incorruptible personage; and
				finally to talk about himself— Little did he think that all this would be brought in
				the shape of charges against Ogilvy and Thompson; and even against Porter, to rest
				upon no better foundation than his evening talk, and his mysterious and pompous
				suspicions— Before he left me, the Mail was brought in, with three despatches from
				<persRef ref="rush-richard">R. Rush</persRef>—two from <persRef ref="hughes-christopher">Ch<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Hughes</persRef> at Stockholm; a multitude
				of Letters and London Newspapers down to the 26<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>of
				March— Reading these till half past five, I found that I had not written one line of
				the additional Instructions to J. Graham, and I was obliged to come home to dinner—
					<persRef key="smith-catherine-johnson">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> W. S. Smith</persRef> dined with us. <persRef key="smith-william-steuben">He</persRef> came for her in
				the Evening.</p>
			
		</div>
	</div>
	
	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-29">
		<head>29 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-29"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">African Americans</note>
			<note type="subject">Anti-Slavery Movements</note>
			<note type="subject">Colonization Movements</note>
			<note type="subject">Emancipation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Native Americans</note>
			<note type="subject">Slave Rebellions</note>
			<note type="subject">Slave Trade</note>
			<note type="subject">Slavery</note>
		</bibl>
		
		<div type="docbody">
			
			<p><pb type="ms" n="100"/><dateline>29. V:</dateline> <persRef ref="eliot-samuel3">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> S. A. Eliot,</persRef> a son of
				<persRef ref="eliot-samuel2">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Samuel Eliot</persRef> of Boston came yesterday and left a
				Letter of recommendation from <persRef ref="quincy-josiah2">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Quincy</persRef>. I called this
				morning at his lodgings at <persRef ref="strother-john">Strother’s</persRef> to see him, but he was gone out. At the Office
				I found <persRef ref="hay-george">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> George Hay</persRef>, who borrowed a parliamentary
				pamphlet containing papers relating to the Slave-trade, received with the last
				despatches from <persRef ref="rush-richard">R. Rush</persRef>. Hay said he had a great avidity for all papers concerning
				the project for abolishing the Slave-trade; a project which he believed would
				ultimately fail; which had already produced incomparably more mischief than good,
				and which he had no doubt would continue to be pernicious. For he had no doubt that
				the Insurrection in Saint Domingo, and the total destruction of the white powers
				there were the legitimate offspring of <persRef ref="wilberforce-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wilberforce’s</persRef>
				first abolition plans, and our colonization Society here, whatever pretences they
				may put forth, and whatever some enthusiastic people among them might believe and
				intend, could have no other ultimate object than a general emancipation— I said that
				the Colonization Society were pushing their objects with so much zeal and
				importunity, that I very much wished their memorials might be taken up by Congress,
				and fairly discussed; for under the colour of colonizing black people, I was afraid
				they would smuggle in upon us a system of establishing Colonies beyond Sea, of the
				consequences of which the People of this Country were little aware; while in
				England, under the mask of abolishing the Slave trade, they were introducing, and
				had already obtained the consent of Spain, Portugal, and the Netherlands, a new
				principle of the Law of Nations more formidable to human liberty, than the Slave
				trade itself—A right of the Commanders of armed vessels of one Nation, to visit and
				search the merchant vessels of another in time of Peace. I observed that the
				Colonization Society had derived great strength from the part which the Virginia
				Legislature had taken in their favour— He said the Virginia Legislature had been
				tricked into that Resolution. That there was no such weak and absurd Reasoner in the
				world as humanity. It never looked but at one side of a question. That the
				resolution of the Virginia Legislature had been obtained by <persRef ref="mercer-charles">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Mercer</persRef>; who was the father of the Colonization Society and of all their
				projects. That he himself had inconsiderately voted for it under the impulse of
				humanity; and three hours after, and ever since had bitterly repented his vote— The
				subject had afterwards been brought up again upon some correspondence between <persRef ref="jefferson-thomas">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Jefferson</persRef> and <persRef ref="monroe-james">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Monroe</persRef>,
				which had been discussed in both Houses of the Legislature with closed doors.
				Afterwards the House had removed the injunction of secrecy; and the Correspondence
				to have been published, but Mercer lost the copies which had been before the house—
				And subsequent application was made to the Senate, for their copies, for
				publication— A motion that the copies might be given was made in the Senate; which
				he Hay had opposed—and he took the occasion to review the whole subject— When the
				vote was taken only two Members of the Senate voted for granting the copies, and
				now, if a vote of the Virginia Legislature could be taken, it would be any thing but
				in favour of the Colonization Society and its projects— M<hi rend="superscript">r
				</hi>Jefferson he said had favoured them, because it was he who many years since had
				introduced and carried through the Law of the State, for partial emancipation of the
				Slaves; and after witnessing the pernicious consequences that had followed from it
				he was desirous of finding another remedy for it. But the friends of emancipation
				had a memorable example before them, of which it was surprizing that they would not
				avail themselves as an admonition— The Negro Slave-trade itself was the child of
				Humanity— The contrivance of <persRef ref="lascasas-bartolome">Las Casas</persRef> to mitigate the condition of the American
				Indians— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hay’s opinions upon the Colonization
				Society, and its projects were unexpected to me— There are so many considerations of
				difficulty and of delicacy mingling with this subject, that I would gladly keep
				aloof from it altogether. But I apprehend the Society, which like all fanatical
				Associations is intolerant, will push, and intrigue, and worry, till I shall be
				obliged to take a stand, and appear publicly among their opponents. Their project of
				expurgating the United States, from the free people of Colour, at the public
				expence, by colonizing them in Africa, is so far as it is sincere and honest, upon a
				par with <persRef ref="symmes-john">John Cleves Symmes’s</persRef> project of going to the North Pole, and travelling
				within the Nut shell of the Earth— I finished the draught of General Instructions to
				<persRef ref="graham-john">J. Graham</persRef>. <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef> spent the Evening at her <persRef key="smith-catherine-johnson">Sister
				Smith’s</persRef>— Evening without fire in my cabinet.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-30">
		<head>30 April 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-30"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">African Americans</note>
			<note type="subject">Colonization Movements</note>
			<note type="subject">Panic of 1819</note>
			<note type="subject">Slave Trade</note>
			<note type="subject">Slavery</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>30. V:</dateline> I had not a thought when writing my Journal of yesterday
				that I should so soon be brought into direct collision with the Colonization
				Society— But this morning, <persRef ref="laurie-james">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Laurie</persRef> the Presbyterian,
				and <persRef ref="hawley-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hawley</persRef> the <pb type="ms" n="101"/>Episcopalian
				Clergymen, came to my Office, as deputies from the Society, with a Subscription
				paper, to raise money to send to Africa the Slaves which have been advertised for
				sale for the benefit of the State of Georgia. The Legislature of Georgia, authorized
				the Governor to deliver over these Slaves to the Colonization Society, if they would
				take upon themselves the whole expence of sending them to Africa or elsewhere; and
				pay back to the State all the charges and expences occasioned to them by the
				smuggling in of these Negroes. The Society have accepted this offer, and are now
				soliciting subscriptions to collect the money— They have been for some days
				addressing the public, and soliciting, in the Newspapers; and now these Clergymen
				are going round as their deputies, with the subscription paper— <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford’s</persRef> name was down for 50 dollars. I declined
				subscribing, and told Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs: </hi>Laurie and Hawley, that on
				full deliberation I had with regret made up my opinion; that the object of the
				Society was impracticable to any considerable extent; and that as far as it would be
				practicable, it would be productive of evil more than of good— That without
				answering for the feelings or the fortunes of individuals one or more, I believed
				that the mass of coloured people who may be removed to Africa, by the Colonization
				Society, will suffer more and enjoy less than they would if they should remain in
				their actual Condition in the United States— That their removal will do more harm
				than good to this Country, by depriving it of the mass of their industry—and thus
				that the result of the whole to both parties will be evil and not good— M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Laurie argued the subject with me for m<unclear>ore</unclear> an hour,
				but M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hawley took no part in the conversation. Laurie
				observed that the Society would greatly regret not having the weight and countenance
				of my name, but would hope I should hereafter be convinced by the experience of
				their success. I told them I would certainly not throw impediments in their way— I
				had the highest respect for the motives of the Society, and for the characters and
				opinions of many of its members. My deference for those opinions made me distrustful
				of my own— Yet by my own, I must necessarily abide. I wished not to appear to be
				thought an adversary to the Society; but I could not with my present opinions give
				it any countenance— I was willing their experiment should be fairly made. I had no
				faith in its success. So far as my refusal to subscribe might operate against the
				Society, I should wish what had passed between us might not be made known—but so far
				as it concerned only myself, I had no wish that it should be kept private— Their
				deportment was entirely proper; and Hawley, looked assent to almost all that I said—
				This was a day of exceptionable subscription papers— <persRef ref="kerr-alexander">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
					Kerr</persRef> brought me one for a Ball to be given to <persRef ref="hyde-de-neuville-jean;hyde-de-neuville-ann">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and
				Madame Hyde de Neuville</persRef>, which I also declined; not from any disregard for them; but
				disapproving it as a precedent and example. In the case of the Ball given to <persRef ref="bagot-charles;bagot-mary">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Bagot</persRef>, I had not
				been consulted; it was got up principally by members of Congress, and although I was
				invited to it, I had accepted not without hesitation— At that Ball unpleasant
				circumstances had occurred, and would have convinced me independent of any preceding
				objections, that the example ought not to be repeated. There was an attempt made
				before <persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</persRef> went away to raise a subscription first
				to give him a dinner; and then a Ball; both of which failed— One of the great
				mischiefs of all these subscription entertainments is that it levies upon perhaps
				half the subscribers a tax, which they have neither ability to pay, nor strength of
				mind to refuse. They cost from ten to twenty dollars a ticket, and if multiplied by
				the practice of giving them to all the departing foreign Ministers would soon become
				insupportable— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Kerr said they had at first intended
				not to offer the paper to the Heads of Departments, but to have invited them— But
				times were so hard, and people were so distressed for money, that they could not
				otherwise make up their subscription— I requested him if it should be made up not to
				send me an invitation; as I could not accept it, especially after having declined to
				subscribe— <persRef ref="brent-daniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Brent</persRef> took the Instructions prepared for
					<persRef ref="graham-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Graham</persRef> to him, at a place on the way to
				Annapolis, to which he is gone. I made the draft of a Letter to <persRef ref="hill-henry">Henry Hill</persRef>, Consul
				at Rio de Janeiro; and it was all that I could accomplish at the Office this day—
				Dined with <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">my wife</persRef> and <persRef ref="hellen-mary">Mary Hellen</persRef> at <persRef ref="frye-nathaniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Frye’s</persRef>. <persRef ref="smith-william-steuben;smith-catherine-johnson">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> W. S. Smith</persRef> were
				also there— They came in the Carriage and took me up at the Office— Stopping at the
				six buildings to take in Mary Hellen, who goes to School there, I left the Carriage
				to walk— The stubborn horse <hi rend="italic">balked</hi>, and broke the Pole <pb
					type="ms" n="102"/>of the Carriage. We were then all obliged to walk: and so in
				the Evening to come home; till opposite the President’s house where we met an empty
				Hack in which we came home; leaving M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Smith at
				<persRef ref="fletcher-noah">Fletchers</persRef>— Smith continued his walk home.— There has already been much warm weather;
				but this is the first day that I have had no fire in my writing room.</p>
			
			
		</div>
	</div>
	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-04-xx">
		<head>Day</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-04-xx"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
		</bibl>
		
		<div type="docbody">
			<!-- This is a summary entry without a date.-->
			
			
			<p><dateline rend="italic">Day.</dateline> My average hour of rising through the month has been six
				O’Clock— It ought to have been five— The early morning has usually been devoted to
				writing in this Journal, the arrears of which at the beginning of month which were
				three weeks or more. They are now redeemed; but I spend too much time upon the
				Journal itself— With the exception of an hour at breakfast, it still occupies me
				till Noon— I then go to the Office where I remain till past five; engaged as
				described in the Day of last Month— Come home to dinner at six— After dinner I read
				the newspapers till ten, or sometimes eleven, and then retire to bed— As the days
				lengthen and the weather grown warm I find it impracticable to write in the Evening;
				and if I spend it abroad, or have company to dine with us at home; it throws over
				the next Morning, the reading of the daily newspapers, and then absorbs the hours
				for writing and immediately produces a breach of a day in the Journal. From the day
				of my return to this City last October to this, my Journal has been more minute and
				prolix than during any former equal period of time in the course of my life— It has
				probably been in relation to public affairs among the most important, and
				incomparably the most successful period of my life, past or future— But whatever the
				series of future Events may be, it is impossible for me to continue the Journal in
				the same proportion— It must henceforth, while continued at-all be more summary.</p>
		</div>
	</div>
</div>
