<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.masshist.org/publications/pub/schema/djqa-prep-2016.rng" type="xml"?>
        <?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="DJQA-authorViewMaybe.css"?>
<div type="month" mhs:volume="31" mhs:startingOnPage="050" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mhs="http://www.masshist.org/ns/1.0">
	<bibl n="metadata">
		<date from="1819-03-01" to="1819-03-31"/>
	</bibl>
	<!-- D/JQA/31.195 -->
	<!-- March 1819. -->

<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-01">
	<head>1 March 1819</head>
	<bibl>
		<author>JQA</author>
		<date type="creation" when="1819-03-01"/>
		<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
		<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
		<note type="subject">Bank of the United States</note>
		<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
		<note type="subject">Recreation</note>
		<note type="subject">Supreme Court</note>
		<note type="subject">U.S. Constitution</note>
		<note type="subject">West, The</note>
	</bibl>
	
	<div type="docbody">
		<dateline type="heading">March 1819.</dateline>
	<p><dateline>1. VI:15.</dateline> Monday— The Columbus, a 74. that is to say ninety gun ship was this morning
		launched from the Navy-Yard. I went there with<persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine"> M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef>, <persRef ref="buchanan-mary">Mary
		Buchanan</persRef> and <persRef ref="hellen-mary">Mary Hellen</persRef>, left them under shelter, on one of the buildings at the yard; and
		went myself on board the ship, and was launched in her. The operation was entirely
		successful, and the movement of the ship so smooth and regular, and gentle that the moment
		of her final parting from the ways, and floating upon the wave was scarcely perceptible to
		those of us who were on board— It was the first time I had ever been in a vessel when <pb
			type="ms" n="51"/>launched— The weather was unfavourable, and a cold rain was drizzling
		for nearly two hours that we were waiting for the blocks to be knocked away and the vessel
		to start— There was a great crowd of Spectators upon the surrounding shores; but few on
		board the ship— Among them, <persRef ref="rodgers-john">Commodore Rogers</persRef>, <persRef ref="brown-jacob">General Brown</persRef>, <persRef ref="rhea-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
			Rhea</persRef> of Tennessee and <persRef ref="thornton-william">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thornton</persRef>. Commodore Rogers stationed
		General Brown and me, on the edge of the Quarter-Deck— We gave her three cheers as she was
		sliding down, and plunged into the deep—no unpleasant accident occurred— May the Columbus
		prove worthy of the name she bears; and may her career upon the Ocean be as brilliant as her
		introduction to it was auspicious. I returned to the shore in a boat— The <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef>, and the
		other Heads of Departments were at the Yard; but none of them on board the ship. After some
		search for the Ladies, I found them at the Marine barracks where a collation and a dancing
		party were prepared— Returning homeward we stopped at the Capitol, with a view of hearing
			<persRef ref="pinkney-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> W. Pinkney</persRef> of Baltimore who was arguing the Bank Question
		before the Supreme Court. But the Hall was so crowded that it was impossible to get in— I
		left the Ladies to return home and walked to the President’s, where I had further
		conversation with him concerning the appointment of <persRef ref="robertson-george">G. Robertson</persRef> as Governor of the Arkansaw
		Territory. <persRef ref="trimble-david">Trimble</persRef> has pressing him and me again upon the subject again, with great
		importunity. He came to the Office about it last Saturday with <persRef ref="johnson-richard">Col<hi rend="superscript"
			>l.</hi> R. M. Johnson</persRef>, who also supports Robertson, though not with so much ardour.
		They insist that the constitutional objection, will be done away after the third of March.
		That the establishment of the Territory is to take effect only on the 4<hi
			rend="superscript">th.</hi> of next July— That there is in the Law itself an express
		provision authorising the appointment of the Governor and other Officers by the President,
		during the recess. That there are numerous Precedents, not only of the appointment of
		members of Congress, under similar circumstances; but of the postponement of appointments
		till after the close of the Session for the express purpose of letting in as candidates and
		of appointing persons who while the Congress lasted were constitutionally excluded— All this
		Trimble has also written me in a Letter to be laid before the President, whose aversion to
		Robertson increases in proportion as he is urged upon him. The President in many of his
		appointments has motives that he does not disclose— He has during the present Session
		declined to appoint <persRef ref="smyth-alexander">Alexander Smyth</persRef>, a member of the present House of Representatives, as
		District Judge for the Western District of Virginia, an Office created during the present
		Session; but the appointment to which could not without manifest impropriety have been
		postponed beyond the Session—the law having passed some time since and taking effect
		immediately— But the cases are so much alike, that the President thinks he would be charged
		with partiality if he should not exclude Robertson as he had excluded Smyth— He told me that
		he would send for <persRef ref="macon-nathaniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Macon</persRef> and enquire if he could not recommend
		some person from North-Carolina— I attended with M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams and
		Mary Buchanan a Ball this Evening at <persRef key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagots</persRef> and lost a game
		at Chess with General Brown— <persRef ref="hopkinson-joseph">Hopkinson</persRef> told me that they had lost in the House of
		Representatives this day, the proposed amendment to the Bill authorizing the President to
		take possession of Florida—by the manner in which <persRef ref="holmes-john">Holmes</persRef> had proposed it— He told the house
		that the Committee had not thought it necessary, but that he proposed it at the suggestion
		of one of the Heads of Departments. This instantly started <persRef key="clay-henry">Clay</persRef> up in opposition to it; and
		<persRef ref="johnson-james">Johnson</persRef> of Virginia, who poured forth their sarcasms and their indignation that Heads of
		Executive Departments should presume to make suggestions to Committees of the House; and
		they prevented the passage of the amendment— Now <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">Crawford</persRef> is constantly boasting that he
		draws up Bills for Committees, who present them exactly as he draws them— Yet never a word
		is said of executive suggestions from him— This was a Bill merely to carry into execution a
		Treaty just made by the executive; and of which the House knew nothing but from executive
		suggestions— Holmes himself as Chairman of the Committee had written to me, asking executive
		suggestions. The fling <pb type="ms" n="52"/>at executive suggestions was therefore in this
		instance misplaced even to absurdity. But the true secret was Holmes did not want the
		amendment to pass— Whence I conclude he has the project of being one of the Commissioners
		himself; and thinks he will stand a better chance, if the appointments are postponed till
		the next Session of Congress, than if they should be made during the recess. It was about
		Midnight when we came home.</p>
	</div>
</div>
	
	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-02">
		<head>2 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-02"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Seminole Wars</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>2. VII:30.</dateline> <persRef ref="buchanan-mary">Mary Buchanan</persRef> left us this Morning, and returned with
					<persRef ref="howard-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Howard</persRef>, and a party of her acquaintance to
				Baltimore. She has been with us from Christmas day to this time, and is an amiable,
				beautiful, and discreet young woman. <persRef ref="bloomfield-joseph">General Bloomfield</persRef> called at my house to take
				leave, and to recommend <persRef ref="bloomfield-joseph2">his nephew</persRef> as a Commissioner under the Spanish Treaty. <persRef ref="edwards-ninian">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Edwards</persRef> the Senator from the State of Illinois was 
				here to speak of the proposed appointments for the Arkansaw Territory; but more
				particularly of those of District judge, Attorney and Marshal for the State of
				Illinois. Edwards, and his colleague <persRef ref="thomas-jesse">Thomas</persRef> are not in very close harmony— They have
				two sets of Candidates whom they patronize, and each of them speaks unfavourably of
				the friends of the other— <persRef ref="mclean-john">M’Lean</persRef>, the member from the State in the House of
				Representatives, sides with Thomas— He carried his own election against <persRef ref="cook-daniel">Daniel P.
				Cook</persRef>, only by a majority of four or five votes. Edwards shewed me a Letter to him
				from <persRef ref="pope-nathaniel">Nath<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> Pope</persRef> mentioning that he would accept the
				Office of District Judge. Edwards is a family relation of the Pope’s and of course
				recommends his cousin. He urges the reappointment of the former <persRef ref="meares-unknown">district Attorney
				Meares</persRef>, whom Thomas affirms to be a very unsuitable person for the Office, and he
				declares <persRef ref="fowke-philip">Fowke</persRef> the former Marshal, to be a worthless drunkard, while Thomas and
				M’Lean recommend the same man, and Thomas says he only once in a while mixes his
				grog too strong— A number of nominations were sent in to the Senate; and several
				were sent back confirmed, which have been some days before them— <persRef ref="macon-nathaniel">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Macon</persRef> chairman of a Committee of the Senate came to
				make some enquiries concerning various nominations. He said there was some complaint
				at their having been made so late in the Session, leaving scarcely time for the
				Senate to obtain the information necessary for them to act advisedly upon them. The
				delays for the most part however had been unavoidable. At the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> he spoke
				of the District Attorney for the Southern District of New-York, <persRef ref="fisk-jonathan">Fisk</persRef>, and desired me
				to ask <persRef ref="vanness-john">judge Van Ness</persRef> to let him know that he must resign, or be removed. Van Ness
				came to the Office; I returned him Fisk’s Letter, and told him what the President
				had said. Afterwards <persRef ref="thompson-smith">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thompson</persRef>, the Secretary of the
				navy came and told me, he thought it would be best that Van Ness should tell Fisk
				that the President left it altogether at his own option to resign, or to abide by
				the result of an enquiry and report by impartial and respectable persons— He said he
				was convinced from the whole tenour of Fiske’s Letter, that if the option of an
				enquiry is given him, he will not dare to face it; and will resign— But that if he
				is peremptorily required to resign; he will be found in complaint against the
				President, and pretend that he had not been allowed the benefit of an enquiry,
				though he had offered to submit to one— I met judge Van Ness again at <persRef ref="middleton-henry">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Middleton’s</persRef> where with <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
				Adams</persRef> I dined and spent the Evening; and I requested him according to Thompson’s
				advice to tell Fisk that resignation or enquiry was left entirely at his own option,
				but that the one or the other was indispensable. He promised to make his report
				accordingly; and told me he had no doubt Fisk would resign— <persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General Jackson</persRef> returned
				at five O’Clock this morning from his tour to New York. He was to have been here
				yesterday at the launch, but was detained at Baltimore. He has been every where
				received and entertained with great distinction, but the Report of the Committee of
				the Senate against him made last week, keeps alive the controversy respecting his
				proceedings in Florida.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-03">
		<head>3 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-03"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Sectionalism</note>
			<note type="subject">Slavery</note>
			<note type="subject">West, The</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>3. VII.</dateline> The second Session of the fifteenth Congress, and
				that Congress itself terminated this day. <persRef ref="edwards-ninian">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Edwards</persRef> the
				Senator from Illinois called again this morning at my house— Still upon the subject
				of appointments. He had recommended <persRef ref="sharp-solomon">Sharpe</persRef> for Governor of the Arkansaw territory;
				but now said he would withdraw his recommendation of him, to give a better prospect
				for <persRef ref="robertson-george">Robertson</persRef>— He was also very desirous that a <persRef ref="scott-andrew">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Scott,</persRef> <persRef ref="scott-john">brother of the Delegate</persRef> from the Missouri Territory should be appointed one
				of the judges for that of Arkansaw. Edwards told me again that he himself had no
				expectation or intention of coming to Congress again— As I was going down to the
				<persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> I was overtaken by <persRef ref="trimble-david">Trimble</persRef> in a Carriage— He stopped and asked me to
				take a seat with him which I did. He pressed again for the appointment of Robertson;
				but said if that could not be, he hoped at least the Office would be given to <pb
					type="ms" n="53"/>an inhabitant of a Slave holding State; otherwise there would
				be great uneasiness in the Western Country, after the attempt made in Congress to
				exclude Slavery from the territory. I alighted from the carriage at the President’s
				door, and in the antichamber of his Cabinet found <persRef ref="thomas-jesse">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Thomas</persRef> the Senator and <persRef ref="mclean-nathaniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M’Lean</persRef> the Representative from
				Illinois—They were there to urge again the appointment of the candidates recommended
				by them and their friends, for District judge, Attorney and Marshal. I found the
				President had resolved to nominate <persRef ref="miller-james">General Miller</persRef> as Governor of the Arkansaw
				territory— The law constituting the territory had passed yesterday, so that the
				nomination could be made this day. The other nominations the President fixed upon,
				partly of one side, and partly of the other. I came home late from the Office, and
				after dinner walked up to the Congress Halls. The President was in the Committee
				Room of the Senate, examining and signing Bills. <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Calhoun</persRef>, <persRef ref="thompson-smith">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thompson</persRef> and <persRef ref="wirt-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Wirt</persRef> were there, and <persRef ref="monroe-joseph">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> J. J. Monroe</persRef>. <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford </persRef>was absent, being still confined by
				indisposition— The Press of business was not great— The number of Bills for
				signature was not considerable, and none of them long. I went in to both houses in
				the course of the Evening before their adjournment. There was nothing to excite
				debate or even interest in either— Between nine and ten O’Clock, the usual Committee
				of two members from each house, Macon and <persRef ref="daggett-david">Daggett</persRef> from the Senate, <persRef ref="harrison-william">Harrison</persRef> and
				<persRef ref="pitkin-timothy">Pitkin</persRef> from the house of Representatives came in and announced that they were ready
				to adjourn, the President informed them that he had no further Communications to
				make, and they adjourned. Calhoun walked home with me.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-04">
		<head>4 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-04"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Seminole Wars</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>4. VII:</dateline> <persRef ref="smith-samuel2">General S. Smith</persRef> of Baltimore came and took leave. He
				recommends <persRef ref="hopkinson-joseph">Hopkinson</persRef> for one of the Commissioners under the Spanish Treaty. I called
				at the President’s and found him relieved from the great pressure of business which
				always attends the close of a Session— At the Office <persRef ref="appleton-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				John James Appleton</persRef> called to enquire if he should have time for a visit to <persRef ref="appleton-john2">his
				father</persRef>, before he must embark upon the voyage to Rio de Janeiro. He has been
				appointed Secretary of the Legation to the Court of Brazil. He has leave to go to
				Cambridge, and is to return here by the 24<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> of this
				Month— <persRef ref="dana-samuel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Dana</persRef>, Senator from Connecticut and <persRef ref="sanford-nathan">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Sanford</persRef> from New-York, were also at the Office. Dana
				has not been here during the late Session of Congress till last week. He is yet
				lame, but walks now with a single cane. He rattles almost as much as ever— We had
				company to dinner— 
				<persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General Jackson</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="estin-unknown">Captain Estin</persRef> and 
				<persRef ref="bronaugh-unknown">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bronaugh</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="bernard-simon">General Bernard</persRef> and 
				<persRef ref="poussin-william">Captain Poussin</persRef>, and 
				Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs. </hi><persRef ref="coles-edward">Coles</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="eaton-john">Eaton</persRef> of Tennessee, 
				<persRef ref="fromentin-eligius">Fromentin</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="mason-jonathan">Jonathan Mason</persRef> and 
				<persRef ref="mason-unknown6">his Son</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="middleton-henry">Middleton</persRef> and
				<persRef ref="tallmadge-james">Tallmadge</persRef>— 
				Invitations had been given to <persRef ref="butler-robert">Col<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> Butler</persRef>, Captains <persRef ref="call-unknown">Call</persRef> and 
				<persRef ref="young-unknown">Young</persRef>, and 
				Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> <persRef ref="baldwin-henry">Baldwin</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="blount-william">Blount</persRef>,
				<persRef ref="cass-lewis">Cass</persRef>, 
				(Governor of Michigan territory) <persRef ref="hogg-samuel">Hogg</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="mcrae-alexander">M’Rae</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="pinkney-william">Pinkney</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="rhea-john">Rhea</persRef> and 
				<persRef ref="ringgold-tench">Ringgold</persRef>, some
				of whom sent excuses and others neither came nor sent excuse— I had little
				Conversation with General Jackson, but he told me he wished to have an opportunity
				of talking with me, before he should leave the City. The only thing that he said to
				me manifesting his feelings was a remark upon the appointment of M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth as Minister to Spain. I told him the
				appointment of <persRef ref="forsyth-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth</persRef>, in which I had no share, was
				determined upon, before he had taken any part in the questions of the Seminole
				Campaign— The company left us early in the Evening, General Jackson being engaged to
				attend the City Assembly and Ball; the last for the Season.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-05">
		<head>5 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-05"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">War of 1812</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>5. VII.</dateline> A succession of visitors occupied the whole day.
					<persRef ref="forsyth-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth</persRef> called at my house to enquire of the
				arrangements to be made for his voyage to Spain— He is to embark in the Hornet at
				Boston for Cadix and I am to prepare his instructions for him as speedily as
				possible— <persRef ref="brent-thomas">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thomas Ludwell Lee Brent</persRef>, now the Secretary
				of Legation at Madrid remains there in that capacity; and young <persRef ref="fenwick-robert">Fenwick</persRef> goes out
				with M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth, as his private Secretary— <persRef ref="graham-john">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> John Graham</persRef> was at the Office; also to enquire how and
				when he is to embark upon his Mission to Rio de Janeiro— The President has
				determined that he is to go in the Congress Frigate now at Norfolk; and after
				landing him she is to go and cruize to protect our trade in the Indian Ocean— <persRef ref="hendricks-william">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Hendricks</persRef> the member of the House of Representatives
				from Indiana, came with some accounts of Printers— <persRef ref="harris-levett">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Levett Harris</persRef>, to take leave, and to say something about the settlement of his own
					<pb type="ms" n="54"/>accounts— He has been here several weeks, endeavouring
				again to obtain some declaration or document from the <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef>, acquitting him of
				the charges of official corruption, while he was Consul at S<hi rend="superscript"
					>t.</hi> Petersburg in the years 1808 and 1809. He has obtained a certificate
				from <persRef ref="cox-charles">Coxe</persRef>, who was Consul at Tunis, the effect of which is to discredit <persRef ref="lewis-william">J. D. Lewis</persRef>,
				whom he represents as the source of all the accusations against him; and he has
				procured declarations from <persRef ref="rodde-diedrich">Rodde</persRef> of Revel and from <persRef ref="kusel-unknown">Küsel</persRef> of Archangel discrediting
				their own former testimony against him— They are artfully drawn up, appearing to
				disavow, but not contradicting any of the facts they had stated. I had most of them
				from Rodde of Revel himself. (see Vol 4. of this Diary Journal of 13. May 1814. p.
				102) and Harris has never dared deny them to me— They make in my opinion a case of
				corruption in Harris, so gross, that the only scruple I have ever had with regard to
				my own conduct in relation to it—a doubt, whether I ought not to have reported it to
				the Government at the time, and broken off all friendly intercourse with him
				forever— But Rodde’s communication to me was confidential, and under an injunction
				of secrecy. The part of an informer, always ungracious, is doubly so, when performed
				by one public Officer against another, with whom he is in relations intimately
				associated— I was aware that if I made the charge the witnesses being themselves
				sharers of both the filth and the lucre, might be tampered with and bribed perhaps
				into a denial of their own statements. The proof was distant and precarious, and I
				was going for an indefinite time to be far distant both from the proof, and from the
				place where it was to be produced. There were circumstances which would at that time
				have given a charge from me against Harris the appearance of being dictated by
				personal animosity or resentment— He had through an intrigue of <persRef ref="dashkov-andrei-">Daschkoff’s</persRef> supplanted <persRef key="smith-william-steuben">W. S. Smith</persRef> my nephew as Secretary to
				the mediation Mission, and the world would readily enough have concluded as <persRef ref="bayard-james">Bayard</persRef>
				did, and told Harris so, that I must be his personal enemy— Lastly, and chiefly, for
				the considerations hitherto mentioned were only prudential, referring to myself, but
				this touches the public concern in the case, Harris was no longer in the situation
				to sell or betray the interest of his country by his venality. The occasion had gone
				by. He might be left in the place then assigned to him, without jeopardizing any
				important public interest. I was therefore silent and have never taken any part
				concerning the charges against him, other than was indispensable— His attempt,
				without giving any notice to me, to saddle the public with the expence of a
				Messenger for <persRef ref="harris-john">his nephew John</persRef>, because he brought one copy of my despatches, at the
				proposal of the mediation, is an instance of unprincipled rapacity, at which I have
				found it difficult to keep my temper. He has pushed for it to the last moment, and
				affected this day, to say, that he thought, upon the explanations he had given me,
				that I had waved my objection to the charge. He asked also now for an outfit as
				charge d’Affaires at S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Petersburg; a charge which he
				had not made, but which he said he understood had been allowed to others— But he had
				charged more than the amount of an outfit for expences of his journey from S<hi
					rend="superscript">t.</hi> Petersburg to London, in pursuit of Mess<hi
					rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Bayard and <persRef ref="gallatin-albert">Gallatin</persRef>, and back to S<hi
					rend="superscript">t.</hi> Petersburg. I told him I had objected to that charge;
				but the President had directed it to be allowed in lieu of an outfit— As no credit
				was given him to draw for his Salary, when he was sent to S<hi rend="superscript"
					>t.</hi> Petersburg as Charge d’Affaires, and he was obliged to live upon his
				own means, I advised and the President directed, that he should be allowed interest
				upon his Salary as it became quarterly due until he was paid— Even this allowance of
				interest is contrary to the rules of the Treasury, and as they have ways of masking
				every thing there, <persRef ref="pleasonton-stephen">Pleasonton</persRef> objected to it as interest, and wanted to allow it
				under the name of loss of exchange— I refused this; for in public affairs one of the
				strongest safe guards of integrity is to call things by their true names; and speak
				of them as they are— <persRef ref="artiguenave-joseph">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Artiguenave</persRef>, sent in to my
				Office a note requesting to see me only for a minute—tres pressé— It was to tell me
				that <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> de Neuville</persRef> had sent for him this morning, in
				great agitation, and begged, intreated, implored him not to recite this Evening the
				<persRef ref="raynal-guillaume">Abbe Raynal’s</persRef> declamation upon American Independence— It was très beau— He, de
				Neuville admired it was much as any man; but he conjured him not to repeat it— If he
				did, not one person of any of the foreign Legations would attend— No! let him take a
				Scene or two from <persRef ref="shakespeare-william">Shakespear</persRef> Amoureux; a most excellent (senseless) piece; and so
				said Artiguenave, what am I to do?— I told him by all means to gratify M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> De Neuville, and turn Shakespear— I attended his
				Séance in the Evening, and Shakespear it was, a French Shakespear. He also repeated
				an Ode of Le Brun, who he said had been called Le Pindare Français— The Ode is
				called Le Vaisseau, and is a loose and dilated paraphrase in eight or ten stanzas,
				of a smaller number of lines in <persRef ref="gray-thomas">Gray’s</persRef> Bard. He also gave us Oreste in the last
				Scene of <persRef ref="racine-jean">Racine’s</persRef> Andromaque. There were fifty or sixty person composing the
				auditory.</p>
		</div>
	</div>
	
	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-06">
		<head>6 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-06"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Suffrage</note>
		</bibl>
		
		<div type="docbody">
			
			<p><pb type="ms" n="55"/><dateline>6. VI:</dateline> <persRef ref="storrow-samuel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Storrow</persRef>, <persRef ref="sherburne-unknown">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Sherburne</persRef>, and a young <persRef ref="weems-unknown2">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Weems</persRef> were morning visitors at my house. Storrow came to take leave; to thank me for
				the advice I had given him, and to tell me that he has determined to settle in the
				State of Ohio, and come forward in the world on the foundation of popular suffrage.
				Storrow is a young man of considerable talents frosted with self-conceit. His
				language; deportment, and very look are full of affectation— Studied
				phraseology—sesquipedalia verba— Ambition to shine—and so enamoured of himself that
				he has scarcely time to bestow a thought upon any thing else— Yet he has acquired
				the good opinion and good will of <persRef ref="brown-jacob">General Brown</persRef> in whose military division he has
				been some time acting as judge Advocate. Sherburne came also to take leave, and to
				repeat his application for the appointment of Commissioner under the Spanish Treaty,
				and to retail once more his family concerns and his wants. Weems is a Son of the
				late <persRef ref="weems-unknown">Doctor Weems</persRef> and came to solicit a place of Clerk in the Department of State;
				or any other public office that I can obtain for him. At one O’Clock, I met <persRef ref="dashkov-andrei">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Daschkoff</persRef> at the President’s house, and presented him
				to the <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef>, to whom he delivered his Letters of recall. He said that in
				presenting them he was commanded by his Sovereign to express the continuance of his
				friendly Sentiments towards the United States, and although it had been his lot to
				reside here in difficult and stormy times he should return to his country with the
				highest respect for the character and institutions of this Nation, of personal
				respect for the <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef>, and of grateful remembrance of the kindness that he had
				experienced here. He spoke with some awkwardness, and evident mortification. The
				President answered him that he received with great satisfaction the assurances of
				the <persRef ref="alexander-i">Emperor’s</persRef> Friendship for the United States— That this Government recollected
				with pleasure the interest which the Emperor on various occasions has taken in their
				favour, and would be earnestly desirous of cultivating and reciprocating his
				friendship in future. With regard to Daschkoff himself he said the Government of the
				United States wished that he might be received with acceptance by his Sovereign, and
				they would learn with pleasure any thing that might contribute to his welfare
				hereafter. And <persRef ref="campbell-george">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Campbell</persRef> would be instructed to
				express the same Sentiments to the Emperor’s Government. Daschkoff was apparently
				much relieved by this kind and gracious dismissal, which he had indeed little
				deserved from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Monroe. No foreign Minister in the
				United States ever had a fairer and easier opportunity of serving faithfully his own
				Sovereign, and at the same time making himself acceptable to the Government to which
				he was accredited— No foreign Minister ever more wantonly threw away all those
				advantages, more grossly outraged this Government, or more rashly hazarded the
				friendship and even the peace between the two Countries. M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Monroe, was so deeply interested and had so great a share in the
				transactions connected with Daschkoff’s misconduct in the affair of <persRef ref="kosloff-nicholas">Kosloff</persRef>, that
				his procaedure to him now is marked with real magnanimity. Daschkoff asked me
				whether he could have an opportunity of paying his respects to, and taking leave of
					<persRef ref="monroe-elizabeth">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Monroe</persRef>— I spoke of it afterwards to the
				President, who said there would either be another drawing room, or he would give the
				foreign Ministers a dinner, before leaving the City for his contemplated Southern
				tour— <persRef key="smith-catherine-johnson">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> W. S. Smith</persRef> dined with us, and <persRef ref="forbes-john">Forbes</persRef> was here
				in the Evening— I am yet unable, even to begin retrieving the long arrears of my
				Journal.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-07">
		<head>7 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-07"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>7. VI:</dateline> <persRef ref="cardelli-pietro">Cardelli</persRef> came to enquire if I had obtained the
				<persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> consent to sit to him, for his bust. I had forgotten to ask it, but
				promised him again to speak for him— I called at <persRef ref="strother-john">Strother’s</persRef> Hotel on <persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General Jackson</persRef>
				with the intention of having some conversation with him, but he was surrounded with
				his Officers and other company so that I was obliged to give up the idea. With the
				exception of the time employed in this walk I was engaged all the day, in drafting
				Instructions for <persRef ref="forsyth-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth</persRef>— <persRef ref="ingersoll-charles">C. J. Ingersoll</persRef> spent the
				Evening with us.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-08">
		<head>8 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-08"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>8. VI:</dateline> Called this morning at the <persRef key="monroe-james">Presidents</persRef> and left with him
				the drafts of Instructions General and Personal to <persRef ref="forsyth-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Forsyth</persRef>— In the course of the Morning <persRef ref="ingersoll-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> C. J. Ingersoll</persRef>
				called upon me with two Notes from the President—one related to the Petition for a
				remission of a judgement of the United States against a man named <persRef ref="sarmiento-unknown">Sarmiento</persRef>,
				sometimes a Portuguese, Sometimes a Citizen of the United States, and sometimes a
				Spaniard— He has been for some years attached pro forma to the Spanish Legation as a
				Secretary— The judgment of the United States against him, is a bondsman for <persRef ref="sarmiento-unknown2">his Son</persRef>,
				upon a breach of the Embargo Laws in 1809— About a <pb type="ms" n="56"/>year ago
				Ingersoll drew up and sent forward a petition for the remission of this judgment;
				which was claimed on the ground of his diplomatic privilege— The President took the
				opinion of the <persRef ref="wirt-william">Attorney General</persRef> upon it; which was against the privilege— Sarmiento
				was then here. His character not in the best repute; and the state of the
				Negotiation such as not to invite any peculiar indulgence to a Spanish intriguer.
				The remission of the judgment was refused— Ingersoll now applies for it again— He
				says that Sarmiento is at Madrid, and has great personal influence there— That he is
				a personal favourite of <persRef ref="ferdinand-vii">the king’s</persRef>; and will be extremely useful to M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth; one of whose objects will be to obtain
				pardon’s for a number of Americans who are in various Spanish prisons— The
				President’s other Note was to say that <persRef key="clay-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Clay</persRef> had been
				with him this Morning, and told him he had been informed the grants of lands made
				last year by the king of Spain in the Florida’s, and which we had understood were
				annulled by the late Treaty, were dated the 23<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> of
				January, one day only before the date assumed in the Treaty, subsequent to which all
				grants are declared to be null and void— The President says in the case an infamous
				fraud has been practiced upon us, and desired me to obtain some declaration from
					<persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</persRef> concerning it; unless the documents in the
				Department would answer the end— I immediately hunted up all <persRef ref="erving-george">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Erving’s</persRef> late Correspondence, and found the copy and translation of the
				grant to the <persRef ref="punonrostro">Count of Puñon Rostro</persRef>, being an order to the <persRef ref="cienfuegos-jose">Governor General of Cuba</persRef>
				to put him in possession of the land— It is dated 6. Feb<hi rend="superscript"
					>y</hi> 1818. which may therefore be considered as the time when the grant was
					<hi rend="italic">made</hi>—and so I considered it when we signed the Treaty,
				for I examined this very paper with a view to ascertain its date before signing the
				Treaty— But now upon a close examination of the paper itself, I found it was not as
					M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Erving described it in his despatch a <hi
					rend="italic">copy</hi> of the grant, but an order to the Governor to put the
				grantee in possession, and referring to the grant itself as having been dated, and
				announced to the Council of the Indies in December 1817. In fair Construction we
				have a right to consider the grant as not <hi rend="italic">made</hi>, until this
				order was issued— Still if I had critically scanned this paper before signing the
				Treaty I should not have agreed to the 24<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> January
				1818 as the date before which all grants are conditionally confirmed— I should have
				insisted upon some months earlier— I came home and dressed, and went and dined,
				(with what appetite I might) with <persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General Jackson</persRef> at his lodgings—Mess<hi
					rend="superscript">rs.</hi> <persRef ref="calhoun-john">Calhoun</persRef>, <persRef ref="thompson-smith">Thompson</persRef> and Wirt were there; but not <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford</persRef>. The rest of the company were Officers, with
					Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> <persRef ref="edwards-ninian">Edwards</persRef>, <persRef ref="eaton-john">Eaton</persRef> and some others. General
				Jackson is to leave the City to-morrow Morning— Immediately after dinner, I
				withdrew, and called upon the French Minister <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">Hyde de Neuville</persRef>— I asked him whether
				in the Negotiation of the late Treaty with Spain, and at the signature, it had not
				been constantly understood by him and by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis, that
				the grants of land in Florida, said to have been made last Winter, by the king of
				Spain, to the <persRef ref="alagon-unknown">Duke of Alagon</persRef>, Count Puñon Rostro, and <persRef ref="vargas-pedro">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Vargas</persRef>, were null and void— He said unquestionably— He recollected specifically only
				the name of the Duke of Alagon, but Onis had also mentioned the names of the others,
				and invariably understood that the grants to them all were annulled by the Treaty— I
				told him it might be necessary that M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis should give
				a declaration to that effect; for there was a rumour in circulation that the grants
				were dated the 23<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> of January 1818 the very day before
				that assumed in the Treaty, subsequent to which the grants were annulled— I said
				that if the grants had been made before the 24<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> of
				January there had been an error in the date proposed by M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Onis and accepted by us, which it would be necessary to rectify, at the
				exchange of the Ratifications and before the Treaty shall have become binding upon
				Spain— That M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth would therefore be instructed on
				exchanging the Ratifications to deliver a Declaration, that the Treaty was signed
				with the full and clear understanding on both sides that those grants were by it,
				null and void; and that they would be accordingly so held by the United States. And
				a declaration to the same effect by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis, might serve
				for the entire satisfaction of the Spanish Government, if they should have any
				doubts on the subject— He said the Spanish Government could have no doubts— They
				knew perfectly well that the grants were annulled, and Onis had himself written to
				his Government proposing a mode of indemnifying the grantees elsewhere— But he would
				go immediately to Onis, and had no doubt he would without hesitation give a
				declaration under his hand that he always understood those grants were to be null
				and void under the Treaty— I returned home, where we had a numerous evening
				party—Onis and his family were not here— They go into no Company; having received
				information, though not official, of the death of the <persRef ref="mariaisabel">Queen of Spain</persRef>. De Neuville
				came late. In the course of the Evening he told me that he had seen M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis, who would readily give a declaration that in
				signing the Treaty, it was with the understanding <pb type="ms" n="57"/>that the
				grants to the Duke of Alagon, Count Puñon Rostro, and Vargas, would be null and void
				under it. But he did not himself know the date of those grants, and as he could not
				suppose them to be before the date assumed in the Treaty, he wished me to write him
				a Note, alluding to the report, and asking of him an explanation. He said Onis
				himself had this Evening named to him all three of the grantees. De Neuville said
				that if Onis’s certificate should not be as explicit as I could desire he would give
				me one that would be as complete as possible— <persRef ref="artiguenave-joseph">Artiguenave</persRef> was of our party this
				Evening, and spoke to me of <persRef ref="otis-harrison">Otis</persRef>— Says he has lost his hopes of the French Mission,
				and is not a little mortified at his disappointment. Several persons of our company
				this Evening remarked that I had a care-clouded countenance. It was emphatically
				true— The discovery that after all the pains I had taken with the eighth Article of
				the Treaty, it might yet be susceptible of so much as a question whether those
				grants are annulled, that this question became possible, by my inattention in not
				thoroughly examining what Erving had transmitted as the copy of Puñon Rostro’s
				grant, before I signed the Treaty, and the consequences, which this carelessness
				might have drawn down upon this Country; aye, and may yet draw down, filled me with
				anxiety and mortification— I have constantly had a vague, general and superstitious
				impression that this Treaty was too great a blessing, not to be followed shortly by
				some thing to alloy it— This is at least enough to damp all vanity and self conceit
				that I could derive from it— Never will this Treaty recur to my Memory, but
				associated with the remembrance of my own heedlessness— Should it hereafter be, as
				it probably will, exposed to the world, and incur from my Country, reproach as
				bitter as my own, it will be no more than I deserve.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-09">
		<head>9 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-09"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Seminole Wars</note>
			<note type="subject">Westward Exploration and Expansion/Westward Migration/Manifest Destiny</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>9. VI:</dateline> After a Night of little, and no cheering repose, I
				drafted this Morning a declaration, to be delivered by <persRef ref="forsyth-john">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Forsyth</persRef> to the Spanish Government, on exchanging the Ratifications of
				the Treaty; and a Letter to <persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</persRef> stating the
				circumstances to him, and asking his answer whether he did not sign the Treaty with
				the Understanding that under it, the three great grants were annulled. I took these
				drafts to the <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef>, to whom I read them, and mentioned my Conversations least
				Evening with <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">De Neuville</persRef>; and the result of my examination of the Paper transmitted
				by <persRef ref="erving-george">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Erving</persRef> as Copy of the grant to <persRef ref="punonrostro">Puñon Rostro</persRef>. The
				President approved the drafts, but directed me to instruct M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Forsyth, if any difficulty should be made by the Spanish Government,
				against receiving the Declaration, he should nevertheless exchange the
				Ratifications; for he considered the Treaty of such transcendent importance to this
				country, that if we should not get an inch of Land in Florida, the bargain would
				still be inexpressibly advantageous to us— The removal of all apprehension of a War
				with Spain, the consolidation of our territorial possessions, the command of the
				gulph of Mexico, the recognized extension to the South Sea, and the satisfaction of
				so large an amount of the claims of our Citizens upon Spain, were objects of such
				paramount consideration, and the attainment of them, would raise our standing and
				character so high in the estimate of the European Powers, that the land was of very
				trifling comparative consequence. Besides as Onis admits that he signed the Treaty
				with the Understanding that the grants were annulled, and De Neuville certifies that
				such was the mutual understanding, if the fact be that they were made before the
					24<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> of January the fraud will be so palpable, that
				when we have got possession of the Country, we shall have the means of doing
				ourselves Justice in our own hands. With regard to <persRef ref="sarmiento-unknown">Sarmiento</persRef>, the President said it
				would be best to remit the judgment against him, and let M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Forsyth take the remission with him—particularly as it might be of
				service to him in obtaining the release of a number of our citizens— I sent to M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis requesting him to call at the Office; and he soon
				came— I read and delivered to him the Letter I had written to him this Morning— He
				told me explicitly that he had signed the Treaty with the Understanding that the
				grants to <persRef ref="alagon-unknown">Alagon</persRef>, Puñon Rostro and <persRef ref="vargas-pedro">Vargas</persRef>, were and would be null and void. He had
				supposed them to be subsequent to the 24<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> of January
				1818. but did not know them to be so. That they had not been made in the ordinary
				way, through the Ministry of Foreign Affairs— They must have passed through some
				other Ministry—perhaps that of Grace and Justice— <persRef ref="pizarro-joseph">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Pizarro</persRef> knew nothing of them— It had been pretended in some of the newspapers of
				this Country, that <persRef ref="laserna-mateo">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> de la Serna</persRef> came here upon those
				affairs, but it was not so. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> de la Serna, was a man
				incapable of having any concern in such transactions. He was and had been many years
				in the diplomatic <pb type="ms" n="58"/>career, and came here to be regularly
				attached to the Legation. The grants had been obtained by some private intrigue, by
				household officers and favourites; and he should explicitly inform his Government
				that he had considered them null and void— He would write to me accordingly, and he
				was perfectly convinced that this little difficulty would prove to be none at all— I
				ransacked again this Morning the whole of Erving’s Correspondence, and found the
				paper transmitted by him as the copy of the grant to Vargas— It is dated 10. March,
				and in the recitals it appears that the whole transaction was subsequent to the
					24<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> of January 1818. Upon this case therefore no
				question can arise, but upon examining the boundaries described in the grant, I
				found that it was land in West Florida, West of the Perdido, and already in
				possession of the United States— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth called at
				the Office, and took leave— He goes to-morrow morning for Boston, to embark in the
				Hornet, <persRef ref="read-george">Captain Read</persRef> for Cadix— His Instructions and Documents were delivered to
				him, and I gave him the form of a Declaration relative to the grants, to be
				delivered on exchanging the Ratifications of the Treaty— A succession of visitors at
				the Office absorbed the day— <persRef ref="poindexter-george">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Poindexter</persRef>, member from
				the State of Mississippi of the late and former Congresses came with a young man
				named <persRef ref="slacumb-unknown">Slacumb</persRef>, who solicits an appointment as Consul at Glasgow and Greenock— <persRef ref="strong-harvey">Harvey
				Strong</persRef> was nominated for that appointment at the late Session of the Senate, and
				rejected— Strong came to me afterwards and intreated that there might be no
				appointment to the place, before the next Session, when he hoped to produce such
				testimonials, as would convince the President of the propriety and Justice of
				nominating him again, and the Senate to confirm the nomination. He said their
				rejection of him had been founded upon an entire misapprehension of certain
				circumstances, which if the <persRef ref="tompkins-daniel">Vice President</persRef>, who strongly recommended him, had been
				present, he would have explained to the full satisfaction of the Senate. I told
				Slacumb that under these Circumstances, it was doubtful whether the President would
				during the Recess of Congress make any appointment for Glasgow; but the application
				should be submitted to his determination— Poindexter was the delegate from
				Mississippi, as long as it was a territory; and has hitherto been its Representative
				since it has been a State. He has now declined being re-elected, and will be a
				serious loss to the Country. He has been one of the ablest boldest, and most
				independent members of the House— And he would have been one of the very first
				members in point of influence, but for the habits of his private life, which is in
				bad repute—gaming and double wives, and other irregularities of morals; not
				worse—perhaps not so bad as <persRef key="clay-henry">Clay</persRef>; but by which he is more discredited. <persRef ref="montesquieu-unknown">Montesquieu</persRef>
				says that <persRef ref="caesar-julius">Julius Caesar</persRef> had not one fault, though he had many vices— Clay, like
				Caesar turns his vices to political account, and makes a merit, of that which
				degrades and ruins others. Poindexter has not the same address, and though a man of
				sounder mind, and more steady principle, and at least equal eloquence, he has
				nothing like the same influence in Congress, or the same standing in public opinion—
				<persRef ref="edwards-ninian">Edwards</persRef> the Senator from Illinois—<persRef ref="dana-samuel">Dana</persRef> from Connecticut, <persRef ref="ingersoll-charles">Ingersoll</persRef>, <persRef ref="mcrae-alexander">M’Rae</persRef>, the
				appointed Consul for Amsterdam, and <persRef ref="mitchell-john">Mitchell</persRef> the late Consul at Martinique were also
				at the Office, and with each of these persons I had conversation upon different
				topics, connected with public interests; general or particular. To record them all
				would be useful if I had the time; but it would be a desperate undertaking. With
				Edwards it was upon the Western appointments—with Dana upon <persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General Jackson</persRef>, the
				Seminole War, and the Treaty with Spain— With Ingersoll upon the remission of the
				Judgment against Sarmiento, which was made out, and delivered to M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth—with M’Rae upon the Virginia politics, <persRef ref="leigh-benjamin">Watkins
				Leigh</persRef>, <persRef ref="selden-unknown">Selden</persRef>, and the league between 
				<persRef ref="giles-william">Giles</persRef>, <persRef ref="nicholas-wilson">W. C. Nicholas</persRef> and <persRef ref="randolph-john">John Randolph</persRef>, as he
				says against M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Monroe— With Mitchell, upon a new
				Ordinance in the island of Martinique, excluding all foreigners from residing there
				as Merchants— Evening at home.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-10">
		<head>10 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-10"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
			<note type="subject">Recreation</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>10. VI:45.</dateline> I received this morning from <persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> de Onis</persRef> two Notes—one in answer to my Letter of yesterday, explicitly
				admitting that he had understood on signing the Treaty, that the grants to the <persRef ref="alagon-unknown">Duke
				of Alagon</persRef>, and others, similarly circumstanced, were null and void; but adding that
				if he had known those grants were of prior date he should have insisted upon their
				validity—and requesting my answer to this other Note which asks a variety of
				explanation of the act against piracy passed at the late Session of Congress— I
				wrote immediately to <persRef ref="forsyth-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth</persRef>, who left the City this
				Morning, and enclosed to him copies of my Letter to Onis and of his Answer. At the
				<persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> I met <persRef ref="thompson-smith">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thompson</persRef> the Secretary of the Navy,
				who had been writing to the <persRef ref="wirt-william">Attorney General</persRef> asking his opinion upon the
				construction of the same act against Piracy, concerning which Onis had written to
				me. The Act is very loosely worded, and throws much responsibility upon the
				Executive Administration. The President will not come to any determination upon it
				at present.— I attended an Evening party, at <persRef ref="thornton-william">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Thornton’s</persRef> <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef> was unwell, and not able to go— I
				engaged <persRef ref="tucker-thomas">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Tucker</persRef> the Treasurer, at a game <pb type="ms"
					n="59"/>of Chess, which detained us half an hour after all the rest of the
				Company was gone— There was a young man belonging to Georgetown, named <persRef ref="travers-unknown">Travers</persRef>,
				brother of <persRef ref="cook-thomas">T. Cook’s</persRef> <persRef ref="cook-unknown">late wife</persRef>, who was to have gone with M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Forsyth to Spain, but shot himself early this Morning.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-11">
		<head>11 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-11"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>11. VII:</dateline> On rising this morning I was surprized to find the
				ground covered with Snow; and Snow-storm, which continued violent till the approach
				of Evening, when it turned to rain— For the first time for a full Month, I was able
				to open this Book, where I found the Diary suspended at the 11<hi rend="superscript"
					>th.</hi> of February p. 32. and sat myself seriously to work upon the minute
				index, to which I constantly keep from day to day, to retrieve its arrears
				(2:[symbols]) <persRef ref="cardelli-pietro">Cardelli</persRef> came to me in the midst of the Storm to enquire if I had
				obtained the President’s consent to sit to him. I had for gotten him again; but
				promised to forget him no longer— I rode in the Carriage to and from my Office,
				where I was occupied chiefly in reading over <persRef ref="sumter-thomas">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sumter’s</persRef>
				despatches, to make preparation for giving instructions to <persRef ref="graham-john">J. Graham</persRef>, as Minister
				Plenipotentiary to Rio de Janeiro. We had a Company of Gentlemen to dinner— <persRef ref="marshall-john">Chief
				Justice Marshall</persRef>, and the Judges <persRef ref="washington-bushrod">Washington</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="johnson-william">Johnson</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="livingston-henry">Livingston</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="duval-gabriel">Duval</persRef> and
				<persRef ref="story-joseph">Story</persRef>—and Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> 
				<persRef ref="anderson-joseph">Anderson</persRef>, Comptroller of the Treasury
				and <persRef ref="anderson-alexander">his Son Alexander</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="caldwell-elias">Caldwell</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="frye-nathaniel">Frye</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="hopkinson-joseph">Hopkinson</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="jones-walter">Walter Jones</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="mccormick-unknown">M’Cormick</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="ringgold-tench">Tench Ringgold</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="thruston-buckner">Judge Thruston</persRef> and 
				<persRef ref="thruston-thomas">his Son</persRef> and 
				<persRef ref="winder-william-henry">Winder</persRef>. Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi>
				<persRef ref="dana-samuel">Dana</persRef>, of the Senate, 
				<persRef ref="davis-john2">J. P. Davis</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="ingersoll-charles">Ingersoll</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="mcrae-alexander">M’Rae</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="sergeant-john">J. Sergeant</persRef>, 
				<persRef key="smith-william-steuben">W. S. Smith</persRef>,
				<persRef ref="verplanck-gulian">Verplanck</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="webster-daniel">Webster</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="wheaton-henry">Wheaton</persRef> and 
				<persRef ref="wirt-william">Wirt</persRef>, had been invited; but Verplanck and Webster
				were gone. Dana, Ingersoll, and Sergeant left the City yesterday, or this Morning,
				and the others were prevented by various accidents from coming. <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi
					rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef> was unwell, and did not dine with us. The
				company broke up about nine in the Evening.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-12">
		<head>12 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-12"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">African Americans</note>
			<note type="subject">American Revolution</note>
			<note type="subject">Anti-Slavery Movements</note>
			<note type="subject">Colonization Movements</note>
			<note type="subject">Dueling</note>
			<note type="subject">Louisiana Purchase</note>
			<note type="subject">Oregon Territory</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
			<note type="subject">Slave Trade</note>
			<note type="subject">Slavery</note>
			<note type="subject">U.S. Constitution</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>12. VII:</dateline> At the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> this morning, he mentioned that he
				wished shortly to have a meeting of the members of the Administration, to consider
				the effect of the Acts passed at the late Session of Congress against Piracy, and
				Slave trade; and he intimated that the Committee of the Colonization Society had
				applied to him, to purchase a territory on the Coast of Africa, to which the Slaves
				who may be taken under the late Act may be sent. The President said there had been
				only an appropriation of one hundred thousand dollars; which could not be sufficient
				for purchasing a territory; but perhaps Congress would appropriate more hereafter. I
				told him I thought it impossible that Congress should have had any purchase of
				territory in contemplation of that Act, and that I had no opinion of the
				practicability or of the usefulness of the objects proposed by the Colonization
				Society; which object professes to be, to establish a Colony in Africa; where all
				the free blacks and people of Colour of the United States may be sent and settled—
				The project is professed to be formed 1. without intending to use any compulsion
				upon the free people of colour, to make them go. 2. To encourage the emancipation of
				Slaves by their Masters. 3. To promote the entire abolition of Slavery—and yet 4.
				Without in the slightest degree affecting, what they call a certain species of
				property—that is the property of Slaves— There are men of all sorts and descriptions
				concerned in this Colonization Society; some exceedingly humane, weak-minded men,
				who have really no other than the professed objects in view; and who honestly
				believe them both useful and attainable. Some speculators in official profits and
				honours which a colonial establishment would of course produce— Some speculators in
				political popularity, who think to please the abolitionists by their zeal for
				emancipation, and the Slave holders by the flattering hope of ridding them of the
				free coloured people, at the public expence— Lastly some cunning Slaveholders who
				see that the plan may be carried far enough to produce the effect of raising the
				market price of their Slaves— But although the plan obviously imports the engrafting
				of a Colonial Establishment upon the Constitution of the United States, and thereby
				an accession of power to the National Government, transcending all its other powers;
				and although this tremendous machinery would be introduced under an ostensible
				purpose comparatively so trivial, and in a captivating form which might bring it in
				unperceived, I do not believe that is the actuating motive of any one member of the
				Society— For it would only be the motive of a man whose magnificence of design, and
				depravity of principle, would both go beyond my opinions of any man belonging to the
				Institution. The President said this subject had been recommended by a Resolution of
				the Virginia Legislature. And then he enlarged upon the great earnestness there was
				in Virginia, for the gradual abolition of <pb type="ms" n="60"/>Slavery, and upon
				the excellent and happy condition of the Slaves in that State—upon the kindness with
				which they were treated, and the mutual attachment subsisting between them and their
				Masters— He said that the feeling against Slavery was so strong that shortly after
				the close of our Revolution, many persons had voluntarily emancipated their Slaves;
				but this had introduced a class of very dangerous people, the free blacks, who lived
				by pilfering, and corrupted the Slaves; and produced such pernicious consequences,
				that the Legislature were obliged to prohibit further emancipation by Law— The
				important object now, was to remove these free blacks, and provide a place to which
				the emancipated Slaves might go—the legal obstacles to emancipation might then be
				withdrawn, and the black population in time be drawn off entirely from Virginia— At
				the Office the Committee from the Society, <persRef ref="mason-john">General John Mason</persRef>, <persRef ref="jones-walter">Walter Jones</persRef> and
				<persRef ref="key-francis">Francis S. Key</persRef> came and renewed the subject— Jones argued that the late Slave trade
				Act contained a clear authority to settle a Colony in Africa, and that the purchase
				of Louisiana, and the settlement, at the Mouth of Columbia river, placed beyond all
				question the right of acquiring territory, as existing in the Government of the
				United States— I treated these Gentlemen with all possible civility; but gave them
				distinctly to understand that the late Slave trade Act, had no reference to the
				Settlement of a Colony; and that the acquisition of Louisiana, and the establishment
				at the mouth of Columbia river, being in territory contiguous to and continuous with
				our own, could by no means warrant the purchase of Countries beyond the Seas, or the
				establishment of a Colonial System of Government subordinate to and dependant upon
				that of the United States. To derive powers competent to this from the Slave trade
				act, was an Indian Cosmogony— It was mounting the World upon an Elephant, and the
				Elephant upon a Tortoise with nothing for the Tortoise to stand upon. They took
				leave of me with good humour; but satisfied I believe that they will have no aid
				from me— A politician would have flattered them. <persRef ref="barton-william">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Barton</persRef> of Philadelphia came to me with a Letter of recommendation from <persRef ref="ewing-samuel">S. Ewing</persRef>,
				and <persRef ref="sergeant-john">J. Sergeant</persRef>— Barton is a Surgeon with a family, and author of several valuable
				Botanical Works— But he has some office in the Medical Marine Department which the
				<persRef ref="thompson-smith">Secretary of the Navy</persRef> has determined to suppress as useless; of which Barton having
				received very short an unexpected notice, is thrown upon the world, and deprived of
				his principle means of support. He came therefore to obtain if possible a
				revocation, but at least a respite of the suppressing order; and asks my influence,
				with the Secretary of the Navy, in his favour— As I was returning home to dinner, I
				met <persRef ref="edwards-ninian">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Edwards</persRef> the Senator from Illinois— I had seen by
				the newspapers that he had been re-elected by the Legislature of the State; which I
				mentioned and told him I now hoped he would come— He said yes— He had hoped his
				friends would have been able to agree upon some other person, to take his place; but
				they could not— Now however he should not be obliged to return home after every
				Session of Congress, and travel twice a year eleven hundred miles to take his seat.
				I told him <persRef ref="parker-daniel">General Parker</persRef>, had said to me the other Evening at <persRef ref="thornton-william">D<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Thornton’s</persRef>, that he was afraid <persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General Jackson</persRef> had
				gone from this City to Virginia with the determination to challenge <persRef ref="eppes-john">J. W. Eppes</persRef>— I
				hoped it was not so— He said no— That he had intended it. That some intimation of
				this intention had been given to the President, and <persRef ref="monroe-joseph">J. J. Monroe</persRef> had come with two
				earnest messages to him, to interfere and restrain Jackson from this design— He had
				called upon him and met <persRef ref="eaton-john">Eaton</persRef> of Tennessee coming from him. Eaton had been
				endeavouring to appease him, without success. When he Edwards went in he found
				Jackson, exasperated beyond any thing that he ever witnessed in Man— But Jackson was
				always willing to listen to the advice of those whom he knew to be his friends, and
				to give it all due weight— So he sat down with him and argued the case till two or
				three O’Clock in the Morning; and then left him perfectly calm and good-humoured,
				and rescued from his project of fighting Eppes— But when he had first represented to
				Jackson, that it would have the appearance of an attempt to overawe members of the
				Legislature in the exercise of their functions, his answer was— But, by ——— Sir, the
					4<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> of March is past— Any man, may “approve or
				disapprove my actions, at his pleasure—but my motives—no man shall impeach my
				motives with impunity”— However, Edwards pressed upon him, that his friends by the
				earnestness with which they had defended him, had made his cause their own, and that
				any indiscretion or intemperate violence on his part, would affect them in the
				public opinion almost as much as himself—a consideration to which he <pb type="ms"
					n="61"/>finally yielded; and he went off quite cool and composed. Of all this I
				had no knowledge at the time. I spent this Evening at home, and at last seriously
				occupied upon the Journal.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-13">
		<head>13 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-13"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Sectionalism</note>
			<note type="subject">South, The</note>
			<note type="subject">Supreme Court</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>13. VI:15.</dateline> Met <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford</persRef> this
				morning at the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef>; the first time he has been out since his illness. I
				applied again to the President in favour of <persRef ref="cardelli-pietro">Cardelli</persRef>, that he would sit to him for
				his bust; to which he consented, and allowed me to send Cardelli to him to-morrow
				Morning— The President has determined to set out the last week of this Month upon a
				tour of three or four Months to the South and West— As the <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">Ministers of France</persRef>,
				<persRef ref="onis-luis">Spain</persRef> and <persRef key="bagot-charles">England</persRef>, are all going to Europe on leave of absence, before he will
				return, and it is very doubtful whether either of them will ever come back, and as
				the <persRef ref="dashkov-andrei">Russian Minister Daschkoff</persRef> is finally recalled, they were all desirous of some
				occasion upon which they might take leave of the President, and of <persRef ref="monroe-elizabeth">his Lady</persRef>. After
				some consideration whether it should be by an extra drawing room or a dinner, he
				concluded upon the last, and invites the whole Corps Diplomatique to dine with him
				next Tuesday. The former President’s, particularly <persRef ref="jefferson-thomas">Jefferson</persRef> and <persRef ref="madison-james">Madison</persRef>, have
				admitted to a certain extent social visits from the foreign Ministers— M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Monroe, upon principle has excluded this sort of
				intercourse, and receives them only 1. at private Audiences, requested by them 2. At
				the Drawing-Rooms. 3. At Diplomatic Dinners; once or twice a Winter— But here arise
				certain questions of etiquette and precedency which it has become necessary to
				settle. Heretofore, it has been invariably customary for the Secretary of State to
				be invited by the President to all the Dinners given by him to the Diplomatic Corps;
				and as there are no Ambassadors among them but only Ministers of the second order,
				they have acquiesced in the principle adopted here that the Secretary of State takes
				precedence of them— Since the commencement however of the present Administration,
					M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Monroe has been given to understand that the
				other heads of Departments, expect an entire equality with the Secretary of State,
				and would consider it as an offensive distinction in his favour, if he should alone
				of them be invited to the Diplomatic Dinners— On the other hand the Foreign
				Ministers, though willing to yield precedence to the Secretary of State, are not
				willing, at dinners of professed ceremony given to them; to be thrown at the bottom
				of the table, by postponement to four or five heads of department and their wives.
				To avoid these difficulties, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Monroe last Winter
				invited the foreign Ministers, without any of the heads of Departments; and to fill
				up the table invited with them the Navy Commissioners, and some respectable private
				inhabitants of the City— But this did not escape remark. The foreign Ministers, were
				not pleased at being invited with persons of inferior rank, and private citizens;
				nor at the absence of the Secretary of State, with whom they had usually been
				associated on these occasions heretofore— The slight to the Secretary of State to
				himself, by the omission to invite him as heretofore was also noticed; not by me,
				for I knew nothing either of the usage, or of the departure from it, till a year
				after; but by the foreign Ministers, and by all the gossips of the district who have
				drawn many shrewd conclusions from it— Soon after the commencement of the late
				Session of Congress, the President informed me that he meant to give the foreign
				Ministers a dinner, and to invite me, and <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">my wife</persRef> to it, as had been customary. But
				he delicately alluded to the punctilious pretensions of the other heads of
				departments to equality; and to the objections of the foreign Ministers to being
				crowded down to the bottom of the table; and he asked my advice— It was at a time
				when I went into no company; and I requested the President, on that account to put
				me out of the question, and not include me in the invitation. This answered for that
				time; but now the questions again recurred, and again the President asked my advice.
				I know not whether he had considered it as I did, but with my sentiments of
				delicacy, to ask the question was to dictate the answer. I advised and requested him
				again to omit sending an invitation to me; and with a view to reconcile all parties
				hereafter, to invite to his Diplomatic Dinners, one of the Heads of Departments
				only—taking them alternately; to which he acceded, and such is hereafter to be the
				practice— These incidents apparently so insignificant and contemptible are connected
				with all the pantings of Crawford’s ambition, and with the future History of this
				Nation and of the world. By the superior real and inherent importance of the
				Department of State, in the organization of this Government <pb type="ms" n="62"
				/>and by the successive transfer of two Secretaries of State to the Presidency, a
				general impression has pervaded the Union, of a higher consideration due to that
				Department, and that in the practice of the Government it is the natural
				introduction to the Head of the Executive— It is now in all the Legislative Acts
				first named among the Departments, as the Treasury is the second. Until the late
				Session of Congress, the Salaries of the Officers at the head of these Departments
				was higher than that of the two others. But a great and unceasing effort has been
				making at the two Sessions of the late Congress, to bring all the Departments to a
				level; and the President has been notified that the mere established usage by which
				the Secretary of State was alone invited to the Diplomatic Dinners, would henceforth
				be considered as a distinction offensive to the other Heads of Departments— To this
				notification the President has assented; for to ask my advice upon it was to settle
				the question— And from this operation of the incident upon his mind, is apparent the
				course that he will take, in the Event for which Crawford is so indefatigably and so
				anxiously preparing. At the Legislative Caucus, preliminary to the last election,
				Crawford was the Candidate, and came near to be the successful Candidate against
					M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Monroe— As the candidate of a very powerful
				minority then, he stands naturally the most prominent Candidate after the close of
					M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Monroe’s Presidential career, he is a native
				Virginian, and has all the sympathies of Southern interests and Southern feelings in
				his favour. On the ordinary impulses to human opinions and conduct, M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Monroe must ultimately favour Crawford’s pursuits, and
				this occurrence trivial as it is, furnishes one among many proofs that such will be
				the fact— I can see nothing in it of which I have any right to complain. It proves
				that the relative position of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Monroe, of Crawford and
				of myself towards each other is a very bad one. That mine in particular, is
				peculiarly bad, and probably to be remedied in no other manner than by my
				withdrawing from it— An Event for which I have only to wish that my mind may be duly
				prepared— I received this day a Letter from <persRef ref="cranch-william">judge Cranch</persRef>, enclosing one to <persRef ref="graham-john">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> John Graham</persRef>, recommending <persRef ref="cranch-william2">his son William Cranch</persRef> to
				him, to go as private Secretary, and preceptor for his children, with him, to Rio de
				Janeiro. Evening at home and much engaged in writing— Supreme Court adjourned
				yesterday.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-14">
		<head>14 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-14"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Recreation</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>14. VI:30.</dateline> Between one and four O’Clock, I walked nearly to the
				borders of Georgetown and on my return home found an enormous budget of despatches
				and Letters, brought by the Mail— The most important were from <persRef key="rush-richard">R. Rush</persRef> at London,
				and <persRef ref="irvine-baptis">Baptis Irvine</persRef> at Angostura— The reading of these packets and of the Newspapers
				consumed three or four hours, and the remainder of the day and evening were absorbed
				in writing the journal 13<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> 14<hi rend="superscript"
					>th.</hi> and part of the 15<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> of February—the
				arrears amounting still to an entire Month.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-15">
		<head>15 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-15"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
			<note type="subject">Slave Trade</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>15. VI:</dateline> <persRef ref="rhea-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Rhea</persRef>, a Member of the
				late Congress from Tennessee called at my house this Morning and took leave; to
				return home— I took <persRef ref="hellen-mary">Mary Hellen</persRef> to see the wild animals exhibited in a new building
				opposite to <persRef ref="gibson-unknown">Gibson’s</persRef> Hotel in our neighbourhood—A Lion—a pair of Camels, male and
				female, a South-American Lama, and a number of Baboons and Monkeys. At the
				<persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> He directed a meeting of the members of the Administration to-morrow, to
				consider the two Acts, passed at the late Session of Congress, concerning Piracy and
				the Slave trade. The <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">French Minister Hyde de Neuville</persRef> came to the Office; with
				complaints of French Vessels robbed by piratical privateers from Baltimore. He told
				me he had given <persRef ref="forsyth-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth</persRef> a Letter to the French
				Ambassador at Madrid, and would write him another, informing him of the
				understanding at the signature of the Treaty with Spain that it annulled the grants
				to <persRef ref="alagon-unknown">Alagon</persRef> <persRef ref="punonrostro">Puñon Rostro</persRef> and <persRef ref="vargas-pedro">Vargas</persRef>— I accidentally mentioned to him the late change
				of the Ministry in France. The resignation of the <persRef ref="richelieu-armand">Duke de Richelieu</persRef>; the appointment
				of the <persRef ref="dessolles-jean">Marquis Dessolles</persRef> as Minister of Foreign Affaires, and the triumph of <persRef ref="decazes-elie">De
				Cazes</persRef>, now nominally Minister of the Interior; and in reality at the head of the
				Cabinet— He had not heard a word of it, and was thunder struck at the news; from
				which he foreboded nothing good to himself— I regretted having mentioned it to him—
				I lent him at his desire the English Newspapers which I received yesterday and which
				contain the information of this change of Affairs in France— <persRef ref="forbes-john">J. M. Forbes</persRef> came also
				to the <pb type="ms" n="63"/>office— He has now an eye upon the place of Post-master
				at Boston, held at present by <persRef ref="hill-aaron">Aaron Hill</persRef>, but who he thinks will soon resign. <persRef ref="waterhouse-benjamin">D<hi
					rend="superscript">r.</hi> Benjamin Waterhouse</persRef> is also an applicant for the
				place. I spent the Evening at a party at <persRef ref="lee-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> William
				Lee’s</persRef>. <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef> was unwell with a Cold, and could not
				go. I told the <persRef ref="correa-joseph">Abbè Correa</persRef> the Portuguese Minister that I wished to have some
				conversation with him, and he promised to call at my Office the day after
				to-morrow.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-16">
		<head>16 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-16"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">African Americans</note>
			<note type="subject">Colonization Movements</note>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Internal Improvements</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
			<note type="subject">Slave Trade</note>
			<note type="subject">Slavery</note>
			<note type="subject">South American Wars of Independence</note>
			<note type="subject">War of 1812</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>16. VI:45.</dateline> The meeting of the Heads of Departments, was held
				this day at the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef>, from Noon till four O’Clock, to consider the Slave
				trade and Piracy Acts, passed at the late Session of Congress, and what Instructions
				it would be proper to give to the Commanders of the armed vessels of the United
				States, for carrying them into execution. It was soon settled that the Slave trade
				act gave no authority to the President to purchase a territory or establish a Colony
				in Africa—though it does authorize him to take measures for removing beyond the
				limits of the United States, the Negroes who may be taken, as imported contrary to
				Law, and to appoint an Agent to receive them in Africa. <persRef ref="jones-walter">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Walter Jones’s</persRef> argument is that the Negroes when received there cannot
				be left to starve—that something must be done with them there— That lands must be
				given them to cultivate, which lands must be first owned by the United States—
				Therefore the President must have the right to purchase land for the Nation, and to
				settle a Colony. <persRef ref="calhoun-john">Calhoun</persRef> and <persRef ref="thompson-smith">Thompson</persRef> scouted this construction of the act, and I
				therefore said nothing about it— <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">Crawford</persRef> is one of the Vice-President’s of the
				Colonization Society, but says the has no faith in the practicability of their
				projects— It is one of his traps for popularity— Thompson mentioned to <persRef ref="wirt-william">Wirt</persRef> that he
				had sent him a number of questions for his opinion upon the construction of the
				Piracy Act; and I read the Note from the <persRef ref="onis-luis">Spanish Minister Onis</persRef>, in which he puts
				many questions concerning it— By the third section of the Act, Merchant vessels of
				the United States are authorized to defend themselves and resist by force the <hi
					rend="italic">search</hi>, of any armed vessel, not being a <hi rend="italic"
					>public armed vessel</hi>, of some nation in amity with the United States— It
				was observed that this authorized resistance against the search of lawful
				privateers. I insisted that this could not be the meaning of the Act. Wirt and
				Crawford contended that the words <hi rend="italic">public</hi> armed vessels were
				always used in contradistinction to <hi rend="italic">private</hi> armed vessels,
				the denomination exclusively applied to privateers: and Crawford referred to several
				Acts of Congress passed during the late War, in which the terms were respectively so
				used. I replied that those Acts all had reference both to our own public ships and
				privateers; the latter of which were therefore denominated private armed vessels, to
				distinguish them from the others.— But that in describing under general expressions
				the armed vessels of foreign Nations, authorized by the Laws of Nations to search
				neutral vessels, the words <hi rend="italic">public</hi> armed vessels must be
				understood to include privateers regularly commissioned which in that sense are
				public armed vessels. This reasoning was not altogether satisfactory to others,
				though it was entirely conclusive to me. All agreed that the Act was very loosely
				worded, but as the Section applied only to a power given to the commanders and crews
				of merchant vessels, it was seen that there was no necessity for the Executive to
				give any construction if it, at present. But as the Commanders of our Public Ships
				are to be instructed under the Act to capture any vessel which shall have committed
				any piratical aggression upon any citizen or vessel of the United States, or <hi
					rend="italic">any other vessel</hi>, the important question was what should be
				understood as a <hi rend="italic">piratical</hi> aggression, and incidental to it,
				what flags and Commissions of the revolutionary South Americans, should be admitted
				as legalizing the exercise of the ordinary rights of War, without coming under the
				denomination of piratical aggression— The question was made, what South-American
				flags were to be admitted as valid; but it was not much considered— The President
				was averse to drawing any line of discrimination, in the form of Executive
				Instructions; which should recognize one flag, and outlaw another. I observed that
				the great object of the Act was the protection of our own Commerce—the material
				incident upon which the authority to capture was given, was some previous
				aggression; and I thought the instructions ought to hinge principally upon that
				fact— If the Commanders of our Ships should meet a vessel, and know of any
				aggression committed by her upon American Citizens or property, I thought he might
				safely presume the piratical character of the Act, and bring her in for adjudication
				without much enquiry under what flag or Commission she had acted. M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi>
				<pb type="ms" n="64"/>Thompson concurred in this opinion, and no objection to it
				being made, it was understood that the instructions should be prepared accordingly.
				The President said it was probable that the operation of this Law, so far as it
				would affect the parties to the South-American War would be against the Patriots
				more than against Spain— Our agents, <persRef ref="irvine-baptis">Irvine</persRef> at Angostura, and <persRef ref="halsey-thomas">Halsey</persRef> and <persRef ref="worthington-william">Worthington</persRef>
				at Buenos-Ayres, had been to say the least indiscreet— The Agents of the
				South-Americans here <persRef ref="aguirre-manuel">Aguirre</persRef>, <persRef ref="gual-pedro">Gual</persRef> and <persRef ref="clemente-lino">Clemente</persRef> had been still more so. The tendency
				of their conduct had been on both sides to embroil us; while it was our mutual
				interest to lie on the best terms together, and while we had been not only rendering
				them important services, but promoting the cause of their Independence far more than
				we could have done by a formal acknowledgment of their Independence. The result of
				our former Commission to Buenos-Ayres had been favourable, and the effect produced
				by it, and by our subsequent measures upon the policy and conduct of the European
				allies had been highly advantageous to them— He thought it would be advisable to
				send one of our public Ships to Buenos-Ayres, with a Commissioner, a person of the
				most trusty character and the highest respectability; to explain confidentially to
				the Government at Buenos-Ayres all these Circumstances; to shew the necessity from
				which the Piracy act arose; to furnish them with a copy, and translation of it; to
				expostulate with them both against the conduct of their agents here, and against the
				irregularities and excesses of their privateers; to remonstrate against their
				sending blank Commissions, to be filled up here, and to ask them to furnish a list
				of their commissioned vessels— The President added that he proposed to draw up a
				paper as a foundation for the Instructions to be given to such an agent; and asked
				who it would be proper to appoint; saying he had himself thought either of <persRef ref="poinsett-joel">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Poinsett</persRef>, or of one of the former Commissioners <persRef ref="rodney-caesar">Rodney</persRef>
				or <persRef ref="bland-theoderick">Bland</persRef>— I asked if Poinsett would accept the appointment—the President did not
				know, and Calhoun thought it certain that he would not— He had declined being a
				member of the former Commission, and was now deeply engaged in schemes of internal
				improvement at home— Various objections were suggested to either of the former
				Commissioners, as well as to their Secretary <persRef ref="brackenridge-henry">Brackenridge</persRef>, who was also mentioned—
				The President finally reserved it for further consideration— I had scarcely half an
				hour this day for the Office— In the Evening M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				<persRef ref="bourqueney-francois">Bourqueney</persRef> the Secretary of the French Legation came fresh from the President’s
				diplomatic dinner, with a Letter from <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hyde de
				Neuville</persRef>, to the <persRef ref="laval-unknown">Duke de Laval Montmorency</persRef>, the French Ambassador at Madrid, which
				was left open for me to read, and then have sealed and forwarded to <persRef ref="forsyth-john">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth</persRef>— It contained a declaration that it was
				understood when the Treaty was signed that the grants of Land to <persRef ref="alagon-unknown">Alagon</persRef>, <persRef ref="punonrostro">Puñon
				Rostro</persRef> and <persRef ref="vargas-pedro">Vargas</persRef>, were null and void. After I had read it, Bourqueney sealed it and
				I enclosed it under cover to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth at Boston— I
				also desired him at M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> De Neuville’s request, in case
				the Duke de Laval should no longer be the French Ambassador in Spain when he arrives
				there; not to deliver the other Letter which De Neuville had given him for Laval, to
				any other person—his successor— This precaution arises from the late change in the
				French Ministry.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-17">
		<head>17 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-17"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>17. VII.</dateline> <persRef ref="cranch-william">Judge Cranch </persRef>called here this morning with his
				<persRef ref="cranch-william2">Son William</persRef>, whom he had some encouragement to expect <persRef ref="graham-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				John Graham</persRef> would take with him as his private Secretary and preceptor to his
				children. After making some enquiries of me they went to M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Graham’s. I drafted a private Letter to the <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">French Minister Hyde de
				Neuville</persRef>, requesting answers to six questions in relation to the <hi rend="italic"
					>grants—</hi> These questions were founded upon circumstances which he has
				repeatedly mentioned to me in the Conversations between us— One was that <persRef ref="onis-luis">Onis</persRef> had
				told him he made it a point of honour that those grants should be annulled, because
				rumours had been in circulation, and even alluded to in our newspapers, that he was
				personally interested in them— Another, that he De Neuville had the certain
				knowledge, from sources other than those to which I had access, that the Spanish
				Government itself were aware that those grants were annulled by the Treaty— But as I
				doubted whether De Neuville would like to answer directly these questions in
				writing, I took the draft with me to the Office; sent for him, and reading it to him
				asked if he would prefer to have it in any other form— He said the delicacy due from
				him to the Spanish Government, and to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis scarcely
				allowed him to suppose it possible that any occasion should arise to make a direct
				answer to these questions from him necessary— He wished therefore that I would ask
				him in <pb type="ms" n="65"/>more general terms a statement of his knowledge and
				participation in these transactions, and he would immediately send me an answer,
				with reference to my questions, which he would recollect, and with all suitable
				decorum with regard to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis— And if afterwards any
				thing further and still more explicit should be necessary he would give it without
				hesitation; for honour and honesty could have but one course, and he felt his own
				concerned in the fairness and good faith of this transaction. He had already written
				an account of the whole affair to his own Government, by his Messenger <persRef ref="demun-unknown">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> De Mun</persRef>, who sailed from Newcastle Delaware, for France
				on the 10<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> (Onis also sent <persRef ref="zamorana-unknown">Zamorano</persRef>, as a special
				Messenger, with the Treaty. He had first asked a passage for him in the Hornet to go
				with M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth; which was readily granted; but he
				afterwards concluded to send him on before <persRef ref="forsyth-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth</persRef>
				was ready; and he sailed the 9<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> from New-York for
				Lisbon.) I wrote a Letter to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> De Neuville, as he had
				requested, asking in general terms a statement of what he had known during the
				negotiation, and at the conclusion of the Treaty, concerning the Grants; and
				received his answer this Evening.— While he was at the Office I communicated to him
				the substance of despatches received yesterday from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				<persRef ref="gallatin-albert">Gallatin</persRef>, giving a particular account of the change of the French Ministry and its
				causes. He had no official account of it himself— He said he did not know, but that
				he was to expect his immediate recall. He comforts himself however with the
				reflection, that “Les choses sont plus fortes que les hommes.” He is a man of
				singularly compounded character— A mixture of ultra-royalism and republican
				liberality— Frank, candid, honourable, generous, benevolent, humane, devoted to and
				adoring his Country; worshiping Monsieur, <persRef ref="artois-charles">the king’s brother</persRef> and the <persRef ref="angouleme-louis">Duke</persRef> and
				<persRef ref="angouleme-marie">Duchess d’Angoulême</persRef>, adhering upon a principle of honour to his party, but detesting
				the foreigners by whom his <persRef ref="louis-xviii">king</persRef> was restored, and most especially the English. He is
				flighty, but not inconstant in his Sentiments; accessible to reason, but not
				powerful as a reasoner, quick, but placable in his temper. Has little knowledge of
				Literature, and less of Science. Somewhat vain; and manageable chiefly by his
				Vanity. Altogether, a safe man with whom to transact business, and one whose good
				qualities, greatly outweigh his failings.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-18">
		<head>18 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-18"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
			<note type="subject">Recreation</note>
			<note type="subject">Seminole Wars</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>18. VI:</dateline> <persRef ref="scott-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Scott</persRef>, the Delegate to
				the late Congress from the Missouri Territory, came this morning and took leave.
				<persRef ref="edwards-ninian">Edwards</persRef> of Illinois is gone. At the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> I met <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Crawford</persRef> and <persRef ref="thompson-smith">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thompson</persRef>— The instructions to be given
				upon the late act against Piracy, were mentioned again— Among the other suggestions
				that I had made to the President in relation to his design of sending an Agent or
				Commissioner of high character to South America, was one that as the compensation of
				such a person must be of considerable amount, it would be necessary to think of the
				fund from which it should be drawn; as that for the contingent expences of foreign
				intercourse, clipped down as it has been by Congress from fifty to thirty thousand
				dollars, will not be adequate to meet the expence. This morning the President said
				he had concluded not to send any Commissioner at all; but to employ the Captain of
				one of our Ships, selecting a man of intelligence and discretion, and authorize him
				to land, and transact the business, which may thus be done without attracting so
				much notice. I have recommended to the President to send a special messenger to
				Madrid, with a duplicate copy of the ratified Treaty, to be exchanged for the
				ratification of Spain, on the contingency of any accident’s happening to that taken
				out by <persRef ref="forsyth-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth</persRef>. To this the President has agreed;
					M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thompson the Secretary of the Navy, recommended
				to me <persRef ref="finch-william">Lieutenant Finch</persRef>, late Commander of the Prometheus, who has lately been put
				out of active employment by that vessel’s being condemned. He wishes for an
				opportunity of going to Europe, and would be glad to go as bearer of despatches from
				the Government. I told Thompson that as one good turn deserves another, I had to
				recommend to him the case of poor <persRef ref="barton-william">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Barton</persRef> an eminent
				botanical writer strongly recommended to me, and whom he was turning with his family
				out of their daily bread, by suppressing his Office— He said he could not help it.
				He had agreed to allow D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Barton three Months to look
				about him, and provide for himself in some other way; but the establishment in which
				Barton was placed was an expence to the public utterly useless; and it could not be
				continued— He afterwards came and introduced Lieutenant Finch to me at my Office. He
				also sent me a draft of his Instructions to the Commanders of our armed vessels, for
				the execution of the Piracy act— He had adhered so closely to the idea of directing
				them to capture only vessels having committed aggressions upon our own citizens or
				their property that he had expressly enjoined them not to capture vessels for having
				committed aggressions upon those of any other Nation— This appeared to me <pb
					type="ms" n="66"/>to be an instruction directly in the face of the Act; and I
				thought there might be many cases in which they ought to capture for aggressions,
				upon foreign vessels. I dined with <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">my wife</persRef> at <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hyde de
				Neuville’s</persRef>—a Diplomatic dinner. All the Heads of Departments and foreign Legations
				there—34 persons at table— I mentioned to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thompson my
				objection to the part of his instructions which prohibited what the Law appeared
				expressly to enjoin. He said he would alter them. I told <persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Onis</persRef>, that I had received a Letter expressing, apprehensions that the
				vouchers and documents stipulated to be delivered up, in Florida, would be carried
				away, and I should write him a Letter requesting him to give notice to the <persRef ref="cienfuegos-jose">Governor
					General of Cuba</persRef>, and to the Governors of <persRef ref="coppinger-jose">S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Augustine</persRef>,
				and <persRef ref="masot-jose">Pensacola</persRef>, of the engagement in the Treaty, with a request that they would duly
				attend to its execution—and that he would also at the same time give them notice
				that the grants were annulled by the Treaty. He said he would very readily write
				such Letters— He then added; “if the <persRef ref="casairujo-carlos">Marquis of Casa-Yrujo</persRef>, had been in your
				situation and mine, in making that Treaty—what a Fortune he would have made, by
				speculating upon those Lands! they have charged me, said he with speculating in the
				Lands, but it is not so— The Governor offered me grants of the Lands; as the
				<persRef ref="bruna-salvador">Governor of Porto-Rico</persRef> has made me the same offer, for Lands in that Island; but I
				refused them in both instances. I particularly refused the grants in Florida,
				because I was engaged in the Negotiation for the cession”— This declaration was
				spontaneously made; and was explicit and positive; but Onis has too much of the
				character ascribed by <persRef ref="pitt-william">Lord Chatham</persRef> to Spanish negotiators in general— He meant me to
				understand that he had no interest, directly or indirectly in the Florida Lands— But
				I pause in my belief— He is a man of mental reservations. Hacknied in the ways of
				Spanish diplomacy; and his working and windings, in the drawing up of the 8<hi
					rend="superscript">th.</hi> Article of the Treaty, and his subsequent allegation
				that he did not know the dates of the grants to <persRef ref="alagon-unknown">Alagon</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="punonrostro">Punon-Rustro</persRef> and 
				<persRef ref="vargas-pedro">Vargas</persRef>,
				with the qualified manner in which he admits that he signed the Treaty with the
				understanding that those grants were null and void, leave scarce a doubt in my mind,
				that he did intend by that artifice to cover the grants, while we were under the
				undoubting impression they were annulled. Now I told M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				de Neuville in conversation with him on the subject the other day, that if this was
				so, it was not the ingenious device of a public minister, but “une fourberie de
				Scapin”— De Neuville did not believe it possible. I wait to hear how the declaration
				to be delivered at the exchange of the ratifications will be received in Spain— If
				there was an intended deception on his part, I can assign no other motive for it,
				than a personal interest of his own: for he must have been aware that as a fraud
				upon the United States, it could not ultimately succeed; they having the remedy in
				their own hands— Onis’s character, is in strong contrast with that of de Neuville.
				Cold, calculating, wily, always commanding his own temper; proud because he is a
				Spaniard, but supple and cunning—accommodating the tone of his pretensions precisely
				to the degree of endurance of his opponent; bold and overbearing to the utmost
				extent at which it is tolerated; careless of what he asserts, or how grossly it is
				proved to be unfounded, his morality appears to be that of the Jesuits; as exposed
				by <persRef ref="pascal-blaise">Pascal</persRef>. In private life his character is respectable and amiable— He is
				laborious, vigilant, and ever attentive to his duties— Vain of his decorations
				rather than of his talents— A man of business and of the world; but not of much
				literature, or mental cultivation.— The <persRef ref="correa-joseph">Abbe Correa</persRef>, who had promised to call at my
				Office yesterday, sent me an excuse as being indisposed, and asked me to appoint
				another day— I had fixed this day or to-morrow— He now told me he would come
				to-morrow— After dinner I had a long conversation with <persRef ref="middleton-henry">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Middleton</persRef>, who is going in a few days to Carolina. He asked me how I
				thought <persRef key="clay-henry">Clay</persRef> had happened to let the Piracy bill pass without opposition— I said I
				did not know; unless it was that he meant to watch for its execution, and then to
				take his stand of opposition against that. He said no—but the last fortnight of the
				Session, Clay had spent almost every night at the card table—and one Night
				<persRef ref="poindexter-george">Poindexter</persRef> had won of him 8000 dollars— This discomposed him to such a degree, that
				he paid no attention to the business of the house, the remainder of the Session—
				Before it closed however he had won back from Poindexter, all that he had lost,
				except about 900 dollars. Middleton spoke also again, about Crawford’s activity in
				spreading his influence by means of appointments—and observed that the newspapers in
				Crawford’s interest had already given hints that <persRef ref="troup-george">Troup</persRef> was to be the Governor of
				Florida— He said he thought <persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General Jackson</persRef> ought to have that appointment. I asked
				him if he felt sure that the Senate would approve the appointment if he should be
				nominated. He did not know; but he hinted that it would be quite necessary for me to
				take some interest in the appointments to Office, unless Crawford was to engross
				them all. He added that he had no friends that he wished to recommend; but he did
				not think M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford’s course altogether fair— I told
				him that to be candid with him, I had been very cautious with <pb type="ms" n="67"
				/>regard to recommending any persons for appointments— The President kept it very
				much in his own hands— There had not been a single appointment of any consequence,
				even in my own Department, made at my recommendation; nor one that I approved. How
				far Crawford had been concerned in procuring them, I could not tell. Forsyth’s
				appointment, and his conduct after it, bore strong indications of Crawford’s agency,
				as his connection with the heads of the Post-Office and Land-Office, with their
				little world of patronage and personal influence, pointed clearly enough to cogent
				motives for him to employ it.— Middleton asked whether I had any communications with
				Calhoun on this subject— I said I had not— That I did not precisely know what
				Calhoun’s views were, and had not thought it necessary to scrutinize them. I had
				found in Calhoun a firm, excellent and most useful coadjutor on the South-American
				questions— But of late, in all this affair of Jackson and the Seminole War, I had
				not exactly understood what he meant, or what he was after— He said that was true—
				He had made the same observation. But he did not believe Calhoun was or would be a
				partizan of Crawford’s. He certainly was not, two years ago; and as a Southern man,
				Calhoun must have views of his own, which could not be advanced by Crawford’s
				election as President— He said he should see him, as well as some of his friends on
				his visit to Charleston; and might ascertain something more as to his dispositions—
				I said nothing further. We were talking till all the rest of the company were gone.
				It was between ten and eleven when we came home.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-19">
		<head>19 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-19"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Native Americans</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
			<note type="subject">Recreation</note>
			<note type="subject">War of 1812</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>19. VII:</dateline> <persRef ref="biddle-nicholas">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Nicholas Biddle</persRef> called
				here this Morning. He came two or three days since; to see the <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef> with whom
				he has a particular and confidential intimacy; and is about to return immediately to
				Philadelphia— Met <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford</persRef> at the President’s— He was
				taking his directions upon some reservation of Lands in the Alabama territory, for
				an Indian chief, conformably to a late Treaty; and also concerning some or all the
				Inspectors of the Revenue, at Baltimore, whom the District Attorney, <persRef ref="glenn-elias">Glenn</persRef>, charges
				with accepting presents from the merchants. Others Speak no better, of M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Glenn himself— It is generally agreed that he is
				incompetent to his Office. The Officers of the United States have been the principal
				causes, by connivance, or by some thing worse of all the piracies which for these
				three or four years have issued from that City. The only remedy yet devised is that
				in the instructions from the <persRef ref="thompson-smith">Secretary of the Navy</persRef>, the Commanders of our armed
				vessels are ordered to bring in their prizes to Ports, other than Baltimore. The
				<persRef ref="correa-joseph">Abbe Correa</persRef> came to my Office this day according to appointment, and delivered me a
				long Note, in crippled English, insisting that the Government of the United States,
				should declare all armed vessels sailing under the Commission and Flag of <persRef ref="artigas-jose">Artigas</persRef>,
				Pirates— After some Conversation with the Abbe, I endeavoured to persuade him to
				take back his notes for two reasons, one of which I did not tell him; and the other,
				I did— The first was that his Note is in such bad English, that I was afraid it
				would some day be called, and published, in which case it would cover him with
				ridicule; and the second that it asked what we could not grant, and in a manner
				which must prove injurious to himself— His main argument is that Artigas having no
				Seaport, is not competent to issue Commissions for privateers; and he says it is the
				same; as if during our late War with England, the Portuguese had fitted out
				privateers to cruize against our Citizens, and their property, under the flag and
				Commission of <persRef ref="tecumseh">Tecumseh</persRef>. The abbe declined taking back his Note, which he said
				contained not one word more than what he was expressly ordered by his Government to
				represent; and he intended me to lay it before the President; which I promised him
				that I would— At the same time I asked him if he could furnish me with any authority
				from the Laws of Nations; shewing that a power not possessing any Seaport, <hi
					rend="italic">was incompetent</hi> to issue Commissions, or to have a flag, for
				the purpose of privateering— He said he believed he could; at any rate he would
				collect and send me such as he could find— This evening I went with <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi
					rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef> in the midst of a heavy Snow-Storm, and in
				profound darkness to a dancing party at <persRef ref="tingey-thomas">Commodore Tingey’s</persRef> at the Navy Yard— There
				were a company of nearly one hundred persons; most of whom were unknown to us. <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> De Neuville</persRef> was there— I played two games of Chess
				with <persRef ref="thruston-buckner">judge Thruston</persRef>—with various success— We came home about Midnight.</p>
		</div>
	</div>
	
	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-20">
		<head>20 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-20"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
		</bibl>
		
		<div type="docbody">
			
			<p><pb type="ms" n="68"/><dateline>20. VIII:15.</dateline> Rising at such an hour, the morning was almost
				lost. I made a draught of a Letter to the <persRef ref="onis-luis">Spanish Minister Onis</persRef>, requesting him to
				write to the <persRef ref="cienfuegos-jose">Governor General of Cuba</persRef>, the <persRef ref="coppinger-jose">Governor of S<hi rend="superscript">t
				</hi>Augustine</persRef>, and the <persRef ref="masot-jose">commanding Officer at Pensacola</persRef>, informing them of the
				substance of the 8<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> Article of our Treaty, and of the
				understanding between us that under it the grants to <persRef ref="alagon-unknown">Alagon</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="punonrostro">Puñon Rostro</persRef> and 
				<persRef ref="vargas-pedro">Vargas</persRef>
				are null and void; and also giving them notice of the stipulation to deliver up the
				Documents and Archives of the Provinces; with a recommendation to them to take care
				of those papers, so that this Condition of the Treaty may be effectually performed—
				I took this draft to the President, and after making an addition to it at his
				suggestion, it was copied and sent to Onis. <persRef ref="thompson-smith">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thompson</persRef>
				the Secretary of the Navy called at the Office to press for the Instructions to be
				given to the Officer who is to go to Venezuela and Buenos-Ayres— He brought me a
				copy of his Instructions to the Commanders, for the execution of the Piracy Act—
					M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thompson is going to pass some Months at
				New-York; and is very impatient to be gone. <persRef ref="baker-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> J. M.
				Baker</persRef> and <persRef ref="forbes-john">Forbes</persRef> were also at the Office— This Evening, I went with <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">my wife</persRef> and <persRef ref="hellen-mary">Mary
					Hellen</persRef>, <persRef ref="smith-william-steuben;smith-catherine-johnson">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> W. S.
				Smith</persRef> to the Theatre, and saw Macbeth, and the Forty thieves— It was for the benefit
				of the manager—and the attraction was a <persRef ref="bartley-sarah">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Bartley</persRef>,
				lately from England, who comes here as an Actress of the first order, and has been
				giving Recitations under the Patronage of <persRef ref="bagot-mary">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Bagot</persRef>— She
				played Lady Macbeth with exemplary mediocrity. She is large and unwieldy and has the
				voice of a Cossack. All the rest of the performers were wretched— The choruses of
				the witches, and the ghost of Banquo appearing to the Spectators were novelties to
				me in this play. Though they said the music was by <persRef ref="arne-thomas">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Arne</persRef>— The house was very full, very cold and very noisy; and although we came away
				before the after piece was finished it was one in the morning when we got home— <persRef ref="lacock-abner">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Lacock</persRef> the late Senator from Pennsylvania’s reply to
				the Strictures on the Report of the Committee of the Senate against <persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General Jackson</persRef>
				was this day published in the National Intelligencer.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-21">
		<head>21 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-21"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Recreation</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>21. IX.</dateline> Another morning lost to useful occupation, in
				consequence of the loss of the preceding Evening. And this time it was the loss of
				the whole day. <persRef ref="cardelli-pietro">Cardelli</persRef> was here after breakfast. He has taken the first mould of
				the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> Bust, and is very much satisfied with his own work— He came to
				enquire if he could secure a copyright or Patent right to it. But upon examining the
				Laws, neither of them appeared to me to afford Sculpture any protection at all— He
				says there was no Law for it in England, until about the year 1810. when <persRef ref="nollekens-joseph">Nollekens</persRef>
				obtained an Act of Parliament, extending the principles of copyright property, to
				Busts and Statues. I took a walk to the Navy-yard wharf; and a distant view of the
				Line of Battle Ship in which I had been launched the first of this Month—the
				Columbus— The newspapers engrossed all the leisure of the day. <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">My wife</persRef> spent the
				Evening at her <persRef ref="frye-carolina">sister Frye’s</persRef>—and <persRef ref="forbes-john">J. M. Forbes</persRef>, great part of it with me— The
				President has determined to send a special Messenger to Madrid with a duplicate copy
				of the Treaty; and a power to <persRef ref="brent-thomas">T. L. L. Brent</persRef> to Exchange the Ratifications, in case
				neither <persRef ref="erving-george">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Erving</persRef>, nor <persRef ref="forsyth-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Forsyth</persRef> should be there— The papers are preparing, and I had determined to employ
				<persRef ref="finch-william">Lieutenant Finch</persRef>, the Officer recommended by the <persRef ref="thompson-smith">Secretary of the Navy</persRef>. But <persRef ref="purviance-john">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> John H. Purviance</persRef>, one of the Clerks in the Department
				of State, wrote me this day a Note, asking to be appointed as the Messenger himself.
				He thinks a Sea voyage, and a relaxation from the labours of the Department will be
				useful to his health, which is infirm.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-22">
		<head>22 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-22"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>22. VI:</dateline> Resumed again the task of bringing up the arrears of
				this Journal, which had been three days interrupted— At the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef>, I mentioned
				to him the desire of <persRef ref="purviance-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Purviance</persRef> to go as the Messenger
				to Madrid— Purviance had also himself applied to him for it— The President said he
				should leave it entirely to my decision— Purviance is a particular friend of the
				President’s, was his Secretary of Legation some time in London, and was left by him
				there as Charge d’Affaires when he went to Spain— His health is always feeble, and
				he has turns of melancholy sometimes to the degree of mental derangement— His
				hand-writing is remarkably beautiful, and he has a talent at translating from the
				French and Spanish Languages. But he has no activity of mind or body, and cannot
				travel out of the Record. As he is the only good translator from the Spanish, in the
				Department, and as I am in daily want of Spanish translations, I can ill spare him
				from the Office; but he says he must at all Events have a furlough for his health,
				and he is altogether so valuable an Officer, that I shall conclude to gratify him,
				by committing this charge to him. At the Office, I received a despatch from <persRef key="rush-richard">R. Rush</persRef>
				N. 50. partly in cypher, and written in a temper of mind, different from that of all
				his former communications. The general tenour of it is, that all parties in England
				are united in the Spirit of hostility to the United States. He says that personally
				he has been treated with universal kindness, excepting by the <persRef ref="george-iv">Prince Regent</persRef>, who
				shews his animosity against this Country by cautious incivilities to its
				representative—but that the hatred and envy of America is equally felt there by
				whigs and tories—Ministerialists and reformers— He also mentions the <persRef ref="wellington-arthur">Duke of
				Wellington</persRef>, lately appointed <pb type="ms" n="69"/>Master of the Ordnance and
				thereby a Cabinet Minister. he speaks of him as a man of very frivolous character,
				in which he is certainly mistaken— After decyphering the cyphered part of this
				despatch, I sent it over to the President— <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">My wife</persRef> spent the Evening at her Sister
				<persRef key="smith-catherine-johnson">Smith’s</persRef>— <persRef key="smith-william-steuben">Smith</persRef> himself is unwell.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-23">
		<head>23 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-23"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>23. VII:15.</dateline> Heavy rain all the morning— I rode to the
				<persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef>, where I met the Secretary of the Navy, <persRef ref="thompson-smith">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Thompson</persRef>; and thence I rode also to my Office. Received the answer from <persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</persRef>; to my Note of the 20<hi rend="superscript"
					>th.</hi> requesting him to write to the <persRef ref="cienfuegos-jose">Governors of Cuba</persRef>, <persRef ref="coppinger-jose">S<hi
					rend="superscript">t.</hi> Augustine</persRef> and <persRef ref="masot-jose">Pensacola</persRef>— He says he has already
				written to them according to my desire, about the vouchers, and about the grant to
				the <persRef ref="alagon-unknown">Duke of Alagon</persRef>— He still avoids naming the others in his notes, though he named
				them to <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">De Neuville</persRef>. He also calls upon me again to answer his Note about the Piracy
				Act. Received also a Note from De Neuville, with several Documents relating to the
				piratical plundering of French Vessels, by cruizers under South American Flags, but
				fitted out, armed and manned at Baltimore. <persRef ref="anderson-alexander">Alexander Anderson</persRef>, the Son of the
				Comptroller, came and brought an Application in writing, from himself for the
				Appointment of Secretary, for the Territory of Florida, when it shall be established
				by Law— <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef> again spent the Evening at <persRef key="smith-catherine-johnson">M<hi
					rend="superscript">rs</hi> W. S. Smith’s</persRef>; and <persRef ref="forbes-john">Forbes</persRef>, part of it with me.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-24">
		<head>24 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-24"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>24. VII:</dateline> Morning visit from <persRef ref="hay-george">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				George Hay</persRef>, the husband of the President’s <persRef ref="hay-eliza">eldest daughter</persRef>. He is a member of the
				Senate of Virginia; and since the adjournment of the Legislature of that
				Commonwealth, he has come from Richmond, to reside with the Ladies during the
				<persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> absence. I had received a Letter from <persRef ref="delaplaine-joseph">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Delaplaine</persRef>, requesting me to sit for my Portrait, for his Gallery, to <persRef ref="king-charles2">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> King’s</persRef> the Painter— King himself had spoken to me some
				weeks since, and told me that he expected very soon to leave the City— I called this
				morning at his rooms; but he told me he should be obliged to remain here two or
				three Months longer. He was now painting the foreign Ministers, who are all shortly
				going away. He proposes to call upon me afterwards— The Portraits that he has taken,
				are almost without exception very strong likenesses; and good Pictures. He had
				<persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General Jackson</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="parker-daniel">Gen<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> Parker</persRef>, and 
				<persRef ref="butler-robert">Col<hi rend="superscript">l</hi> Butler</persRef>— 
				<persRef ref="calhoun-john">Calhoun</persRef>, twice, 
				<persRef ref="morril-david">Morrell</persRef> of the Senate, 
				<persRef key="bagot-charles">Bagot</persRef>,
				<persRef ref="onis-luis">Onis</persRef>, 
				the <persRef ref="correa-joseph">Abbe Correa</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="graham-john">John Graham</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="forsyth-john">Forsyth</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="johnson-richard">Col<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> R. M. Johnson</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="smyth-alexander">Alex<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Smyth</persRef> of Virginia, 
				<persRef ref="rhea-john">Rhea</persRef> of Tennessee,
				and several others. There were only three or four of the whole number, that I did
				not immediately recognize at first sight— At the Office I made a draught of an
				Instruction for <persRef ref="brent-thomas">T. L. L. Brent</persRef> at Madrid; authorizing him in the case of the
				absence, both of <persRef ref="erving-george">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Erving</persRef> and M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Forsyth— <persRef ref="graham-george">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> George Graham</persRef> came, about the
				final settlement of his account, for his expedition last Summer to Galvezton; and to
				break up the magnificent settlement of the Champ d’Asyle. He told me his brother
				John had been some days confined to his chamber, in consequence of having had a
				tumour extracted from his thigh, of which he had at first scarcely thought at-all;
				but of which he is now not without alarm, finding it much more slow and irregular in
				healing than he had expected— His Secretary <persRef ref="appleton-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Appleton</persRef>
				returned this Evening from his visit to <persRef ref="appleton-john2">his father</persRef> and family at Cambridge.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-25">
		<head>25 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-25"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>25. V:30.</dateline> <persRef ref="thompson-smith">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thompson</persRef> the Secretary
				of the Navy, left the City this morning for a visit to New-York— This Office sits
				easy upon its holders— <persRef ref="crowninshield-benjamin">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crowninshield</persRef> used to remain
				at Washington only when Congress were in Session, and spent the remainder of his
				time at home. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thompson appears to be determined to
				follow the example. The <persRef ref="goldsborough-charles">Chief Clerk</persRef>, and the Navy Commissioners make the duties of
				that Department comparatively very light. Met <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Crawford</persRef> at the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef>— <persRef ref="kerr-alexander">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Kerr</persRef>, the Cashier of the
				Bank of the Metropolis came and told me there was a vacancy in their board of
				Directors, to be filled up in a few days, and asked me if I would accept it, if
				chosen. I told him that I would think of it, and give him an answer to-morrow. I had
				every disposition to serve the Stockholders, and was grateful to them for the offer
				of their confidence— But I must consider of two things before giving a definitive
				Answer. one, whether I could give the time necessary for doing justice to the
				interest of the Stockholders, and to the duties of the Office—the other whether it
				would be perfectly compatible with the duties of my public station. We had Company
				to dinner— Chiefly the Corps Diplomatique— <persRef ref="bagot-charles;bagot-mary">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and 
				M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Bagot</persRef>— 
				<persRef ref="hyde-de-neuville-jean;hyde-de-neuville-ann">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and 
				Madame Hyde de Neuville</persRef>, <pb type="ms" n="70"/>
				<persRef ref="onis-luis;onis-clementina">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and Miss de Onis</persRef>
				and <persRef ref="heredia-narcissa">Madame de Heredia</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="greuhm-frederick">Greuhm</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="goupydequabeck-alexander">Quabeck</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="antrobus-gibbs">Antrobus</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="baker-anthony">Baker</persRef>, 
				<persRef key="crawford-william-harris">Crawford</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="bourqueney-francois">Bourqueney</persRef>,
				<persRef ref="stoughton-francis">Stoughton</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="goupydebeauvolers-unknown">Beauvolers</persRef>, and 
				<persRef ref="sasse-unknown">Sasse</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="correa-joseph">Correa</persRef>, 
				<persRef ref="amadogrehon-joseph">Amado</persRef>, and 
				<persRef ref="tayloe-john;tayloe-ann">Col<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> and 
				M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Tayloe</persRef>. We were twenty two at
				table. <persRef ref="middleton-henry;middleton-mary">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> and 
					M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Middleton</persRef>, and <persRef ref="mason-john;mason-anna">General and 
				M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Mason</persRef> of Georgetown were
				invited, but did not come. It was a parting dinner to the Ministers of England,
				France and Spain, all of whom are going to Europe on leave of absence, and neither
				of whom will probably ever come back. We dined late, and the company broke up
				between nine and ten O’Clock.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-26">
		<head>26 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-26"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Bank of the United States</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Panic of 1819</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
			<note type="subject">Seminole Wars</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>26. VI:30.</dateline> I called this morning at the Bank of the Metropolis,
				and told <persRef ref="kerr-alexander">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Kerr</persRef> that upon full consideration I had come
				to the conclusion that I ought to decline accepting the office of a director of that
				Bank, chiefly for the reasons that I had suggested to him yesterday, with the
				additional consideration, that as there are several other Banks in the District, and
				as the Bank of the United States particularly is a subject of great public agitation
				at this time, there might be some impropriety in my assuming the special relation of
				a Director to one of the Banks— He was not altogether satisfied with my reasons, and
				I am not certain that they are absolutely conclusive— But in questions relative to
				delicacy of conduct, I consider the negative rule as the best—quod dubitas, <hi
					rend="italic">ne</hi> feceris. At the President’s he gave me the paper that he
				had drawn up, as the basis for instructions to be given to the Captain of one of our
				armed ships who is to go to Venezuela, and Buenos Ayres— I called at <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun’s</persRef> Office, and gave him to read the despatches
				last received from <persRef key="rush-richard">R. Rush</persRef>. They contain the account of his interview with <persRef ref="castlereagh-robert">Lord
				Castlereagh</persRef>, after he had received my despatches of 1. and 3. December, and the copy
				of my Letter to <persRef ref="erving-george">G. W. Erving</persRef> of 28. November. Lord Castlereagh told him that copies
				of the proceedings of the Court Martial on the trial of <persRef ref="arbuthnot-arthur">Arbuthnott</persRef> and <persRef ref="ambrister-robert">Armbrister</persRef>
				had been received from <persRef key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot</persRef>, and submitted to the
				consideration of the Cabinet; who considering the conduct of those two men as
				unwarrantable, had determined to make no representation to the Government of the
				United States on account of their execution.— At the same time Lord Castlereagh
				intimated that their execution, particularly that of Armbrister, after the mitigated
				sentence of the Court-Martial, was a subject of great regret to him— Calhoun is
				going to South-Carolina; and accompanies thus far the <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef>. He asked me last
				week, if any thing should during his absence occur in the Department which I could
				do for him, whether I would oblige him by attending to it; which I very readily
				promised. I asked him if <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford</persRef> had not under taken
				it when he was absent last year, he said he had— The chief Clerk, <persRef ref="vanderventer-unknown">Major Vandeventer</persRef>
				had been referred to him, as he had himself been previously at the head of the
				Department of War— But the Treasury Department not being in the same building with
				ours, the reference would be more conveniently made to me. He would ask the
				President to give me a written authority to act for him in case of necessity— This
				day he told me he had spoken to the President, who did not think it necessary that
				any special authority should be given, as it had not been usual on such occasions;
				but if Major Vandeventer should want advice upon any thing to be done in the
				Department, he would apply to me— <persRef ref="slacumb-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Slacum</persRef> brought me a
				Letter of recommendation from <persRef ref="cranch-william">judge Cranch</persRef>. He came for an answer to his application
				to be appointed Consul at Glasgow &amp; Greenock. But the President has concluded to
				make no appointment there before the next Session of Congress— The French Minister,
				<persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">Hyde de Neuville</persRef> came, and brought me a copy of his answer to my last Note
				concerning the grants, enclosed to the <persRef ref="laval-unknown">French Ambassador at Madrid</persRef>; to be carried by
					<persRef ref="purviance-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Purviance</persRef>— He enquired also upon the subject of
				his complaints, on account of the French vessels taken or plundered by the piratical
				privateers fitted out from Baltimore. Nothing decisive has been done on this
				subject— <persRef ref="forbes-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forbes</persRef> called on me to urge the appointment
				of a Consul at Copenhagen— The house of Balfour, Ellah and Rainals had applied for
				two appointments. One for John Rainals, an elderly man who resides at Copenhagen, to
				be Consul there— The other for <persRef ref="balfour-alexander">Alexander Balfour</persRef>, a young man, to be vice Consul at
				Elseneur where he resides. I had sent the names of <persRef ref="rainals-o">Rainals</persRef> to the President to be
				nominated for Copenhagen; but when the Letter of application for him came to be
				looked up, on the files; they found instead of it, only that for Balfour, and
				concluding I had made a mistake in the name sent over that of Balfour to the
				President; and he was accordingly nominated, and confirmed by the Senate— Two days
				after the close of the Session of Congress, Forbes, on applying at the Office, to
				have the Commission forwarded, discovered, and pointed out the mistake. The only
				remedy was, that the President should annul the appointment of Balfour, just made;
				send a temporary Commission to Rainals, and authorize him to appoint Balfour as Vice
				Consul at Elseneur <pb type="ms" n="71"/>all which the President directed should be
				done. This incident affords one of the numerous and unavoidable blunders that occur
				in the transaction of the public business.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-27">
		<head>27 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-27"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>27. VI:45.</dateline> At the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> this morning; I found him making
				preparations for departure upon his Southern journey, and intending to leave the
				City on Monday. <persRef ref="lewis-unknown">Commodore Lewis</persRef> was at the Office, relative to the settlement of his
				account. In June 1816. he was appointed upon a special and secret agency to
				South-America; but from a variety of delays which he now imputes to the Government,
				he never left his home for twenty Months after his appointment. <persRef key="rush-richard">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r.</hi> Rush</persRef> once wrote to him to hasten his departure; but
				without effect— When I came in to the Department he was still at home; and as other
				Commissioners were sent to South-America, it was thought his services there would
				not be necessary. Last Spring therefore his appointment was changed, and he was sent
				as Agent to Port au Prince; and a passage thither was provided for him at Hornet. He
				went, and after staying there about six Months, without asking or waiting for leave,
				came home; and has been all winter at Washington, demanding pay for two years and a
				half of Service—for six Months passed at Port au Prince. He has been one of the
				continual hangers on at the Office, during the Session of Congress. From the
				accounting Officers of the Treasury he appealed to me, and from me to the President;
				who has had all the papers before him, and after full examination of them charged me
				to inform Lewis, that he could not upon any of the principles observed for the
				settlement of accounts allow him more than a years Salary. I this day informed him
				of this decision, which he said was very distressing to him because he thought it
				affected his honour. He again insisted that it was the Government, which had
				prevented him from proceeding upon his secret agency to South America, and he made
				an argument in his favour from the fact that his draughts for Salary had been paid
				and not protested. He is not the only one, who turns the indulgence of the
				Government by advances of money, into an argument for allowances which they have no
				right to claim. Lewis finally told me he would write to the President himself, and
				hoped to obtain a revision of his decision— <persRef ref="forbes-john">Forbes</persRef> was here again, about the
				Consular Commission for <persRef ref="rainals-o">Rainals</persRef> at Copenhagen. I was much engaged in making
				preparation to despatch <persRef ref="purviance-john">Purviance</persRef>— Just as I was about leaving the Office, I
				received a Note from the <persRef ref="onis-luis">Spanish Minister Onis</persRef>, enclosing copy of a Letter, from the
				<persRef ref="ferdinand-vii">king of Spain</persRef>, to the United States of America, announcing the demise of the <persRef ref="mariaisabel">Queen</persRef>
				his consort; and requesting an Audience of the President, to deliver the Letter; as
				also to present <persRef ref="laserna-mateo">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> de la Serna</persRef>, as the Charge d’Affaires
				from Spain during his absence— I took his Note to the President, who told me, that
				he would postpone his departure till Tuesday Morning, and would receive M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis on Monday at one O’Clock, to deliver the Letter.
				According to the usual custom, he thought it would be sufficient for Onis to present
					M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> La Serna to the Secretary of State—<persRef ref="calhoun-john"> M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun</persRef> returned me the despatches from Rush, whose
				style he does not admire.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-28">
		<head>28 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-28"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Bank of the United States</note>
			<note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
			<note type="subject">Seminole Wars</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>28. VI:</dateline> I answered <persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis’s</persRef> Note;
				that the <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef> would give him an Audience, at one to-morrow, to receive <persRef ref="ferdinand-vii">the king
				of Spain’s</persRef> Letter, and that I would then agree with him upon the time when I would
				receive him to present, <persRef ref="laserna-mateo">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> de la Serna</persRef>, as Charge des
				Affaires. I paid visits to <persRef ref="hay-george">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> George Hay</persRef> at the
				President’s and to <persRef ref="graham-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John Graham</persRef> at his house to which
				he is confined. Hay told me that <persRef ref="leigh-benjamin">Watkins Leigh</persRef> was certainly the author of Algernon
				Sidney, although he had positively denied it.— He said that when he went from here
				last December to attend the Legislature of Virginia, he had read my Letter of 28
				November to <persRef ref="erving-george">G. W. Erving</persRef>— That immediately after the meeting of the Legislature,
				when those who had undertaken to make of <persRef ref="jackson-andrew">Jackson’s</persRef> Seminole War an Engine against
				the Administration, found they were getting into a minority, they immediately got up
				a plan for prevailing upon the Virginia Legislature to come forward with Resolutions
				of censure; but not a man was found, who dared to introduce them— He himself had
				from the beginning declined giving any opinion upon the subject, from the
				circumstance of his personal relation to the President; but in proportion as the
				discussion was protracted here, the current of popular opinion set so strong in
				Jackson’s favour, that towards the close of the Session of the Legislature, it was
				with difficulty that they were restrained from passing Resolutions of approbation
				upon the whole proceedings— He was glad they did not, because he thought that State
				should be peculiarly reserved, at present, upon topics connected with the
				administration of the General Government; but he was <pb type="ms" n="72"/>pleased
				to see that it had been taken up by the Legislatures of other States, and
				particularly by the House of Representatives of Pennsylvania; who have passed a vote
				of approbation upon Jackson’s proceedings by a majority of 54 to 26— M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Hay told me that he should remain with <persRef ref="hay-eliza;monroe-elizabeth">the Ladies</persRef> till
				the President’s return, but that the time of their going to Virginia was yet
				unsettled— I found M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John Graham, confined to his
				chamber, and somewhat alarmed at the slowness with which his wound is healing. He
				has misgivings that it is of a cancerous character, though his <persRef ref="cutbush-edward">Surgeon D<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Cutbush</persRef> endeavours to laugh him out of the conceit. I
				found his brother <persRef ref="graham-george">George</persRef> with him— While I was out there were several visitors at my
				own house, and among the rest, <persRef ref="hyde-de-neuville-jean;hyde-de-neuville-ann">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and Madame Hyde de
				Neuville</persRef>— I read in the National Intelligencer of yesterday, <persRef ref="lowndes-william">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Lowndes’s</persRef> powerful characteristic Speech on the Bank question.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-29">
		<head>29 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-29"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Press</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
			<note type="subject">South American Wars of Independence</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>29. VII:</dateline> At the President’s House, I met the <persRef ref="onis-luis">Spanish Minister de
				Onis</persRef>, at precisely one O’Clock, and presented him to the <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef>. He delivered the
				Letter from the <persRef ref="ferdinand-vii">king of Spain</persRef>, and after less than five minutes of conversation we
				withdrew. At these Audiences the President observes the usual forms practiced by
				European Sovereigns on similar occasions— That is he receives them standing, dressed
				in half military uniform, or a full suit of black. The Ministers are in full Court
				dresses— He stands in the centre of the Drawing room, and I accompany them keeping
				the right hand. On receiving the Letter the President hands it unopened to me— The
				<persRef ref="george-iv">English Prince Regent</persRef> had the same practice with <persRef ref="castlereagh-robert">Lord Castlereagh</persRef>— All the other
				Sovereigns to whom I have delivered Letters, opened and cast a cursory glance over
				them—The king of England, the Stadtholder of the Netherlands, the President of the
				States General, the King of Prussia, and the Emperor of Russia. The President has a
				general answer to the short addresses which the Ministers make in delivering these
				Letters—namely that the United States take a great interest in every thing that
				concerns the happiness of their Sovereign, with very little variation adopted to
				each particular case. He makes no other Conversation; and of the Ministers, the <persRef ref="correa-joseph">Abbe
				Correa</persRef> is the only one who makes it on his part by starting topics, for which he has
				a peculiar talent— He immediately after the office of etiquette is performed doffs
				the diplomat aside, and opens a discursive field of Conversation, upon which the
				President then readily enters. None of the others have the faculty or the
				inclination for this, and their interviews are merely formal and dull— After
				withdrawing from the President into the anti-chamber, I agreed with Onis to receive
				him, and <persRef ref="laserna-mateo">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> de la Serna</persRef>, at the Department Office
				to-morrow, at 2. O’Clock. Onis told me that two or three days since he had seen a
					<persRef ref="garrido-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Garrido</persRef>, the Agent of the <persRef ref="alagon-unknown">Duke of Alagon</persRef>, who had
				just come from S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Augustine, where he had been put in
				possession for the Duke, by <persRef ref="coppinger-jose">the Governor</persRef>, and passed through here, being on his
				return to Spain— I asked Onis if he had told Garrido that the Duke’s grant was
				annulled by the Treaty? He answered that he had; and had told him that the Duke must
				obtain an equivalent elsewhere. There was plenty of Land in the Province of Texas— I
				asked him if he knew whether Garrido had sold any part of the Duke’s grant. He said,
				not a foot. Garrido told him that the Duke’s grant was dated the 17<hi
					rend="superscript">th.</hi> of December 1817. That those to <persRef ref="punonrostro">Puñon Rostro</persRef> and
				<persRef ref="vargas-pedro">Vargas</persRef> were subsequent to the 24<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> of January 1818.
				That of the grants of Lands in Florida before the Duke’s there were only about one
				million eight hundred thousand acres of English grants, and 480,000 less than half a
				million of Spanish grants— That the Duke’s grant was of about seven Millions— I
				asked Onis if he had not seen a copy of any of the grants; he said he had not, and
				that he had not known what the date of either of them was— And he repeated that La
				Serna had never had anything to do with the business; and intimated that it was a
				transaction in which no honourable men would have taken a part. I told Onis that I
				should perhaps ask of him a Passport for a person to go to S<hi rend="superscript"
					>t.</hi> Augustine; which he said he would very readily give. <persRef ref="forrest-richard">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Richard Forrest</persRef>, one of the Clerks in the Department
				wishes to go there upon his private concerns; to look up a man for whom he was
				security, and obliged to pay the money, and who he hears is gone there; and to
				examine the place to ascertain whether it would be advisable for one of <persRef ref="forrest-unknown">his Sons</persRef> to
				go, and settle there— It occurred to me that it would be advisable to send some
				person to S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Augustine, to obtain such information
				there, particularly in relation to the grants, and the documents to be delivered up
				as may hereafter prove useful. I mentioned it to the President, and asked him if
				some one of the Officers who were with <persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General Jackson</persRef> in his late campaign might
				not be employed in this service— He directed me to consult upon it with <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun</persRef>; but Calhoun thought an officer could not be
				sent, unless with a party of troops, and for a purpose of making a topographical
				survey, which it was not probable the Governor or Onis would or could authorize—
					M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forrest may perhaps still be employed for the
				service— After Onis went away I returned to the President in his Cabinet, and found
					M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun with him. <pb type="ms" n="73"/>He said
				as he was going to-morrow Morning, he wished to have a Meeting of the Members of the
				Administration immediately, to determine what should be done, with the Article,
				suspended for reference to this Government, at the Negotiation of the Commercial
				Convention with Great-Britain, by Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> <persRef ref="gallatin-albert">Gallatin</persRef> and
				<persRef key="rush-richard">Rush</persRef> last October. <persRef ref="king-rufus">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> King</persRef> had been averse to accepting
				the Article, and indeed to doing any thing further in the business at present. <persRef ref="otis-harrison">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Otis</persRef> had been very anxious that the article should be
				accepted, or at least that attempts should be made to obtain such a modification of
				it, as would make it acceptable— He has written me a long Letter from New-Haven, on
				his way home from Congress; urging the affair again; and some days since I laid the
				Letter before the President— I now went over to the Office, and brought to the
				Presidents all the papers relating to the Negotiation, with the Resolution of the
				Senate, referring a Report of their Committee upon the suspended Article, and the
				subject generally to the Secretary of State— The Article, or rather Articles, for
				there are two—one relating to the Commerce of the U.S. with the West Indies, and the
				other to their intercourse with the North-American Colonies; these Articles as
				presented by the British Plenipotentiaries would have the effect of leaving the
				whole intercourse at the discretion of the British Government— We examined and
				discussed them until we became unanimously convinced to this; and consequently that
				we ought not to accept the British project, without considerable modifications—what
				these should be, we had not time to determine. <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Crawford</persRef> made several proposals; which upon examination he thought himself would not
				be safe or effectual on our part. Finally the President desired him, and <persRef ref="wirt-william">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Wirt</persRef> to meet with me again, to come to some
				conclusion, with which he declared he should be satisfied and directed me to
				instruct M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Rush accordingly. It was about half past
				four when the meeting adjourned, and I returned to my Office to open the Letters by
				the Mail— The French Minister <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">Hyde de Neuville</persRef>, immediately afterwards came in, and
				told me that he had received despatches from the new French Minister of foreign
				Affairs the <persRef ref="dessolles-jean">Marquis Dessolles</persRef>; instructing him to make new and urgent
				representations on two subjects—one of them was the piratical depredations committed
				by armed vessels, fitted out in the United States, and especially at the Port of
				Baltimore; and sailing under the South-American flags— The other was the desertion
				of Seamen from French Vessels in the Ports of the United States, upon which he has
				made many and earnest remonstrances before— As to the piratical privateers he read
				me a passage from the Marquis Dessolles’s despatch, stating that the Government of
				Portugal had presented to the Congress at Aix La Chapelle a Memorial, complaining in
				the most energetic manner against these Baltimore privateers, and also against the
				Governor of the Swedish Island of S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Bartholomews, for
				shelter, harbour and encouragement afforded to those same pirates— It further stated
				that the Sovereigns after entering up on the protocol of their conferences a
				declaration of their displeasure and indignation at these practices, and agreed that
				amicable expostulations concerning it should be made to the Swedish Government, and
				by the Powers who had Ministers at Washington, to that of the United States. He also
				read me the answer which had been received from Sweden, which was very full of
				compliments and professions, and promises to punish the <persRef ref="berghult-carl">Governor of S<hi
					rend="superscript">t.</hi> Bartholomews</persRef>. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> De
				Neuville told me that he had a copy of the Memorial from the Court of Portugal to
				the Congress, which was exceedingly energetic— I asked him if he could not shew it
				to me; and he promised that he would— I told him that as to those piratical
				privateers, we had them in as great abhorrence as the Congress could have— Our own
				Commerce suffered from them nearly as much as that of any other Nation— But it was
				very notorious that they were fitted out from the Ports of other Nations as well as
				from ours; and besides the repeated Laws which had before been enacted in the United
				States against that description of persons, the Act of the last Session of Congress
				would shew the continued solicitude of this Government for the suppression of such
				Offences— De Neuville asked me, if <persRef key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot</persRef> had made any
				representation here, conformably to the entry on the Protocol at the Congress— I
				said none. He then intimated very broadly that Great-Britain had no real aversion to
				these Piracies— That she agreed with the rest pro forma at the Congress; but gave
				herself no further trouble concerning it afterwards. <pb type="ms" n="74"/>As to the
				desertion of French Sailors, his Government were the more anxious on that subject,
				because even now, by the French Laws, American Merchants and Masters of Vessels
				enjoyed there the advantage of having all deserting Seamen delivered up to them— He
				was instructed to say that if any obstacle to the establishment of the like
				principle here, arose from a doubt with regard to the certainty of enjoying the
				reciprocal benefit in France, he was ready to enter into a formal Convention to that
				effect. I asked him if he had a full-power. He said he had one for that purpose— I
				told him I would immediately submit the question to the President, and give him an
				answer as soon as possible; and in the meantime asked him to draw up, and send to me
				the form of an Article, such he would wish to have adopted; which he promised— I
				then called again the third time, this day at the President’s, and told him the
				Conversation I had just had with De Neuville. He said as to the Representation
				against the Baltimore privateers it was what he had been for some time expecting.
				One of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gallatin’s late despatches had given notice
				that such remonstrances would be made, and he directed me to write to <persRef ref="glenn-elias">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Glenn</persRef> the District Attorney at Baltimore, and urge him
				to take suitable measures for suppressing this enormous scandal— But this direction
				was general. The misfortune is not only that this abomination has spread over a
				large portion of the merchants, and of the population of Baltimore, but that it has
				infected almost every Officer of the United States in the place. They are all
				fanatics of the South-American cause— <persRef ref="skinner-john">Skinner</persRef> the Post-master has been indicted for
				being concerned in the piratical privateers— Glenn the District Attorney, besides
				being a weak incompetent man, has <persRef ref="glenn-unknown">a son</persRef> said to be concerned in the privateers.
				<persRef ref="mcculloch-james">M’Culloh</persRef> the collector, Crawford says is a very honest man, but only an enthusiast
				for the South-Americans, and easily duped by knaves because he thinks all other men
				as honest as himself— Not long since Glenn wrote to Crawford, that he had been
				informed, all the Inspectors of the Revenue at Baltimore, were in the habit of
				receiving <hi rend="italic">Presents</hi>, from the importing Merchants; and that
				Crawford said accounted for another fact; namely that there never was any detection
				of Smugglers at Baltimore— So Crawford wrote very indignant Letters both to the
				Collector and the District Attorney, directing them to take every measure according
				to the duties and powers of their respective Offices to bring these offenders to
				punishment— But Glenn replied that on pressing the persons who had given the
				information, they were unwilling to testify publicly to the facts, and M’Culloh
				answered that all the Inspectors were perfectly honest men, and faithful Servants of
				the public; and there the matter drops— The District <persRef ref="houston-james">Judge Houstoun</persRef>, and the Circuit
				<persRef ref="duval-gabriel">Judge Duval</persRef> are both feeble inefficient men, over whom <persRef ref="pinkney-william">William Pinkney</persRef>, employed by
				all the Pirates as their Counsel domineers like a Slave-driver over his negroes—
				After the pirates were indicted last September, and before they were tried, a piece
				was published in the National Intelligencer, threatening that any judge who should
				condemn them could not be expected to live long either as a judge or as a man. The
				paper containing this piece was sent under a blank cover to judge Houstoun just
				before he opened his Court— He read the paragraph in open Court, blustered about his
				Independence; and how impossible it was to intimidate <hi rend="italic">him</hi>;
				and then as well as judge Duval, Wirt says, was perfectly subservient to whatever
				Pinkney chose to dictate— <persRef ref="middleton-henry">Middleton</persRef> told me that he saw that threatening piece, in
				the hand-writing of Skinner the Post master, one of the parties indicted. When
				trials came on, Glenn wrote to me, asking to be assisted in the management of the
				Causes— I prevailed upon the President to direct the Attorney General Wirt to assist
				him; but Wirt considered it as extra-official, and made the public pay him fifteen
				hundred dollars for losing the Causes— The Grand Jury indicted many; and the petit
				Jury convicted one man; but every one of the Causes fell through upon flaws in
				Glenn’s bills of indictment— The conduct of the Juries, proves the real soundness of
				the public mind— The Soldiers are good men and true— But the Officers! the
				Commanders! what with want of honesty in some and want of energy in others the
				political condition of Baltimore is as rotten as corruption can make it. Now that it
				has brought the whole body of the European allies upon us in the form of
				remonstrance, the President is somewhat concerned about it; but he had nothing but
				directions altogether general to give me concerning it— I must take the brunt of the
				Battle upon myself, and rely upon the Justice of the Cause. As to De Neuville’s
				proposal to conclude a Convention upon the single point of Seamen deserting from
				their vessels, the President directed me immediately and positively to decline it.
				He said there were many objects all of the far more important to be adjusted in our
				commercial relations with France, and the people of this Country, would be very much
				dissatisfied, if we should go through the formality of making a Treaty upon that
				alone, agreeing to an arrangement, the whole benefit of which would be on the side
				of France, and leaving every thing else <pb type="ms" n="75"/>unsettled. The great
				object of his concern now he added, would be the carrying into Execution of the new
				Treaty with Spain. He expected its operation would be to strengthen the
				administration at home, and to increase the consideration of the Country abroad. It
				would enable us to give the direction to the public sentiment with regard to
				South-American affairs, and to keep our own policy under our own controul— I told
				him I should have no difficulty in giving a satisfactory answer to M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> de Neuville— I took leave of the President, and it was
				past seven O’Clock when I came home to dinner.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-30">
		<head>30 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-30"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Press</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>30. VI:</dateline> The President left the City this morning in the
				Steam-boat, for Norfolk. <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun</persRef> the Secretary at
				War, and his family go with him, and his nephew, <persRef ref="gouverneur-samuel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Gouverneur</persRef>, as his private Secretary— They had a stormy day; it blew a very heavy
				gale, and in the afternoon there was a gust of thunder and lightening, like the most
				violent of those which happen in the Summer. <persRef ref="purviance-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Purviance</persRef> likewise departed this morning for Philadelphia; going as a special
				messenger to Madrid, with a duplicate of the ratified Treaty with Spain; and a power
				to <persRef ref="brent-thomas">T. L. L. Brent</persRef>, to exchange the Ratifications, if neither <persRef ref="erving-george">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Erving</persRef> nor <persRef ref="forsyth-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth</persRef> should be at Madrid,
				when Purviance arrives. This measure was suggested not only by the consideration of
				the accidents which may happen to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth, but by
				accounts in the Newspapers, from France that M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Erving
				had left Spain, and was gone to Montpelier for his health— <persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Onis</persRef> came at two O’Clock, and presented <persRef ref="laserna-mateo">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				de la Serna</persRef> to me, as the Charge d’Affaires of Spain during his absence. <persRef ref="forbes-john">Forbes</persRef>
				spent the Evening with us— <persRef ref="weems-unknown3">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Weems</persRef>, widow of the late
					<persRef ref="weems-unknown">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Weems</persRef>, the physician who formerly attended my
				family, here, called this morning at my house to recommend to me <persRef ref="weems-unknown2">her eldest Son</persRef>, for
				an appointment as a Clerk, in any of the public offices. I received two days ago a
				letter from <persRef ref="brown-katherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Catherine Brown</persRef>, recommending her <persRef ref="brown-unknown2">Son</persRef>
				the same way.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-31">
		<head>31 March 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-31"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
			<note type="subject">Seminole Wars</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>31. VI:</dateline> I called this morning at <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Crawford’s</persRef> office to enquire after a list of grants in West Florida, which he had at
				the President’s one day, when the Spanish Treaty was in discussion; and from which I
				suppose some useful information may be collected. He promised to send it to me— I
				next stopped at <persRef ref="wirt-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wirt’s</persRef> office to make some enquiries
				for <persRef ref="duponceau-peter">Duponceau’s</persRef> translation of one of <persRef ref="bynkershoek-cornelius">Bynkershoek’s</persRef> Treatises on public Law; which
				he lent me— They both met at my Office at one O’Clock, when we took into
				consideration the Articles suspended at the Negotiation of the Convention with Great
				Britain— We examined the Article, proposed by our own Plenipotentiaries— That
				finally offered on the British side— The entries concerning them on the Protocols—
				The Comments upon them of <persRef ref="gallatin-albert">Gallatin</persRef> and <persRef key="rush-richard">Rush</persRef>— The Report of the Committee of the
				Senate, and Otis’s Letter to me from New-Haven— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Gallatin had sent us a statement of the exports and imports of our trade with the
				British West-India Islands in the years 1802. 3. and 4. which was of importance in
				coming to a result. We discussed the whole subject, without the slightest diversity
				of views extraneous to the subject; certainly the most comfortable; perhaps the most
				useful, but not the most ordinary mode of discussing political questions— There are
				two objections to the British project of the two Articles—one the restricted list of
				Articles both of export and import, to which they wish to limit the trade, and the
				other the right which they insist upon reserving to lay heavier duties, upon the
				same Articles, imported directly from the United States into the West-Indies, than
				when imported indirectly through New-Brunswick and Nova-Scotia. M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford started the question whether we could not
				propose a certain limit to the excess of duties which they should be allowed to lay
				on the direct over the indirect importations; but it appeared such a proposal had
				been offered by our Plenipotentiaries, and rejected. We also found upon examination
				that the practicability of carrying such a discrimination would be very doubtful— We
				agreed to meet again in two or three days; and M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Crawford promised to have prepared in the meantime statements of the existing trade
				with the West-Indies in 1816. 17. and 18. similar to those of M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Gallatin for the earlier period— We parted between
				three and four O’Clock, and I soon afterwards came home— I have been several days
				unwell with a severe cold, which within the last two days has fallen upon my eyes—
				This Evening as well as the last, I have been unable either to write or to read; and
				<persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">my wife</persRef> read to me, <persRef ref="poindexter-george">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Poindexter’s</persRef> Speech on the
				Seminole War question; one of the most solid and brilliant of those that were
				delivered on either side of that debate. It is most distressing and unseasonable
				time for me to be deprived of the use of my eyes, and I can <pb type="ms" n="76"
				/>only hope that it will teach me a lesson of Patience and Resignation— It
				necessarily delays the accomplishment of my task, of retrieving the arrears of this
				Journal.</p>
			
		</div>
	</div>
	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-03-xx">
		<head>Day</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-03-xx"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
		</bibl>
		
		<div type="docbody">
			<!-- This is a summary entry without a date.-->
			
			
			<p><dateline rend="italic">Day.</dateline> I have seldom risen this month earlier than six O’Clock,
				and not usually later than seven— After making my fire, reading or assorting my
				newspapers often occupies two hours; or if not that or something equally
				insignificant, I write in this Journal till nine or ten— Breakfast, usually with
				<persRef ref="hellen-mary">Mary Hellen</persRef>. Write again till twelve or one. Called at the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> for an hour
				or more, till he went away— since then I go directly to the Office— Trifle with
				business or receive visitors till two— Then comes the Mail— Despatches Letters and
				Newspapers— It takes me generally till five, and often till near six to open the
				Letters and read them— I then return home to dinner, usually from six to seven— Then
				two hours of reading newspapers, and two hours writing of diary bring the day to its
				close, between eleven and twelve at Night. I take my glass of cold water—cover up my
				coal fire for the morning and have the coal scuttle brought in full to be ready to
				make the fire on the morrow. Dinner’s and Evening parties have subsided. My journal
				which had been necessarily suspended for a month before the 11<hi rend="superscript"
					>th.</hi> of this, when I resumed it and have since been assiduously redeeming
				the time.</p>
		</div>
	</div>
</div>
