<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.masshist.org/publications/pub/schema/djqa-prep-2016.rng" type="xml"?>
        <?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="DJQA-authorViewMaybe.css"?>
<div type="month" volume="30" startingOnPage="291">
    <bibl n="metadata">
        <date from="1818-01-01" to="1818-01-31"/>
    </bibl>
    <!--D/JQA/30.1329 -->
    <!--January 1818 -->
    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-01">
        <head>1 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-01"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">
            <dateline type="heading">January 1818.</dateline>
            <p><dateline>1. V:</dateline> Thursday— Began the year by bringing up my Journal to the
                close of the last. At half past eleven O’Clock I went with my <persRef
                    key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef> to the President’s House, which was
                first opened since its rebuilding, this day— The foreign Ministers were received
                together, the heads of Departments being all present, and in a separate room. The
                Ladies were in the other with <persRef ref="monroe-elizabeth">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Monroe</persRef>. I presented <persRef
                    ref="tencate-j">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> ten Cate</persRef> as Chargé
                d’Affaires from the Netherlands to the <persRef key="monroe-james"
                    >President</persRef>— At Noon commenced the tide of general company, which
                crowded all the Apartments till 3. My wife went out between twelve and one, and
                brought her sister, <persRef ref="hellen-adelaide">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                    Hellen</persRef> with her. Soon after two I went to my Office, where I was
                engaged with voluminous despatches from the Mediterranean brought by the frigate
                Constellation, till five; when my wife called for me, and I rode home. In the
                Evening, and until 11. I was writing remarks for <persRef ref="middleton-henry">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> Middleton’s</persRef> draft of a report to the
                House of Representatives upon Amelia-Island. He sent it to me yesterday with a
                private Note requesting my observations upon it— I commenced this morning a series
                of observations of the Thermometer— We discovered that <persRef ref="adams-charles2"
                    >Charles’s</persRef> watch, <persRef ref="quinzard-unknown">Quinzard’s</persRef> legacy has been stolen from our
                bed-chamber; probably by <persRef ref="neufer-christine">Christine</persRef> when
                she ran away.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-02">
        <head>2 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-02"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>2. VII:</dateline> Finished the draft of Remarks upon <persRef
                    ref="middleton-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Middleton’s</persRef>
                Report, which engaged the Morning hours— As I was going to the <persRef
                    key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> I met <persRef ref="mason-jonathan">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> Jon<hi rend="superscript">n:</hi> Mason</persRef>,
                who told me he should introduce <persRef ref="ripley-eleazer">General
                    Ripley</persRef> to me, and he afterwards came with him and <persRef
                    ref="nicholas-unknown">Lieutenant</persRef><space>     </space>his Aide de Camp to the Office.
                At the President’s; but I had not time myself to read all the despatches yesterday
                received; and still less has he the time to read them— Instead of taking his
                directions upon almost every thing done at the department, it will be indispensable
                for me to do much of the minor business, and prepare much of the other, without
                putting him to the trouble of reading the papers relating to it— This was again a
                fine and moderate day; and my <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef>
                received new year’s visits from all the Corps Diplomatique— In the Evening I was
                writing answers to members of the House of Representatives, and Chairmen of
                Committees.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-03">
        <head>3 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-03"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
            <note type="subject">Recreation</note>
            <note type="subject">Slave Trade</note>
            <note type="subject">Slavery</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>3. VI:30.</dateline> <persRef ref="shaler-william">Shaler’s</persRef> Letters, and a complaint of
                    <persRef ref="fitch-a">A. Fitch</persRef> at Marseilles against <persRef
                    ref="cathalan-stephen">S. Cathalan</persRef>, the Consul there employed all the
                morning to read. At the <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef>, I mentioned
                to him again the proposal for the fisheries to be proposed to <persRef
                    key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot</persRef>— After some
                conversation upon the subject he directed me to ask <persRef
                    ref="crowninshield-benjamin">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    Crowninshield</persRef>, <persRef ref="holmes-john">M<hi rend="superscript"
                        >r</hi> Holmes</persRef>, <persRef ref="silsbee-nathaniel">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> Silsbee</persRef>, <persRef ref="nelson-jeremiah"
                        >M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Nelson</persRef>, and all the members from
                Massachusetts, representing districts, interested in the fisheries, to call at his
                house at eleven O’Clock, Monday Morning, for a consultation upon the proposal to be
                made— The President also asked my opinion concerning his entertainments to be given
                to the Heads of Departments, and the foreign Ministers; whether they should be given
                together or separately; I advised that it should be separately, which was apparently
                his own inclination. He determined to give both dinners next week. The first on
                Wednesday and the other on Friday— <persRef ref="middleton-henry">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> Middleton</persRef> came to the office and I gave
                him the notes I had made upon his draft of a Report— But he now inclines to make the
                Report much shorter than he had intended, and to confine it altogether to the
                illicit introduction of Slaves into the United States— M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Silsbee likewise came, and enquired concerning his claim upon the money
                recovered from the <persRef ref="omar-bashaw">Dey</persRef> of Algiers by <persRef
                    ref="decatur-stephen">Decatur’s</persRef> Treaty. As there are several
                claimants, and to an amount much larger than the sum recovered, I doubted the
                competency of the Secretary of State to distribute the money among them. <persRef
                    ref="gray-william2">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> W. Gray</persRef> has a
                claim for the proceeds of a specific article, some cotton, which was taken at the
                commencement of the War; restored at the Peace and afterwards sold. <persRef
                    key="rush-richard">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Rush</persRef> as Attorney
                General gave two Opinions, pro and con upon this question; which yet remains
                unsettled. I came home early, and went with my <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine"
                    >wife</persRef> and dined at the French Minister, <persRef
                    key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hyde de
                        Neuville’s</persRef>. <persRef ref="crawford-william-harris;crawford-susanna">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi
                        rend="superscript">rs</hi> Crawford</persRef>, M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> and <persRef ref="crowninshield-mary">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                    Crowninshield</persRef>, <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi rend="superscript"
                        >r</hi> Calhoun</persRef>, <persRef ref="porter-david">Commodore
                            Porter</persRef>, and <persRef ref="jones-w2">Captain W. Jones</persRef>, <persRef
                                ref="cutts-richard;cutts-anna">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Cutts</persRef>, and <persRef
                                    ref="smith-w">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> W. Smith</persRef> were there. In the
                Evening there was a large Company, Ladies and Gentlemen; Music and dancing—Waltzes,
                Quadrille’s and Country dances—Cards and Chess— The Morning was very moderate with
                rain; and in the Evening cleared away, Cold.</p>
        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-04">
        <head>4 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-04"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Religion</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">
            <p><pb type="ms" n="292"/><dateline>4. VII:</dateline> <persRef ref="brent-daniel">D. Brent</persRef> was
                here this Morning— I went with my <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine"
                    >wife</persRef> and <persRef ref="hellen-mary">Mary Hellen</persRef> to the
                Capitol and attended public worship— <persRef ref="allison-burgess">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> Allison</persRef> was the preacher—without Notes,
                and very indifferent— After Church I paid several visits— Saw <persRef
                    ref="smith-samuel2">General S. Smith</persRef> of Baltimore and <persRef
                    ref="stgeorgetucker-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> H. S<hi
                        rend="superscript">t.</hi> George Tucker</persRef>— I had much conversation
                upon commercial concerns, with Gen<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> Smith— I afterwards
                paid a visit to <persRef ref="ripley-eleazer">Gen<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi>
                    Ripley</persRef> at Heronimus’s, &amp; after dinner I called to see <persRef
                    ref="mason-jonathan">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Mason</persRef>, but after
                waiting an hour at his chamber found he was not at home. I wrote him a Note
                requesting him to attend the fishery conference at the <persRef key="monroe-james"
                    >President’s</persRef> at eleven O’Clock to-morrow. I had asked <persRef
                    ref="holmes-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Holmes</persRef>, at the
                capitol, and <persRef ref="crowninshield-benjamin">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    Crowninshield</persRef> yesterday after dinner. Weather clear, and moderately
                cold.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-05">
        <head>5 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-05"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
            <note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>            
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>5. VII:</dateline> My <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef>
                who for some days has been troubled with a bad cold and cough, was bled this morning
                by <persRef ref="huntt-henry">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Hunt</persRef>.
                    <persRef ref="cardelli-pietro">Cardelli</persRef> was here, and told me of the
                arrival of <persRef ref="bulfinch-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> C.
                    Bulfinch</persRef>, the Architect of the Capitol. At eleven O’Clock, I called at
                the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef>, where I found <persRef
                    ref="crowninshield-benjamin">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    Crowninshield</persRef>, and nine or ten of the Members of the House of
                Representatives from the Districts of Massachusetts interested in the fisheries,
                consulting upon the subject of the proposal to be made to the British Government—
                After examining the map, and some Conversation several of the Members asked for time
                to write to their districts for information, and I undertook to reconcile <persRef
                    key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot</persRef> to wait until
                the February Packet for the proposal. Crowninshield had received despatches with
                information of the surrender to us of Amelia-Island, on the 23<hi rend="superscript"
                    >d.</hi> of last Month. <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi rend="superscript"
                        >r</hi> Calhoun</persRef> afterwards came in with the same despatches, and
                the President appointed a Cabinet Meeting for eleven O’Clock to-morrow Morning, to
                determine what should be done with Amelia-Island. At the Office I had visits from
                    <persRef ref="gaillard-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gaillard</persRef>
                the President pro Tempore of the Senate, and his Colleague <persRef
                    ref="smith-william2">Judge Smith</persRef>; and had conversation with them on
                various topics. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gaillard, finally asked me, if there
                had been any new System of Etiquette established with regard to visiting; to which I
                answered, certainly none to my knowledge— I was myself determined to make no
                question of etiquette with any one— But I had been negligent in paying visits from
                absolute want of time— They said there had been a rule adopted by the Senators so
                long ago as when <persRef ref="burr-aaron">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    Burr</persRef> was a member of the body, and drawn by him, that the Senators
                should visit only the President of the United States—and <persRef ref="king-rufus"
                        >M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> King</persRef> had lately referred them to a
                Book, in which it was recorded— I told them this was the first intimation I had ever
                received of the existence of such a rule— I had been five years a member of the
                Senate, and at the commencement of every Session had invariably paid the first visit
                to all the heads of Departments, excepting <persRef ref="gallatin-albert">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> Gallatin</persRef>, who never having returned my
                first visit, I never afterwards visited him, except upon business at his Office; and
                I understood he had neither paid, nor returned any visits, while he was Secretary of
                the Treasury— I had always supposed the universal practice to be that the Senators
                paid the first visit to the heads of Departments, though since I had now arrived
                here, I had heard the practice was different— I was ready to conform to any
                arrangement that might be proper, but I supposed the rule that Senators would visit
                only the President, did not extend to a requisition that the heads of Departments
                should first visit them— We parted in perfect good humour on the subject— I met M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r.</hi> Bulfinch and his <persRef ref="bulfinch-thomas"
                    >Son</persRef>, as I was going to the President’s, and they afterwards called
                upon me at the Office— <persRef ref="cranch-william">Judge Cranch</persRef> spent
                the Evening with us.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-06">
        <head>6 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-06"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Adams Family Finances</note>
            <note type="subject">Bank of the United States</note>
            <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
            <note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>6. VII:</dateline> I wrote the Answer to <persRef ref="lowndes-william">W.
                    Lowndes</persRef>, Chairman of the Committee of Ways and Means, to a Letter from
                him asking explanations concerning the Estimates. Attended at eleven O’Clock the
                Cabinet Meeting at the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> concerning
                Amelia-Island— <persRef ref="macgregor-gregor">M’Gregor’s</persRef> proclamation,
                upon taking the Island being wanted, I went for it to the Office and there was met
                by <persRef ref="rhea-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Rhea</persRef> of
                Tennessee, with papers of <persRef ref="kingston-stephen">Stephen
                Kingston</persRef>— Claims on Spain, France the Netherlands &amp;c— I could not then
                read the Papers— There were a multitude of Letters and despatches from Europe and
                the first that I opened was one from <persRef ref="smith-john">J. A.
                Smith</persRef>, of 6. November with the Official Notification from <persRef
                    ref="bathurst-henry">Earl Bathurst</persRef> of the death of the <persRef
                    ref="charlotte-augustus">Princess Charlotte</persRef> that morning, in
                child-birth, having been delivered of a still-born male child. I returned to the
                Cabinet Meeting at the President, which was fully attended— The President had partly
                drawn up a Message to Congress stating the taking of Amelia-Island, and concluding
                that the troops, which took it would be withdrawn— It seems that when the Orders for
                taking the Island were sent; those from the War Department directed that the persons
                to be expelled, should not carry away any public Spanish property taken by them upon
                the Island— Those Orders I never saw; the President says he has no doubt they were
                shewn to, and authorised by him, but now comes the embarrassment what to do with
                that property consisting of two or four Cannon. The President is apparently
                determined, to withdraw the troops from the Island, but he asks the opinions of the
                Cabinet, to take the measure with deliberation. <persRef
                    key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford</persRef>,
                    <persRef ref="crowninshield-benjamin">Crowninshield</persRef> and <persRef
                    ref="wirt-william">Wirt</persRef> are with the President, for withdrawing the
                    troops—<persRef ref="calhoun-john">Calhoun</persRef> and myself are for keeping
                possession of the Island, subject to negotiation <pb type="ms" n="293"/>for it with
                Spain— If I understand the character of my Colleagues, Crawford’s point d’honneur is
                to differ from me, and to find no weight in any reason assigned by me—. Wirt and
                Crowninshield will always be of the President’s opinion— Calhoun thinks for himself,
                independently of all the rest, with sound judgment, quick discrimination and keen
                observation. He supports his opinions too with powerful eloquence— The discussion of
                this day was adjourned, for the President to finish preparing his draft of the
                Message to Congress— On returning to my Office I had a second visit from M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Rhea of Tennessee, but had not had time to read M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                Kingston’s papers. Rhea is to call upon me again to-morrow— Left the Office at five.
                    <persRef key="smith-catherine-johnson">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> W. S.
                    Smith</persRef> dined with us. I was the whole Evening reading without getting
                nearly through the despatches and Letters received this Morning. I left a Card at
                    <persRef ref="talbot-isham">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Talbot’s</persRef>,
                Senator from Kentucky— Called also at the Branch Bank, and received my book,
                balanced.</p>
        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-07">
        <head>7 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-07"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">U.S. Constitution</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">
            <p><dateline>VII: 6:30.</dateline> <persRef ref="rhea-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Rhea</persRef>
                of Tennessee came to the Office for <persRef ref="kingston-stephen">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> Kingston’s</persRef> papers, which I had read, but
                concerning which claims upon France, Spain, England, Holland, &amp;c. I could say
                nothing definitive. <persRef ref="sanford-nathan">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    Sanford</persRef> came also to make enquiries concerning the Journal of the
                Convention which made the Constitution of the United States. He has made a motion in
                the Senate, that it should be published under the direction of the Secretary of
                State, and he wished to know whether there are any papers of the Convention here
                besides the Journal; but there are none. Dined with my <persRef
                    key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef> at the <persRef key="monroe-james"
                    >President’s</persRef>— The first public dinner given since the opening of the
                House to the Heads of Departments and their Ladies. <persRef
                    ref="crawford-william-harris;crawford-susanna">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and
                    M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                    Crawford</persRef> were not there, having company at home. <persRef
                    ref="gaillard-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gaillard</persRef> the
                President of the Senate, <persRef key="clay-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    Clay</persRef>, Speaker of the House of Representatives and his <persRef
                    ref="clay-lucretia">Lady</persRef>, Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs:</hi>
                <persRef ref="macon-nathaniel">Macon</persRef>, <persRef ref="king-rufus"
                    >King</persRef>, and <persRef ref="eppes-john">Eppes</persRef> of the Senate,
                and Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi>
                <persRef ref="lowndes-william">Lowndes</persRef>, and <persRef ref="holmes-john"
                    >Holmes</persRef> of the House. <persRef ref="graham-george">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> G. Graham</persRef>, &amp;c, were of the Company;
                we came home between eight and nine in the Evening.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-08">
        <head>8 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-08"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
            <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>8. VI:</dateline> The <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef> is so
                much, and so constantly engaged that having nothing of indispensible urgency to call
                upon him for, I omitted going this day to his house— I received two Notes from the
                Spanish Minister <persRef ref="onis-luis">Onis</persRef>; one with a strong
                remonstrance against the occupation of Amelia Island, and the other a third long
                Memoir upon the Negotiation pending. As I was returning home from my Office, I met
                    <persRef ref="forsyth-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth</persRef>,
                the Chairman of the Committee of Foreign Relations, and had some Conversation with
                him— We had company to dinner— <persRef ref="crawford-william-harris;crawford-susanna">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi
                            rend="superscript">rs </hi>Crawford</persRef>, <persRef ref="calhoun-john;calhoun-floride"
                        >M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Calhoun</persRef>, <persRef
                            ref="crowninshield-benjamin;crowninshield-mary">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                            Crowninshield</persRef>, <persRef ref="pleasonton-stephen;pleasonton-mary">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi
                        rend="superscript">rs</hi> Pleasonton</persRef>, <persRef
                            ref="decatur-stephen;decatur-susan">Commodore and M<hi
                        rend="superscript">rs</hi> Decatur</persRef>, <persRef ref="king-rufus">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> King</persRef>, and <persRef ref="talbot-isham"
                        >M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Talbot</persRef> of the Senate, who brought
                excuses from <persRef ref="king-mary;talbot-margaret">their Ladies</persRef>, <persRef ref="hay-eliza">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                    Hay</persRef> and <persRef ref="monroe-joseph">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> J.
                    J. Monroe</persRef>. <persRef ref="mason-jonathan">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    Mason</persRef>, <persRef ref="ripley-eleazer">General Ripley</persRef>, who brought
                with him his Aide de Camp <persRef ref="nicholas-unknown">Lieut<hi
                        rend="superscript">t.</hi> Nicholas</persRef>, formed the Company— <persRef
                    ref="walsh-robert;walsh-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Walsh</persRef> sent excuses
                and <persRef ref="hay-george">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hay</persRef>, being
                elected a Senator in Virginia, has been obliged to go to Richmond— Our company went
                away about nine.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-09">
        <head>9 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-09"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>9. VI:</dateline> I prepared the draft of a Letter to <persRef
                    ref="shaler-william">W. Shaler</persRef>— When I called at the <persRef
                    key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> I found <persRef ref="biddle-nicholas"
                    >N. Biddle</persRef> of Philadelphia with him. He directed a Cabinet Meeting on
                the Amelia Island Affair at One O’Clock— I went to the Office, and returned to the
                President’s at One— The draft of the Message to Congress was again discussed; and it
                still persisted in the paragraph announcing that the troops would be withdrawn. I
                presented for consideration the doubt whether having taken possession under the act
                of January 1811. the Executive had a right to withdraw the troops and abandon the
                island, unless authorised thereto by a new Act of Congress. This question was again
                discussed with great earnestness till past four O’Clock— <persRef ref="calhoun-john"
                    >Calhoun</persRef> urged retaining it with great force and effect. I repeated
                the arguments of the former day, and added new ones as they occurred to me now— The
                President without giving up his opinion was very apparently affected by the conflict
                of Sentiment among his advisers— <persRef key="crawford-william-harris"
                    >Crawford</persRef> was staggered, and maintained his ground more feebly than
                the former day. <persRef ref="crowninshield-benjamin">Crowninshield</persRef>
                candidly told me that the argument was decidedly with us; but that he thought the
                best <hi rend="italic">policy</hi> would be to give the island up. <persRef
                    ref="wirt-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wirt</persRef> who came in
                very late and heard little of the debate, was still of the President’s opinion, and
                if he changes, will I believe change with him. We parted leaving the question yet
                undetermined, and the President, not a little embarrassed— These Cabinet Councils
                open upon me a new <pb type="ms" n="294"/>Scene and new views of the political
                world. Here is a play of Passions, Opinions and characters different in many
                respects from those in which I have been accustomed heretofore to move. There is
                slowness, want of decision and a Spirit of procrastination in the President which
                perhaps arises more from his situation than his personal character— The weather
                being foul, I rode home from the Office; and just as we were sitting down to dinner,
                came a <persRef ref="hodge-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hodge</persRef>,
                with a packet of despatches from <persRef ref="sumter-thomas">T. Sumter</persRef>,
                Minister Plenipotentiary at Rio de Janeiro, and also a Letter from <persRef
                    ref="prevost-john">J. B. Prevost</persRef>, who had arrived there in the
                Ontario, after a passage of 44 days from New York. These despatches, and a budget
                from <persRef ref="waterhouse-benjamin">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    Waterhouse</persRef>, with a plan for a Military Penitentiary engaged me the
                whole Evening.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-10">
        <head>10 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-10"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
            <note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
            <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
            <note type="subject">Privateering</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>10. VI:</dateline> <persRef ref="gouge-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gouge</persRef> brought
                me a Letter from <persRef ref="delaplaine-joseph">Jos. Delaplaine</persRef>
                concerning his biographical work; with a subscription paper, and the two published
                numbers of the work. <persRef ref="hauel-lucy">Lucy Hauel</persRef> left us— At the
                    <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> I found <persRef
                    ref="fromentin-eligius">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Fromentin</persRef>, one
                of the Senators from Louisiana, who has just returned from a tour to France— When he
                went away, I was about to give the President an account from the despatches of
                    <persRef ref="sumter-thomas">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sumter</persRef>;
                but I found his mind was intent upon another object— He said <persRef
                    ref="biddle-nicholas">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Biddle</persRef> had told
                him that some person of the family of <persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</persRef> had in the most positive terms
                affirmed that Spain was in a desperate and desponding condition, and Onis had very
                lately received a despatch ordering him to dispose as soon as possible of the
                Florida’s to the United States, upon the best terms he can obtain. the President
                therefore wished me to see Onis this day, and ask him simply what Spain would take
                for East-Florida; that is to say for all Spain’s possessions East of the
                Mississippi— I told him I would see Onis as he desired; but that I knew he would
                beat about the bush, and not make any proposition at all— I sent for Onis to come to
                me at the Office, and he came— I urged him for a full hour to make me a proposition,
                what they would ask for all their Territories East of the Mississippi; but he
                absolutely declined— He said <persRef ref="pizarro-joseph">Pizarro</persRef> had
                made a proposition to <persRef ref="erving-george">Erving</persRef>; and he had
                repeated it here— It was now our turn to make our proposition, and he would receive
                it with a most earnest desire which was that of the <persRef ref="ferdinand-vii"
                    >king of Spain</persRef>, that we should agree— And not only agree; but Spain
                wished for an Alliance with the United States—at least defensive— He urged strongly
                for an answer to his remonstrances against the occupation of Amelia Island— I told
                him we could easily justify that— I had no doubt to his satisfaction. But it might
                be necessary to say things which it would be disagreeable for Spain to hear, and for
                us to say. We had not taken the possession from Spain, nor committed any hostility
                against her— We had been obliged in our own defence, to take the place, in defense
                of our Laws, of our Commerce, and that of Nations at Peace with us, Spain included—
                But all this it would be useless to say, if he would make me a proposition upon
                which we could in a few days agree. All discussion about Amelia Island would then be
                superseded— He still refused to make any proposition about Amelia-Island. But said
                he wanted an answer. I might assign what motives for the act, I thought proper— He
                wanted something to say to the <persRef ref="cienfuegos-jose">Governor General of
                    the Havanna</persRef>, to the <persRef ref="coppinger-jose">Governor of S<hi
                        rend="superscript">t.</hi> Augustine</persRef>, and to his Court— I asked
                him what guaranty he could give that if we should withdraw from the Island it should
                not again be immediately occupied by freebooters to the annoyance of all lawful
                Commerce— He said that we might require that the Governor of the Havanna should send
                there a garrison of 400 men. I asked him if he could engage that they should be
                sent— He said, no, but he could write to the Governor of the Havanna about it; and
                if it should take six, nine, or twelve Months he could tell him it was a subject for
                Negotiation between the Governments— I reported the substance of this Conversation
                to the President, who said he should perhaps modify his Message to the House of
                Representatives in consequence of it— He thought he would have another cabinet
                meeting upon it on Monday— <persRef ref="irvine-baptis">M<hi rend="superscript"
                        >r</hi> B. Irvine</persRef> called likewise at the Office, and had some
                conversation with me concerning the affair of Amelia-Island— I had some suspicion
                that he came for the purpose of sounding—</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-11">
        <head>11 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-11"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
            <note type="subject">Privateering</note>
            <note type="subject">Recreation</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>11. VI:30.</dateline> <persRef ref="cardelli-pietro">Cardelli</persRef> was here this Morning. <persRef
                    ref="smith-samuel2">Gen<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> S. Smith</persRef> came,
                and left with me a Letter to the <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef>
                asking for the appointment of a commercial agent at Batavia— He also wanted
                information upon various other subjects, and particularly concerning Amelia-Island.
                He said <persRef ref="aury-louis">Aury’s</persRef> Letter in answer to the Summons,
                had produced, a great sensation among the members of the house. His Son <persRef
                    ref="smith-john2">John</persRef> wrote him it had had the same effect at
                Baltimore. He was sure it would greatly injure the Administration among its best
                friends if the island should be given up. I told him confidentially that I had from
                the beginning thought it should not be given up: that I believed the President had
                not finally determined what course to take, but that a Message to Congress would go
                in two or <pb type="ms" n="295"/>three days; perhaps even to-morrow— Smith said he
                would call and see the President this day— I paid visit to Mess<hi
                    rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                <persRef ref="holmes-john">Holmes</persRef>, <persRef ref="hopkinson-joseph"
                    >Hopkinson</persRef> and several other Members of Congress, and walked from near
                Georgetown home. <persRef ref="frye-nathaniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    Frye</persRef> was here; and in the Evening <persRef ref="bulfinch-charles">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> Bulfinch</persRef> and his <persRef
                    ref="bulfinch-thomas">Son</persRef>. <persRef ref="walsh-robert">R.
                    Walsh</persRef> sent me this morning the works of <persRef ref="aquinas-thomas"
                    >Thomas Aquinas</persRef> to read— I wrote a couple of Letters, and retrieved my
                arrears of Journal.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-12">
        <head>12 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-12"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
            <note type="subject">Immigration</note>
            <note type="subject">Press</note>
            <note type="subject">Privateering</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>12. VII:</dateline> At the <persRef key="monroe-james"
                    >President’s</persRef> I found <persRef ref="desha-joseph">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> Desha</persRef>; member of Congress from Kentucky.
                    <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun</persRef> and
                    <persRef ref="wirt-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wirt</persRef> were
                also there— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun soon went away, and <persRef
                    ref="crowninshield-benjamin">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    Crowninshield</persRef> came in— The Message concerning Amelia-Island was still
                under Consideration; and the President had modified it to the purpose of retaining
                the possession of it for the present. It appeared from some remarks of the President
                that <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">Crawford</persRef> had been there and
                agreed to this modification— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crowninshield was also
                satisfied with the change, and M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wirt had some scruples
                which were however soon removed— The President had likewise added several very
                important paragraphs to the draft of the Message, which he said he should send to
                Congress to-morrow. <persRef ref="middleton-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    Middleton</persRef> made the Report from the Amelia-Island Committee to the
                House of Representatives on Saturday, and it is printed in the National
                Intelligencer of this day— I took the President’s directions upon several other
                objects; but his mind is so absorbed with Amelia-Island, that he can scarcely bear
                to have any other presented to him— <persRef ref="chevallie-j">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> Chevallié</persRef> called on me at the Office,
                about the Message on the <persRef ref="beaumarchais-pierre">Beaumarchais</persRef>
                claim— The President had sent me the Papers, asking me to make the draft of a
                Message to go with them; I read him the draft last Friday, and after making an
                alteration which he suggested sent it back to him with the Papers on Saturday— He
                said this morning that he intended to send it in this day; which I told M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                Chevallié. I had a note from <persRef ref="aguirre-manuel">Aguirre</persRef> asking
                an interview, for which I appointed to-morrow at two O’Clock. <persRef
                    key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">Hyde de Neuville</persRef> came and I had a
                conversation of an hour or more with him. He told me the <persRef
                    ref="richelieu-armand">Duke de Richelieu</persRef> had written him, there was a
                Convention about South American affairs on foot in Europe— Urged again for an Answer
                to his notes of complaint, about french vessels captured by privateers; and hinted
                fears that the French Tombigby settlers were engaged in a project against the
                Florida’s. I shewed him the Amelia Island Committee Report, which appeared thus far
                to satisfy him— I received an important Letter also from <persRef
                    ref="toulmin-henry">H. Toulmin</persRef>, but it was too late to communicate it
                to the President— It was half past five O’Clock when I left the Office— Evening
                Cold.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-13">
        <head>13 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-13"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
            <note type="subject">Commerce</note>
            <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
            <note type="subject">Privateering</note>
            <note type="subject">South American Wars of Independence</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>13. VII:</dateline> Fahrenheit at 12. Going this morning to the <persRef
                    key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> I met <persRef ref="middleton-henry"
                        >M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Middleton</persRef>, who asked me if there
                would soon be a message from the President about Amelia Island; and said that
                    <persRef key="clay-henry">Clay</persRef> looked plaguy hard at him since his
                Report. At the President’s I met again <persRef ref="biddle-nicholas">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> Biddle</persRef> who immediately retired as I went
                in. The President’s Message to the two houses was ready, and he sent it in this day.
                The measures relating to Amelia-Island, South-America, and Spain are laying the
                foundation of a new system of Opposition to the Administration, with Clay at its
                head. <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">Crawford</persRef> told me the other
                day, that Clay, Saturday Evening before last, being gay and warm with wine, told him
                he meant to follow up his attack; and added—“and I’ll beat you, by ——”! But a day or
                two afterwards he came to him cool, and said he was very anxious to avoid collision
                if possible, and proposed to make merely an appropriation for a Minister to Buenos
                Ayres— I read to the President <persRef ref="toulmin-henry">Judge
                    Toulmin’s</persRef> Letter, and some other papers indicating the purpose of
                    <persRef ref="macgregor-gregor">M’Gregor’s</persRef> project against the
                Florida’s, and requested him to make a Memorandum of the points to be proposed in my
                reply to <persRef ref="onis-luis">Onis’s</persRef> Notes— He asked me to send him an
                extract from <persRef ref="erving-george">Erving’s</persRef> Instructions relating
                to the boundaries; which I did. He afterwards sent me a note advising me to see Onis
                to-morrow, and shew him the indications of M’Gregor’s projected expedition against
                the Floridas, and Judge Toulmin’s Letter. <persRef ref="aguirre-manuel">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> Aguirre</persRef> came this day at two O’Clock,
                and urged again for answers to his demand for the acknowledgment of the Government
                of Buenos-Ayres— He also said he came to tell me, that the Commerce between this
                Country and that stood merely on the footing of the will and pleasure of his
                Government— That they had opened their Ports without limitation, and might shut them
                again when they saw fit— It was therefore proper that some fixed <pb type="ms"
                    n="296"/>agreement on the subject should be made— He also entered into a long
                statement of the transactions between the Government of Brezil and that of Buenos
                Ayres, on the Brezilian occupation of Montevideo, and the Banda Oriental. They had
                interdicted all intercourse between Buenos Ayres and the Brazilians, but without
                declaring War. He also spoke equivocally of <persRef ref="artigas-jose"
                    >Artigas</persRef>, intending evidently that I should understand him as meaning
                that Artigas was a General of Buenos Ayres— I therefore asked him distinctly whether
                it was so, and whether Artigas acknowledged the Government of Buenos Ayres. He said
                no. But that Buenos Ayres claimed the whole Banda Oriental, and <hi rend="italic">he
                    thought</hi> would never relinquish it— I asked him if he was instructed by his
                Government to give me the intimations about shutting their Ports: He said no. I told
                him that as they were of a serious nature, I wished him to give them to me in
                writing— That if Buenos Ayres was to be viewed as a Colonial Government its Ports
                might by the usages of European Powers be shut to all nations but the Mother
                Country. But as an Independent Nation, by the customary Law of Nations they could
                not shut their Ports to other Nations, and still less to one particular Nation
                without a cause— That we had opened our Ports to their flag, and certainly should
                not shut them without a special Cause— He said the opening of our Ports to their
                flag was no benefit to them— They were not a maritime Nation, and had neither ships
                nor Seamen. They had issued Commissions for Privateers to annoy their enemy, but
                none of them were owned by their own People; and it would be no injury to them if
                our Ports should be shut against them— I wrote this Evening to <persRef
                    key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot</persRef>, on the case
                of the Erie, <persRef ref="gamble-thomas">Captain Gamble</persRef>, at
                Marseilles.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-14">
        <head>14 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-14"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
            <note type="subject">Commerce</note>
            <note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
            <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
            <note type="subject">Native Americans</note>
            <note type="subject">Privateering</note>
            <note type="subject">Seminole Wars</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>14. VII:</dateline> Met and spoke to <persRef key="bagot-charles">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot</persRef> this morning, on my way to the
                    <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef>— He asked me, if it was the
                intention of the President to communicate to Congress the Letters which had passed
                between the Secretary of State, &amp; him (Bagot,) containing the arrangement
                concerning Armaments on the Lakes; which he said was a sort of Treaty. I spoke of it
                to the President; who did not think it necessary that they should be communicated—
                It has been usual heretofore with the Message, at the opening of the Session of
                Congress to send a collection of documents with it, relating to the principal
                subjects mentioned in it— This was not done at the present Session, and some
                inconvenience has resulted from the omission— I had a letter to M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot prepared, in answer to a complaint from him of
                9. June last against <persRef ref="gamble-thomas">Captain Gamble</persRef> of the
                Sloop of War Erie, for damage done to the Cable of an English Merchant Vessel in the
                Harbour of Marseilles, and for not permitting a citation from the tribunal of
                Commerce to be served upon him on board his vessel. The tribunal of Commerce gave
                sentence against Captain Gamble by default, for damages and Costs— Gamble’s report
                admitted that he had resisted the service of the citation, and I proposed to the
                President to pay the money at once; if it were only for the sake of the precedent.
                the President agreed to this yesterday, and I had this morning a draft of a Letter
                ready to the same effect. He now thought it would be best to take the opinions of
                the Heads of Departments; and I accordingly consulted <persRef ref="calhoun-john"
                    >Calhoun</persRef> and <persRef ref="crowninshielf-benjamin"
                    >Crowninshield</persRef>, both of whom agreed to my draft— <persRef
                    ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</persRef> came to the Office
                at half past two, and I had an hour’s Conversation with him upon our Negotiation— I
                shewed him <persRef ref="toulmin-henry">judge Toulmin’s</persRef> letter, and that
                of the <persRef ref="masot-jose">Governor of Pensacola</persRef>; to him— The recruiting
                advertisement in the name of <persRef ref="macgregor-gregor">M’Gregor</persRef> at
                New Providence and told him we had other evidence of his design to attack the
                Florida’s in the Spring. I mentioned also the hostilities of the Seminole Indians
                upon our frontiers, probably connected with the same plan— And I urged that if we
                should not come to an early conclusion of the Florida Negotiation, Spain would not
                have the possession of Florida to give us. He said he knew of the Letter from the
                Governor of Pensacola. That the pirates might possibly take that place for a short
                time, but would certainly be soon driven from it and certainly would not get S<hi
                    rend="superscript">t.</hi> Augustine, at least he did not believe they would—
                They had been subdued in Mexico and New Grenada; and would be soon subdued in Buenos
                Ayres and Chili. That as to the Seminole Indians there were two divisions of them,
                one living in Florida, and the other within the territories of the United States.
                That those now in hostility with us were our own Indians, and not those of the
                Spanish dominions— He asked me why we had suffered the Pirates at Amelia-Island to
                carry away their booty— I told him because we had no competent jurisdiction for
                trying whether it was theirs or not— He finally desired me to make these statements
                to him in writing— When I came home, I found <persRef ref="hellen-adelaide">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">rs</hi> Hellen</persRef> here— She had dined, and in the
                Evening went with us to <persRef ref="monroe-elizabeth">M<hi rend="superscript"
                        >rs</hi> Monroe’s</persRef> first drawing-room. The house was much crowded,
                but the number of Ladies there was not very considerable. I had various conversation
                with many persons— The party broke up soon after nine. We went home with M<hi
                    rend="superscript">rs</hi> Hellen, and were at our own house about ten.</p>
        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-15">
        <head>15 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-15"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">
            <p><pb type="ms" n="297"/><dateline>15. VII:</dateline> <persRef ref="goddard-nathaniel">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> N. Goddard</persRef> of Boston was here, and
                brought Letters from <persRef ref="welles-samuel">Gen<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi>
                    Welles</persRef> and <persRef ref="dawes-thomas">judge Dawes</persRef>. He has a
                Petition to Congress. At the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> I met
                    <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    Crawford</persRef>, who agreed to the draft of a note to <persRef
                    key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot</persRef> on the case
                of the Erie at Marseilles. The President sent yesterday his Message to Congress on
                the taking possession of Amelia-Island. This morning he gave me a memorandum for a
                Note to <persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</persRef>, in
                answer to three received from him— Dined with my <persRef
                    key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef> at <persRef ref="walsh-robert">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> Walsh’s</persRef>— <persRef ref="bagot-charles;bagot-mary"
                        >M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi
                        rend="superscript">rs</hi> Bagot</persRef> were there. <persRef
                    key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hyde de
                            Neuville</persRef>, <persRef ref="middleton-henry;middleton-mary">M<hi rend="superscript"
                        >r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript"
                        >rs</hi> Middleton</persRef>, <persRef ref="dickerson-unknown">Gen<hi
                        rend="superscript">l.</hi> Dickerson</persRef>, <persRef
                    ref="ripley-eleazer">Gen<hi rend="superscript">l:</hi> Ripley</persRef>,
                    <persRef ref="hopkinson-joseph">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    Hopkinson</persRef>, and <persRef ref="brent-daniel">M<hi rend="superscript"
                        >r</hi> D. Brent</persRef> were there— I had conversation with Hopkinson
                after dinner, who says the federal members in Congress will support the measures of
                the Executive concerning Amelia-Island; being once satisfied that there was no
                intention of making conquest of Spain— There was also an Evening party at Walsh’s,
                from which we went and attended a large Evening party at <persRef ref="smith-samuel"
                        >M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sam<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> H.
                    Smith’s</persRef>.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-16">
        <head>16 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-16"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
            <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
            <note type="subject">Treaty of Ghent</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>16. VII:</dateline> I made the draft this Morning of a note to <persRef
                    ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</persRef>, in answer to his
                three long ones upon the negotiation, and at the same time, I took the opportunity
                to say something in answer to his two Notes, upon the occupation of Amelia Island—
                This I did because having several times intimated to the <persRef key="monroe-james"
                    >President</persRef> the necessity of giving <hi rend="italic">some</hi> answer
                to those Notes, he has always said that his message would be an answer. My draft
                therefore this day was merely a note of references, and with some slight alterations
                was approved by him— <persRef ref="porter-peter">General Peter B. Porter</persRef>,
                Commissioner under the 6<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> and 7<hi rend="superscript"
                    >th:</hi> Articles of the Treaty of Ghent came to the Office. He says it will
                take several years to get through both the objects of the Commission. We had company
                to tea, and to spend the Evening. <persRef ref="walsh-robert;walsh-unknown">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi
                        rend="superscript">rs</hi> Walsh</persRef>, the <persRef ref="correa-joseph"
                            >Abbe Correa</persRef>, <persRef ref="boyd-george;boyd-harriet">M<hi rend="superscript"
                        >r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript"
                            >rs</hi> Boyd</persRef>, <persRef ref="frye-nathaniel;frye-carolina">M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi
                        rend="superscript">rs</hi> Frye</persRef>, <persRef
                    key="smith-william-steuben">W. S. Smith</persRef>, <persRef
                    ref="hellen-adelaide">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Hellen</persRef>, <persRef
                    ref="trimble-david">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Trimble</persRef>, <persRef
                    ref="pope-nathaniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> N. Pope</persRef>, who has
                just returned from New-York, having been no farther and <persRef ref="vail-unknown"
                        >M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Vail</persRef>. I told Trimble in
                confidence, that there was one paper stating a fact to which he had referred in his
                speech on the motion for a call upon the President for papers in the case of
                <persRef ref="meade-richard">R. C. Meade</persRef>, and which we should not send in answer to
                the call— And I gave him the reason why? It comes from <persRef ref="erving-george"
                    >Erving</persRef>; and not officially, but through <persRef ref="meade-margaret"
                        >M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Meade</persRef>. If it should be published
                Erving could no longer be of any service at Madrid, and it would be absolutely
                necessary to remove him— Trimble said he was satisfied— And when the papers came, he
                should move a resolution for reprizals. I received this Evening a Letter from
                    <persRef ref="pope-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John Pope</persRef> of
                Frankfort, Kentucky.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-17">
        <head>17 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-17"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>17. VII:</dateline> <persRef ref="holmes-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Holmes</persRef> paid me a visit
                this Morning at my house, and introduced to me another of the members of the House
                of Representatives, from Massachusetts, <persRef ref="morton-marcus">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Morton</persRef>— At
                the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef>, he made his return to the Summons to attend a naval Court Martial
                at Philadelphia— This summons was enclosed by <persRef ref="dallas-george">G. M. Dallas</persRef>, in a Letter to me, three
                days ago. It was first referred to the Attorney General, <persRef ref="wirt-william">M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Wirt</persRef>, for his opinion which he gave; and which was that the President of
                the United States is amenable to a Summons as a witness; but that he may excuse
                himself from giving attendance, from his paramount duty of remaining at Washington;
                offering at the same time to give his deposition. The President made his return
                accordingly; and conformably to the Precedents in the trial of <persRef ref="burr-aaron">A. Burr</persRef>; and in that
                of <persRef key="smith-william-steuben">Col<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> W. S. Smith</persRef>— I called by the President’s
                direction, upon <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun</persRef>, with a Letter from the
                Secretary of the State of Pennsylvania, concerning the power of remitting certain
                Militia fines. The Question is whether the power is vested in the President or in
                the Governor of Pennsylvania— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Monroe thinks it is in
                him— Calhoun thinks it is in the Governor— <persRef ref="rhea-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Rhea</persRef> of
                Tennessee, and <persRef ref="silsbee-nathaniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Silsbee</persRef> were at the Office— I had sent
                to ask <persRef ref="irvine-baptis">B. Irvine</persRef> to call at the Office; the President having determined to send him
                as commercial agent to Venezuela; but he was gone to Baltimore. <persRef ref="homans-benjamin">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Homans</persRef> called for orders to the <persRef ref="read-george">Captain</persRef> of the Hornet—
                But we are not ready to give them; though the President has determined to send <persRef ref="lewis-jacob">Jacob
                Lewis</persRef> to Port au Prince, and <persRef ref="taylor-william">William Taylor</persRef> to Cape Henry. As I was returning home,
                I met at my door <persRef ref="goddard-s">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Goddard</persRef> with a copy of his petition
                    <pb type="ms" n="298"/>to Congress— <persRef ref="hellen-adelaide">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Hellen</persRef> came
                in immediately after dinner, and went with my <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef> to the weekly Evening party at
                <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hyde de Neuville’s</persRef>— I wrote to my <persRef ref="adams-thomas">brother</persRef>.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-18">
        <head>18 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-18"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>18. VI:</dateline> Morning visit from <persRef ref="ripley-eleazer">General Ripley</persRef>. I attended Church at
                the Hall of the House of Representatives; where Prayers were read, and a short
                Sermon— I returned home and with my <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef> paid visits to <persRef ref="sergeant-john;sergeant-margaretta">M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> J. Sergeant</persRef>— And I afterwards
                visited <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun</persRef> and <persRef ref="lowndes-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                Lowndes</persRef>— The remainder of the day I was closely engaged at home without
                accomplishing any thing more than merely fetching up the lee-way of my Journal. My
                Servant man <persRef ref="giusta-antoine">Antoine Michel Giusta</persRef> who has lived with me since June 1814. gave me
                notice that he should leave me— He says he cannot accommodate himself to this
                Country, and must return to his own.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-19">
        <head>19 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-19"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
            <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
            <note type="subject">Press</note>
            <note type="subject">Privateering</note>
            <note type="subject">South American Wars of Independence</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>19. VI:</dateline> At the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> this Morning I found <persRef ref="reed-philip">Col<hi
                    rend="superscript">l.</hi> P. Reed</persRef>, of Maryland; now a member of the House of
                Representatives, and formerly one of my Colleagues in the Senate— He was
                recommending paupers for Office. It is one of our misfortunes that all the places
                under the Government are bestowed upon people of this description; men whose wants
                are their principal if not their only qualifications. When Col<hi rend="superscript"
                    >l.</hi> Reed withdrew I found the President was much agitated by a report, in
                the Baltimore Newspapers of the 16<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> and 17<hi
                    rend="superscript">th.</hi> announcing a Letter of the 7<hi rend="superscript"
                    >th.</hi> inst<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> from Savannah, stating that advices
                had arrived there by Letter and otherwise from the Havanna, that all the American
                vessels there had been detained, on the news of the capture of Amelia-Island by the
                American troops. He appeared alarmed at the idea of a War with Spain, backed by the
                allied powers; observed that our squadron in the Mediterranean would be exposed, and
                that there was no sufficient cause for us to go to War with Spain— He asked me what
                I thought was to be done, and without expressly alluding to it, evidently appeared
                to regret that he had not as he had inclined, ordered our troops to withdraw from
                the Island when the Pirates were removed. This incident is in truth an untoward one,
                and therefore most likely to be well founded— I had as visitors at the Office,
                <persRef ref="porter-peter">General P. B. Porter</persRef> with his accounts, <persRef ref="burrill-james">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Burrell</persRef>, a
                Senator and <persRef ref="mason-james">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Mason</persRef>, a Representative from
                Rhode-Island, who came to recommend persons for Offices, and <persRef ref="pope-nathaniel">M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> N. Pope</persRef>, who spoke of Resolutions in the Legislature of Kentucky,
                proclaiming the Independence of the South-Americans, and who gave me a curious
                account of Western Politics— The President sent to ask me to call at his house on my
                return from the Office, which I did. He came out to me from his dinner— It was from
                a second account of the news from the Havanna— He had read it in a Charleston
                newspaper. That three Officers had arrived at Amelia Island from the Havana,
                demanding its surrender; and that in the mean time all the American vessels at the
                Havanna, amounting to two hundred were embargoed. The number he said, must be an
                exaggeration; there could not be more than twenty or thirty— But what was to be
                done? would it not be best to write immediately to <persRef ref="onis-luis">Onis</persRef>— We could not for a moment
                parley with a subaltern like the Governor of the Havanna. The Negotiation with Onis
                he considered it as certain would fail— But this Event would immediately change the
                state of our Relations with Spain; and bring us at once into War— I told him if the
                account was true, it could not fail to come officially within two or three days; and
                I thought it best to wait till then and he appeared more calm on the subject, than
                he had been this Morning— My <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef> spent the Evening at <persRef key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Bagot’s</persRef>; and I employed it in writing private Letters.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-20">
        <head>20 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-20"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
            <note type="subject">Immigration</note>
            <note type="subject">Press</note>
            <note type="subject">Privateering</note>
            <note type="subject">Treaty of Ghent</note>
            <note type="subject">War of 1812</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>20. VI:</dateline> Calling as usual this morning at the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> I found
                him quite cool and easy upon the subject of the supposed news from the Havanna— I
                asked him if he had observed the dates mentioned in the Charleston Newspaper, he had
                not; but he had seen a Newspaper of a later date which said nothing on the subject,
                and was now convinced the Report was without foundation. My own uneasiness was not
                entirely removed; for although I saw the paragraph afterwards and found by its date
                at S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Mary’s. of 3. January it must be groundless; as
                despatches from our Commander at Amelia Island of that same day have been received;
                yet as the report may be only the precursor of the fact, I shall yet be anxious to
                hear the first real news from the Havanna— The President examined <persRef ref="porter-peter">General P. B.
                Porter’s</persRef> Accounts as Commissioner under the 6<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> and
                    7<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> Articles of the Treaty of Ghent, and made some
                remarks upon them— At the Office I had visitors— <persRef ref="middleton-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                Middleton</persRef> who came to make further enquiries concerning the affairs at
                Amelia-Island, particularly as to Commissions for privateering granted to our
                Citizens by <persRef ref="macgregor-gregor">M’Gregor</persRef> and <persRef ref="aury-louis">Aury</persRef>, upon which I gave him the fullest proof. He expects a
                violent attack upon the Report of the Committee in the House— A <persRef ref="laurence-unknown">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Laurence</persRef> of New-York came, concerning the accounts of
                the Marshal of the District of New-York lately deceased— <persRef ref="smith-samuel2">Gen<hi rend="superscript"
                    >l.</hi> S. Smith</persRef> had a Letter from his partner <persRef ref="buchanan-james">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                Buchanan</persRef> referring to a packet sent by him to the Department of State, and which I
                received by this day’s Mail— It was a Commission for a privateer—with Commissions
                for a Captain, four Lieutenants, and six prize Masters all with the names left in
                blank, from the Buenos Ayres Government, sent by <persRef ref="halsey-thomas">T. L. Halsey</persRef> the Consul there to <persRef ref="wolfe-james">De
                Wolfe</persRef> at Bristol R.I. with a recommendation if he did not think fit to use them,
                that <pb type="ms" n="299"/>he would send them to Smith and Buchanan at Baltimore—
                De Wolfe sent them accordingly, and Buchanan sent these Documents to the Department
                of State— In his Letter to Gen<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> Smith he expressed
                himself with great indignation at this attempt upon the honour of the house. Gen<hi
                    rend="superscript">l.</hi> Smith spoke also of a demand which his house have as
                Agents to a British house in Calcutta, for a balance of more than 7000 dollars due
                to them for a Vessel called the Venus, and her Cargo, taken by the Peacock <persRef ref="warrington-lewis">Captain
                Warrington</persRef>, after the Peace. I have a Note from <persRef key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                Bagot</persRef>, on the subject to answer. <persRef ref="crowninshield-benjamin">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crowninshield</persRef> came
                in, and I asked him if he had the Money. He objected to paying it, and thought it
                should come from the contingent fund of the Department of State, which it certainly
                cannot. I agreed to speak about it to the President. <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                Hyde de Neuville</persRef> came principally to tell me, informally that to-morrow, there would
                be at the Catholic Church the anniversary funereal service for the death of <persRef ref="louis-xvi">Louis
                16</persRef>— That he had last year invited M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Monroe who did not
                attend, and had observed that there were certain circumstances in the feelings and
                sentiments of people in this Country, which might make his attendance improper. De
                Neuville said he was aware of this, and if I was of the same opinion, I could
                consider his invitation as non-avenu; as if he had said nothing to me— I said
                nothing to him in answer to his invitation, though I determined to go— I received
                several Letters from <persRef ref="degrand-peter">De Grand</persRef> at Boston, and <persRef ref="lee-william">W. Lee</persRef> brought me his statement of
                <persRef ref="galabert-unknown">Galabert’s</persRef> Revelations about the projects of the <persRef ref="lallemand-charles;lallemand-henri">L’Allemand’s</persRef> and the <persRef ref="galvez-unknown">Count de
                Galvez</persRef>— My <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef> spent the Evening at <persRef ref="decatur-susan">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Decatur’s</persRef>, and
                <persRef ref="gales-joseph">Gales</persRef> and <persRef ref="seaton-william">Seaton</persRef> part of it with me. I answered De Grand’s letter— After eleven at
                Night, I received a Letter from <persRef ref="walsh-robert">R. Walsh</persRef> renewing, for M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> De Neuville the invitation for the funeral service to-morrow
                Morning.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-21">
        <head>21 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-21"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
            <note type="subject">Press</note>
            <note type="subject">Religion</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>21. VII.</dateline> As I was going out this Morning, <persRef ref="sever-unknown">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Sever</persRef> <space/> of Massachusetts came and made me a
                communication respecting my <persRef ref="adams-thomas">brother</persRef>— Attended with my <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef> and <persRef ref="hellen-mary">Mary Hellen</persRef> at the
                Catholic Church, the funeral service for <persRef ref="louis-xvi">Louis 16</persRef>. We sat in the same pew with <persRef ref="onis-luis">Onis</persRef>,
                the Spanish Minister. The Mass was short, but there was a funeral Oration, read by
                the Priest, from the text 1. Eccles: 1. Vanity of Vanities; and all is Vanity, the
                most extraordinary composition, of jacobinism, heresy, and priestly doctrine that I
                ever heard— All the foreign Ministers and their Legations were present, and all
                their gravity could not restrain some of them from laughter. At the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> I
                found him relieved from all concern about the news from the Havanna, and expecting
                offers from Onis that will be acceptable— I shewed him the papers from <persRef ref="halsey-thomas">Halsey</persRef>, whose
                Commission he ordered to be immediately revoked, assigning to him the reasons for
                the measure. The President directed that the money to be paid for the Venus,
                captured by <persRef ref="warrington-lewis">Warrington</persRef> should be furnished by the Navy department. At the Office I
                had visitors, <persRef ref="leamy-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Leamy</persRef>, a Merchant of Philadelphia, part
                owner of a vessel called the Liberty, captured by the Venezuelian <persRef ref="brion-luis">Admiral Brion</persRef>, in
                the River Oroonoque; <persRef ref="irvine-baptis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> B. Irvine</persRef>, whom the President
                has determined to send to the Terra Firma, among other things to demand satisfaction
                for this case and that of the Tiger— <persRef ref="lee-william">W. Lee</persRef>, who came to say something further about
                <persRef ref="galabert-unknown">Galabert</persRef> and the <persRef ref="lallemand-charles;lallemand-henri">L’Allemand’s</persRef>, and who was amazed at my asking him to ascertain from
                Galabert, whether he was not holding communications with Onis— <persRef ref="boothroyd-jabez">J. Boothroyd</persRef>, an
                unsuccessful candidate for the agency at Cape Henry, Haÿti much disappointed—and
                <persRef ref="barker-jacob">Jacob Barker</persRef> of N’York who shewed me a slip of the Mercantile Advertiser, issued as
                he says is usual to give early news, a day before it appears in the Newspaper— This
                slip mentioned the arrival of a Vessel at New-York from the Havanna, in twelve days—
                My wife spent the Evening at her <persRef ref="boyd-harriet">Sister Boyd’s</persRef>— I drafted a Letter to the French
                Minister, <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">Hyde</persRef>, in answer to a complaint received from him on the case of the Erie,
                <persRef ref="gamble-thomas">Captain Gamble</persRef>.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-22">
        <head>22 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-22"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
            <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
            <note type="subject">Privateering</note>
            <note type="subject">South American Wars of Independence</note>
            <note type="subject">U.S. Constitution</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>22. VII:</dateline> My <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef> received this Morning notes from <persRef ref="monroe-elizabeth">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">rs</hi> Monroe</persRef> requesting she would call upon her this day at
                one or two O’Clock, and she went— It was to inform her that the Ladies had taken
                offence at her not paying them the first visit— All Ladies arriving here as
                strangers it seems expect to be visited by the wives of the heads of Departments and
                even by the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> wife— <persRef ref="madison-dolley">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Madison</persRef> subjected
                herself to this torture, which she felt <pb type="ms" n="300"/>very severely, but
                from which having begun the practice, she never found an opportunity of receding
                from it. M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Monroe neither pays nor returns any visits—
                My wife returns all visits but adopts the principle of not visiting first, every
                stranger who arrives, and this is what the Ladies have taken in dudgeon. My wife
                informed M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Monroe that she should adhere to her
                principle, but not on any question of etiquette; as she did not exact of any Lady
                that she should visit her— At the President’s I met <persRef ref="crowninshield-benjamin">Crowninshield</persRef> and told him the
                President had determined, the money to pay for the Venus must come from his
                Department. He said he must then get an appropriation for it— At the Office, <persRef ref="waite-thomas">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Waite</persRef> a Printer from Boston brought me Letters of
                Recommendation from <persRef ref="waterhouse-benjamin">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Waterhouse</persRef>, and <persRef ref="prince-james">Marshal Prince</persRef>.
                He wishes to have the printing of the Journal of the Convention, which formed the 
                present Constitution. He has printed two Editions of a Collection of State Papers,
                in ten Volumes, a great part of which he says he never should have obtained but from
                my library at the Athenaeum in Boston. He is to call again— <persRef ref="aguirre-manuel">M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Aguirre</persRef> came, and asked me to return his two Commissions, as Agent for
                Buenos Ayres, and Chili. He had left the original Commissions themselves at the
                Office. They were now returned to him, copies having been taken of them. He now
                explained to me the motive for his verbal statement to me at a former conference, of
                the manner in which his Government had considered the occupation of Montevideo by
                the Portuguese, and which at my request he afterwards repeated in a written Note— It
                was a view to the transactions of the United States at Amelia-Island— That his
                Government though including in its declaration of Independence, only the Provinces
                which had constituted the Vice-Royalty of La Plata, considered that it could not be
                indifferent to the transactions of any foreign power regarding any part of the
                former Spanish possessions in America South or North; because the occupation of any
                part of them by one power, might occasion the interposition of other European Powers
                in a manner injurious to his Country— I asked him if before the departure of <persRef ref="rodney-caesar">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Rodney</persRef> and <persRef ref="bland-theoderick">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bland</persRef>, he
                had had some conversation with them, on the subject of our occupation of
                Amelia-Island— He said he had— That he had told them the adventurers, who had taken
                possession of that place, never had any authority from his Government whatever. That
                he thought the Government of the United States were fully justified in breaking them
                up; and that he was assured it would be considered in the same light by his
                Government— But since then he had been induced to consider it in a more enlarged
                point of view; and with that impression had communicated to me the proceedings and
                principles of his Government, on the invasion of Montevideo by the Portuguese. I
                asked him whether he knew that the former agent from Buenos-Ayres, <persRef ref="tompson-james">Tompson</persRef> had been
                dismissed from his agency, by the <persRef ref="pueyrredon-juan">Suprème Director Pueyrredon</persRef>, for having
                transcended his authority, in granting Commissions— He said certainly not; and it
                was not so— I shewed him the Letter from Pueyrredon, to the President, declaring the
                revocation of Tompson’s Commission— I then told him that as the view he now
                presented of the manner in which his Government might view our proceedings at Amelia
                Island, were entirely different from those which he had taken in Conversation with
                    Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Rodney and Bland; if it was so that the
                Government of Buenos Ayres considered themselves as having a superintendency over
                all the Spanish Provinces in both Continents of America, I should request him to
                make this communication to me in writing, for it was fitting that distinct and
                explicit notice of it should be given to the Government of the United States— We
                should regret exceedingly that his Government or country should view our
                transactions at Amelia Island as implying or intending any thing unfriendly to them
                or to their cause— We were as friendly to them as we could be compatibly with our
                engagements of neutrality. But if by our proceedings at Amelia-Island, or in the
                Florida’s we were to be considered as interfering with the interests or policy of
                Buenos Ayres, it would be proper that we should have previous notice of those
                pretensions that we might regulate our own policy accordingly— He said he could not
                give any thing on the subject in writing. That his observations had been merely his
                own, without authority from his Government; and that he had no right to speak in any
                public capacity other than that of agent to the Government of La Plata— He added
                that he proposed going to-morrow to Baltimore to pass a fortnight, and should
                proceed from thence to New-York, where he should remain at my commands if I should
                have any thing to communicate to him until the Spring— <persRef ref="lee-william">W. Lee</persRef> came to tell me that
                to his utter <pb type="ms" n="301"/>amazement he last Evening saw <persRef ref="galabert-unknown">Galabert</persRef> go into
                <persRef ref="onis-luis">Onis’s</persRef> house— That he had not seen him since, but would see and ask an explanation
                of him— <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun</persRef> called at the Office, with the papers
                concerning the question about the remission of Militia fines in Pennsylvania. He
                wishes the opinion of the Attorney-General to be taken upon it— Calhoun spoke also
                of the Negotiation with Spain, and expressed a strong aversion to any concession
                with regard to the boundary West of the Mississippi— Dined with my wife at the
                chevalier Onis’s, the Spanish Minister’s. All the Corps Diplomatique were there; and
                    <persRef ref="biddle-nicholas">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Biddle</persRef> of Philadelphia. Onis told me he should
                reply to my Note to-morrow or the next day. But asked me which I meant of three
                Rivers Colorado, for the boundary— <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">Hyde de Neuville</persRef> talked with me more than an
                hour, urging that we should settle our affairs with Spain—flattering and cajoling
                me. It was ten O’Clock before we came home— <persRef ref="pope-nathaniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Pope</persRef> paid
                a visit here this Morning with <persRef ref="clark-william">Governor Clarke</persRef> of the Missouri Territory.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-23">
        <head>23 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-23"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
            <note type="subject">Immigration</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>23. VII:</dateline> At the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef> I found him anxious to receive
               <persRef ref="onis-luis">Onis’s</persRef> reply to my last Note. At the Office <persRef ref="lee-william">W. Lee</persRef> came and told me that he had
                demanded of <persRef ref="galabert-unknown">Galabert</persRef> an explanation of his going in to Onis’s, and received a very
                imperfect one. He had written from Philadelphia to Onis telling him that if he could
                be furnished with the means of coming here, he could make communications which would
                be useful to him— Upon which sent him a hundred dollar Bill— He had therefore come;
                and made his Communication, but would not tell Lee what it was— He said he had asked
                of Onis a Passport to go to Mexico which Onis had not given him; but took it into
                consideration and told him to call again— But Galabert had received a Letter from
                <persRef ref="bonaparte-joseph">Joseph Bonaparte</persRef>, urging him not to enter into the wild and extravagant projects of
                these french fugitives, and offering him the means of settling himself in
                Pennsylvania. This Letter affected him so that Lee said he cried like a child, and
                inclined to return and settle in Pennsylvania— Lee says that he saved Galabert’s
                life at Bordeaux; but that the intriguing ways of a Frenchman are past all finding
                out— <persRef ref="riley-james">Captain Riley</persRef> came also to the Office, and brought me a large bundle of
                accounts and Memoirs from <persRef ref="simpson-j">James Simpson</persRef> the Consul at Tangier to be read. Simpson
                who has been more than twenty years a Consul with a Salary of 2000 dollars a year
                now claims to be allowed 4000 on a final settlement— I received from <persRef key="bagot-charles">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot</persRef> a Note, with a copy of a Letter from the <persRef ref="george-iv">Prince
                Regent</persRef> to the President, announcing the decease of the <persRef ref="charlotte-augustus">Princess Charlotte</persRef>, and
                asking for an Audience of the President to present it— My <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef> took <persRef ref="hellen-mary">Mary Hellen</persRef> with
                her and spent this Evening at her <persRef ref="hellen-adelaide">Sister Hellen’s</persRef>— Much occupation, and a rhumatism
                in the breast confined me at home.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-24">
        <head>24 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-24"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>24. VII:30.</dateline> I rose with a severe rhumatism in the breast, and
                suffered with it the whole day. <persRef ref="holmes-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Holmes</persRef> called this
                morning at my house, to recommend <persRef ref="parris-albion">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> A. K. Parris</persRef> for
                District Judge, in the District of Maine, in the room of judge <persRef ref="sewall-david">David Sewall</persRef> who
                resigns— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Parris himself called on me yesterday at the
                Office to enquire as to the fact of judge Sewall’s resignation— At the Office I had
                again this day a succession of visitors who absorbed all my time till five O’Clock.
                    Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs:</hi> <persRef ref="nelson-jeremiah">Nelson</persRef>, <persRef ref="silsbee-nathaniel">Silsbee</persRef> and <persRef ref="newton-thomas">Newton</persRef> of the House of
                Representatives— <persRef ref="irvine-baptis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> B. Irvine</persRef> who is going as agent to
                Venezuela, and <persRef ref="preble-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Preble</persRef> who has just come home from
                Marseilles to solicit a consular appointment there or elsewhere— My <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef> intended to
                have passed the Evening at<persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean"> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hyde de Neuville’s</persRef>, but
                before we rose from dinner <persRef ref="frye-nathaniel;frye-carolina">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi
                    rend="superscript">rs</hi> Frye</persRef> came in with <persRef ref="buchanan-susan">Susan Buchanan</persRef>, a daughter of <persRef ref="buchanan-andrew">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">rs</hi> Frye’s former husband</persRef> by <persRef ref="buchanan-anne">his first wife</persRef> who was a
                daughter of the late <persRef ref="mckean-thomas">Governor M’Kean</persRef>— They passed the Evening here, and Miss
                Buchanan remains here to pass some weeks with my wife— I suffered very severely;
                with the rhumatism, on going to bed this Night.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-25">
        <head>25 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-25"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>25. VII:</dateline> Still afflicted with the rhumatism, in the breast,
                though not so sharp as it was yesterday. It prevented me from attending Church, but
                I was taken up great part of the day with visitors— <persRef ref="smith-samuel2">General S. Smith</persRef> came to enquire
                what was the state of our affairs and relations with Naples— He asked if there would
                be an objection to a call of Congress upon the Executive for the Papers of that
                Negotiation— I promised to speak of it to the <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef>; <pb type="ms" n="302"/>and
                write to him the result. Smith wants to have his <persRef ref="smith-john2">Son John</persRef> sent to Naples as Charge
                d’Affaires. He also read me part of a Letter from <persRef ref="hughes-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                Hughes</persRef> his daughter at Stockholm and was anxious to know if <persRef ref="russell-jonathan">M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Russell</persRef> was to remain longer than a year at Stockholm— <persRef ref="bailey-john">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Bailey</persRef> came and introduced to me a <persRef ref="varnuns-unknown">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Varnuns</persRef> of this place; and M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Stetson of Dorchester, just arrived from Boston— <persRef ref="porter-peter">General Peter B. Porter</persRef>
                came and introduced M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi><space/> <persRef ref="storrow-samuel">M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Storrow</persRef> was also here. He came with <persRef ref="brown-jacob">General Brown</persRef>, and is now in his
                family— <persRef ref="walsh-robert">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Walsh</persRef> was here, returned two days since from
                Baltimore— And <persRef ref="barker-jacob">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Jacob Barker</persRef> left a card. I walked to
                the Capitol Hill and paid a visit to <persRef ref="otis-harrison;otis-sally">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi
                    rend="superscript">rs</hi> Otis</persRef>— Evening absorbed in writing.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-26">
        <head>26 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-26"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>26. VII:</dateline> Several Morning visitors at the house. <persRef ref="holmes-john">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Holmes</persRef> with <persRef ref="vanness-cornelius">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Van-Ness</persRef>
                the Commissioner under the fifth Article of the Treaty of Ghent— <persRef ref="talcott-unknown">Captain Talcott</persRef> who
                brought me a letter of introduction from <persRef ref="dearborn-henry">General H. Dearborn</persRef>, and who comes upon
                some question concerning his rank— <persRef ref="cranch-william">Judge Cranch</persRef> with a <persRef ref="goddard-s">M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Goddard</persRef>, son in Law of <persRef ref="dawes-thomas">Judge T. Dawes</persRef>, but now residing at Alexandria,
                and a solicitor for employment as a Clerk in the Post-Office, or some other of the
                public Offices. Soon after twelve I rode to the <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef>’s and at One, presented to
                him <persRef key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot</persRef>, who delivered to him a Letter from the
                <persRef ref="george-iv">Prince-Regent of England</persRef>, announcing the death of the <persRef ref="charlotte-augustus">Princess Charlotte</persRef>— M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot said he wished to have some conversation with
                me, and I appointed to-morrow at one O’Clock to see him at the Office. He also
                enquired if we should be ready for the fishery proposition to go by the February
                Packet— At the Office, <persRef ref="cardelli-pietro">Cardelli</persRef> came to complain that <persRef ref="lane-samuel">Col<hi rend="superscript"
                    >l.</hi> Lane</persRef>, the Commissioner of the public buildings would no longer employ
                him upon the Capitol, and to ask for my influence in his favour, but that is nothing
                at all— <persRef ref="riley-james">Captain Riley</persRef> came again about <persRef ref="simpson-j">J. Simpson’s</persRef> Accounts, and said he would
                present a Memorial for him to Congress— He had also much to say against <persRef ref="sullivan-a">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> A. Sullivan</persRef>, the present Consul at Mogadore— I passed
                the Evening with my <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef> at <persRef ref="tayloe-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Tayloe’s</persRef> It was a Ball,
                on the Marriage of <persRef ref="tayloe-benjamin">his Son</persRef>— We came home between ten and eleven— I left Cards this
                Morning at <persRef ref="brown-jacob">General Brown’s</persRef> lodgings and was introduced to him this Evening at M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Tayloe’s.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-27">
        <head>27 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-27"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
            <note type="subject">Commerce</note>
            <note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
            <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
            <note type="subject">South American Wars of Independence</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>27. VII:</dateline> <persRef key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot</persRef> came to my Office,
                according to appointment at one O’Clock, and by order of his Government made an
                offer of their mediation to settle the differences between the United States and
                Spain— This offer was accompanied with many professions of a friendly disposition
                towards the United States, and many intimations of no good harmony subsisting
                between Great-Britain and Spain— He read to me an extract from a despatch from <persRef ref="castlereagh-robert">Lord
                Castlereagh</persRef> to him, referring to his conferences with me before I left England— To
                his belief that he had convinced me of the frankness and candour with which he had
                disclosed to me the whole Policy of the British Government at this time, and that it
                was bent upon nothing so earnestly as upon the preservation of universal Peace— That
                he had derived great satisfaction from the assurances given him by me of the same
                disposition, on the part of the American Government, and on my own part personally—
                With many flattering compliments to me which Bagot after reading to me, said he
                believed he ought not to have done so— He also read to me in confidence a copy of a
                despatch from Lord Castlereagh to <persRef ref="wellesley-henry">Sir Henry Wellesley</persRef> the British Ambassador at
                Madrid, dated 27. August last, and being an answer to a despatch from him with which
                a Note from <persRef ref="pizarro-joseph">Pizarro</persRef> the Spanish Minister of foreign affairs asking for this
                mediation of G.B. had been forwarded—and Pizarro had made an extended Statement of
                the subjects of dispute between Spain and U.S— Castlereagh answers that before the
                <persRef ref="george-iv">Prince Regent</persRef> could definitively answer this proposal, he must know much more of the
                subject than he could from Pizarro’s statement, however extended, and also that the
                mediation was desired by both parties— At the same time he complains in very angry
                terms of certain restrictions upon the British Commerce in Spain, and hints that
                unless they are removed England will not act as a Mediator between Spain and U.S.
                This Letter M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot allowed me in confidence to take
                and shew to the <persRef key="monroe-james">President</persRef>, on condition that it should not be otherwise used— At the
                same time he read me another part of his despatch, relating to South America,
                explicitly declaring that if Great-Britain alone, or the allied powers jointly
                should interpose between Spain and the South American Provinces, the system
                recommended and urged by Great-Britain would be one of perfect liberality to the
                Provinces—a System which would open their ports and their commerce to all Nations,
                including the United States, and in which Great-Britain would neither ask nor accept
                any exclusive privilege for herself—and adding that this subject was now in
                negotiation among the allied powers— I told M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot,
                that I must of course refer <pb type="ms" n="303"/>the subject to the consideration
                of the President; who I was sure would receive the communication as a proof of a
                friendly disposition in Great-Britain— I desired him to thank Lord Castlereagh for
                the kindness and confidence in me expressed in his despatch, and with the full
                promise of my hearty concurrence in the good work of preserving universal Peace— As
                to the mediation, the only objection I could anticipate to it was that G.B. had
                heretofore taken some part with Spain, on the very points now in controversy— He
                said that whatever may have been the feelings or policy of the British Government,
                under different circumstances and at another period, if she should now assume the
                character of a Mediator it would be with perfect impartiality, and solely with a
                view to conciliate the parties to each other— Abstractedly speaking it might be more
                agreeable to G.B. to have a weak neighbour than a strong one; but she must
                accommodate her policy to the nature of things; and she was sincerely desirous of
                maintaining the best understanding with this Country. He had told <persRef ref="onis-luis">Onis</persRef> the Spanish
                Minister yesterday that if the interposition of Great-Britain should be desired by
                this Country, he must not expect that she would support Spain in any extravagant
                pretensions. He also told him that he should make this communication to me this day.
                Bagot also told me, that <persRef ref="macgregor-gregor">M’Gregor</persRef> had when he was here, called upon him, and told
                him that <persRef ref="thornton-william">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thornton</persRef> had sent him— He told him that he
                was going to take Florida and asked him what the opinion of the British Government
                upon it would be. Bagot told him he could give him no answer to that question and
                could say nothing about it. Bagot afterwards asked Thornton if he really had sent
                M’Gregor to him; and he admitted that he had— After Bagot left me, I called at the
                President’s but he was not at home— I came home to dinner at four, and we had a
                Tea-party and Ball, to which about three hundred persons were invited, and more than
                two hundred attended. The company began to come between six and seven and left us
                about Midnight— The Evening was excessively dark and several accidents happened to
                persons on coming and returning.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-28">
        <head>28 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-28"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Adams Family Finances</note>
            <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>28. VII:</dateline> Rainy day— At the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef>, met <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi
                rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford</persRef>. The despatch from <persRef ref="castlereagh-robert">Lord Castlereagh</persRef> to <persRef ref="wellesley-henry">Sir
                Henry Wellesley</persRef> was read, and the communication from <persRef key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                Bagot</persRef> to me concerning a British Mediation, discussed. Crawford said it was a
                maladdress of Bagot to shew me that Letter of Castlereagh’s. The President and he
                were evidently averse to the acceptance of the Mediation— The President directed the
                translation of <persRef ref="onis-luis">Onis’s</persRef> Note to be sent to the other heads of Departments and
                appointed the day after-to-morrow at Noon, for a Cabinet Meeting and consultation
                upon the whole subject. <persRef ref="pope-nathaniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> N. Pope</persRef> called at the Office,
                and I had much conversation with him on various topics— I met <persRef ref="davidson-john">Captain J. Davidson</persRef>,
                and asked him to come to me to-morrow upon certain business that I wished to have
                transacted, and in which my private affairs will suffer severely, from my having
                been too much engaged with public business to transact it before— The day and
                Evening were so bad that we did not attend the drawing Room, to the great
                disappointment of <persRef ref="buchanan-susan">Susan Buchanan</persRef>.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-29">
        <head>29 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-29"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Adams Family Finances</note>
            <note type="subject">Adams Family Residences</note>
            <note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>29. VII:</dateline> Met <persRef ref="crowninshield-benjamin">Crowninshield</persRef> this Morning at the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef>. <persRef ref="silsbee-mary">M<hi
                rend="superscript">rs</hi> Silsbee</persRef> was overset in her Carriage, returning from
                our house, and was much hurt by a bruise in the head— <persRef ref="north-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                North</persRef> also who walked home to avoid an accident, pitched over the bridge into the
                Tyber, and dislocated his shoulder. <persRef ref="davidson-john">Davidson</persRef> came to the Office, and I executed a
                Power of Attorney to <persRef ref="mceuen-thomas">M’Ewen</persRef>, <persRef ref="hale-thomas">Hale</persRef> and <persRef ref="davidson-william">Davidson</persRef> of Philadelphia, which I am to give
                him to-morrow. He told me that upon enquiry he had found the objection that I had
                made to the validity of his title to the house and land in F. Street that I had
                engaged to purchase of him, was insuperable; but he had written to England to get
                such additional security to his title as would be obtainable— I told him that our
                bargain was of course at an end, to which he agreed. <persRef ref="bayard-samuel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                S. Bayard</persRef> came also upon the subject of the American Bible Society, and asked me for
                a small Subscription to it— I told him I had already sent it to <persRef ref="romeyn-john">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Romeyn</persRef>, with the answer to his Letter announcing my
                election, as one of the Members of the Society. He gave me his book to subscribe my
                name for the amount which I did. <persRef ref="porter-peter">General P. B. Porter</persRef> came again to the Office about
                his Accounts. In the Evening I wrote a couple of pages of general remarks on a
                subject of great public interest.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-30">
        <head>30 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-30"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Adams Family Finances</note>
            <note type="subject">Adams Family Residences</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>30. VII.</dateline> When I went this Morning to the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef>,
                    <persRef ref="middleton-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Middleton</persRef> of South Carolina was with him; but
                after a few minutes went away. I gave him the Letter last received from <persRef ref="collins-charles">C. Collins</persRef>
                concerning <persRef ref="macgregor-gregor">M’Gregor</persRef> and his expectation. <pb type="ms" n="304"/><persRef ref="davidson-john">M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Davidson</persRef> came again to the Office— I gave him the
                power of Attorney, and the Certificate; and he told me that he had received Letters
                from Philadelphia, from which it appears I have taken my measure too late— I must
                take the consequences. Davidson enquired also what the state of his house and land
                in F. Street is, conformably to the Laws of Maryland— I found the Statute relating
                to Descents and read to him the provision applying to his property— My <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">wife</persRef> passed
                the Evening with <persRef ref="buchanan-susan">Susan Buchanan</persRef> at <persRef ref="pleasonton-stephen">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Pleasonton’s</persRef>— I
                was at home, preparing instructions for <persRef ref="irvine-baptis">B. Irvine</persRef> going as agent to Venezuela.</p>

        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-31">
        <head>31 January 1818</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-31"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
            <note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
            <note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
            <note type="subject">South American Wars of Independence</note>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">

            <p><dateline>31. VI:45.</dateline> <persRef ref="taylor-waller">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> W. Taylor</persRef> paid us a
                visit this morning at my house— There was a full cabinet meeting at the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef>;
                on the question what answers shall be given to <persRef key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                Bagot’s</persRef> proposal and to <persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis’s</persRef> last Note; in
                connection with which were considered the question of South American Independence,
                and the transactions at Amelia-Island. The Sentiment against accepting the Mediation
                was unanimous; but more earnest in all the others than in me— I had doubts whether
                we should ultimately be able to avoid European interference in this affair, and
                therefore whether we ought now absolutely to decline that of Great-Britain— The
                determination however was positive to decline; and the only question was upon what
                grounds we should decline. The President and <persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford</persRef>
                suggested the ground that our differences with Spain were not such as to threaten a
                War. They were of little comparative consequence; and we had no intention to push
                them to a War. But <persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun</persRef> remarked, that if we
                should take this ground, and Spain should be very urgent for the mediation; it would
                be a temptation to her to commit some act of hostility to make the mediation
                necessary— The President and M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford also inclined,
                while rejecting the Mediation to make a statement to the British Government of the
                merits of our case, in answer to that sent them by <persRef ref="pizarro-joseph">Pizarro</persRef>— I objected that if we
                gave any statement of the merits it would give a plausible pretext to the British to
                reply and go deeper into the case. I suggested the idea of answering with thanks for
                the friendly manifestations of G.B. and the strongest assurances of their being
                reciprocated, that we were obliged to accommodate our measures to the public
                feelings of the Country— That our controversies with Spain though not of the first
                rank in importance had a strong hold upon the popular sentiments—that to refer them
                to any interposition of a third party would certainly be disapproved by all parties
                in this Country, and have the tendency to create ill-will between this Country and
                England, which we were very desirous of avoiding— This was agreed upon as the
                principle to be assumed for declining, and the President desired me to make a minute
                in writing to be shewn him on Monday, of the substance of what should be said to
                    M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot— It was also agreed that the next reply to
                    M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis, must be longer and more particular than the
                last— It was four when the meeting broke up. I was an hour at the Office, and got
                home little before six. <persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</persRef> and <persRef ref="buchanan-susan">Susan Buchanan</persRef>
                spent the Evening at <persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hyde de Neuville’s</persRef>— Snow, all
                day.</p>
        </div>
    </div>

    <div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v30-1818-01-xx">
        <head>Day</head>
        <bibl>
            <author>JQA</author>
            <date type="creation" when="1818-01-xx"/>
            <editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
        </bibl>

        <div type="docbody">
            <!-- This is a summary entry without a date.-->

            <p><dateline rend="italic">Day.</dateline> I now seldom rise before seven— Write till ten—
                Breakfast— Walk to the <persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</persRef>. Am one or two hours with him; usually
                interrupted two or three times by lounging visits to him, from Members of Congress.
                Go to my Office about one. Engaged there commonly till five— Walk home— Dine at six—
                At home reading newspapers and writing from seven till eleven or twelve. I make late
                Evening’s because my apartment is then warm; but in the morning is so cold that the
                first hour or two I cannot write.</p>

        </div>
    </div>
</div>
