<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.masshist.org/publications/pub/schema/djqa-prep-2016.rng" type="xml"?>
        <?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="DJQA-authorViewMaybe.css"?>
<div type="month" mhs:volume="31" mhs:startingOnPage="024" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mhs="http://www.masshist.org/ns/1.0">
	<bibl n="metadata">
		<date from="1819-02-01" to="1819-02-28"/>
	</bibl>
	<!-- D/JQA/31.94 -->
	<!-- February 1819 -->
	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-01">
		<head>1 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-01"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Science and Technology</note>
			<note type="subject">Treaty of Ghent</note>
			<note type="subject">West, The</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">
			<dateline type="heading">February 1819</dateline>
			<p><dateline>1. Monday. V:</dateline> Call upon the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President</mhs:persRef> and had a
				conversation with him upon this renewal of Negotiation, with the <mhs:persRef ref="onis-luis">Spanish Minister</mhs:persRef>—
				There are various symptoms that if we do come to an arrangement there will be a
				large party in the Country, dissatisfied, with our concessions from the Rio del
				Norte to the Sabine, or the gulph of Mexico— <mhs:persRef key="clay-henry">Clay</mhs:persRef>, has taken the alarm, at hearing
				that Onis was again treating with us, and is already taking ground, to censure the
				Treaty, if one should be made— He told me last week at <mhs:persRef key="crawford-william-harris">Crawford’s</mhs:persRef> that he thought we
				were offering too much for Florida, and he enclosed me yesterday a Letter to
				himself, from a person at Lexington Kentucky and hinted at a different opinion from
				ours respecting the Western Boundary. I received a long and impertinent Letter from
				Lexington, making many objections to the line which we have proposed and I mentioned
				all this to the President for his Consideration. He desired me to see and converse
				with <mhs:persRef ref="jackson-andrew">Gen<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> Jackson</mhs:persRef>, upon the subject, and to ask
				confidentially his opinion— At the Office I had visits from <mhs:persRef ref="vanness-cornelius">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Van Ness</mhs:persRef> the Commissioner under the 5<hi rend="superscript">th.
				</hi>Article of the Treaty of Ghent; from <mhs:persRef ref="petry-jean">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Petry</mhs:persRef> the
				French Consul at Philadelphia and from <mhs:persRef ref="stith-townshend">Captain Stith</mhs:persRef>, who came for an answer, upon
				his application for the appointment of Consul at Tunis. I was not able to give it to
				him, though <mhs:persRef ref="lewis-unknown">Commodore Lewis</mhs:persRef> had declined the appointment, and solicits that <pb
					type="ms" n="25"/>of Consul General at Algiers, in the room of <mhs:persRef ref="shaler-william">William Shaler</mhs:persRef>,
				who is expected to come home. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Van Ness came to inform
				me that he should leave the City in a few days, and spoke again concerning the
				Salary of <mhs:persRef ref="hassler-ferdinand">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hassler</mhs:persRef>, the Astronomer to the Commission.
				He thinks it should be something more than that of the Astronomer to the other
				Commission, <mhs:persRef ref="adams-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Adams</mhs:persRef>, the duties to be performed by
				Hassler being more laborious. But Hassler claims the same Salary and charges that he
				received for surveying the Coast, under a Law, the part of which authorising the
				employment of him, was at the last Session of Congress repealed, barely on account
				of the expense which it occasioned— Petry is here on a visit at the <mhs:persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">French
				Minister’s</mhs:persRef>. <mhs:persRef ref="thornton-william">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thornton</mhs:persRef> came also, for his papers. He is
				very urgent to obtain from Congress an increase of his Salary, and teazes me as he
				has teazed all my predecessors to ask it of Congress for him— I gave him his papers,
				and added my certificate to that of <mhs:persRef key="rush-richard">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Rush</mhs:persRef>, concurring
				with him in opinion that the Salary is inadequate to the duties of the Office. We
				had company to dine, <mhs:persRef ref="calhoun-john;calhoun-floride">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript"
					>rs</hi> Calhoun</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef key="clay-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Clay</mhs:persRef>, and <mhs:persRef ref="middleton-henry;middleton-mary">M<hi
						rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Middleton</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="strother-george;strother-theodosia">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Strother</mhs:persRef>, Mess<hi
					rend="superscript">rs.</hi> <mhs:persRef key="crawford-william-harris">Crawford</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="graham-john">John</mhs:persRef> and <mhs:persRef ref="graham-george">George Graham</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="johnson-richard">R. M. Johnson</mhs:persRef>,
				<mhs:persRef ref="colston-edward">Colston</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="lincoln-enoch">Lincoln</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="robertson-george">Robertson</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="terrell-william">Tarrell</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="trimble-david">Trimble</mhs:persRef> and <mhs:persRef ref="vandyke-nicholas">Van Dyke</mhs:persRef>. <mhs:persRef ref="crawford-susanna">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>rs</hi> Crawford</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="graham-susan">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> John Graham</mhs:persRef>, and <mhs:persRef ref="vandyke-mary">M<hi
					rend="superscript">rs</hi> Van Dyke</mhs:persRef> were invited, but sent excuses. <mhs:persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi
					rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</mhs:persRef> was again obliged to keep her bed almost the
				whole day, and could not receive the company— While at dinner I received a note from
				the French Minister asking when I could see him; I sent him word at two O’Clock to
				morrow at the Office.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-02">
		<head>2 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-02"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Native Americans</note>
			<note type="subject">Science and Technology</note>
			<note type="subject">Seminole Wars</note>
			<note type="subject">West, The</note>
			<note type="subject">Westward Exploration and Expansion/Westward Migration/Manifest Destiny</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>2. VII:</dateline> Col<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> <mhs:persRef ref="johnson-richard">R. M. Johnson</mhs:persRef> had
				promised to call upon me this Morning at ten, but I expected him at my house, and he
				went to the Office. I did not see him; but sent him the books to which he had
				referred in his speech on the Seminole War. <mhs:persRef ref="martens-georg">Martens</mhs:persRef>, the annual Register for 1780,
				and the Laws, authorizing the President to call out the Militia against the Indians.
				I called on <mhs:persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General Jackson</mhs:persRef>, and mentioned in confidence to him the State of the
				Negotiation with the Spanish Minister; and what we had offered him for the Western
				Boundary; and asked his opinion of it. He thought the friends of the administration
				would be satisfied with it; but that their adversaries would censure it severely and
				make occasion for opposition from it— He thought even that it would bring us again
				in collision with the Indians whom we are removing West of the Mississippi. But as
				we had no map at hand, I could not give him a precise idea of the proposed line by
				mere description, and he promised to call at my house to-morrow Morning at ten, and
				look it over upon the Map— At the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</mhs:persRef>— I received from <mhs:persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</mhs:persRef> a Note Yesterday, proposing a line approaching
				considerably towards that which has been offered by us. I told the President of the
				Letter signed <mhs:persRef ref="franklin">Franklin</mhs:persRef> which I have received, dated Lexington, Kentucky; of the
				preparation making, and sufficiently notified by <mhs:persRef key="clay-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Clay</mhs:persRef>, to take ground against the Western boundary offered by us to Spain; and what
				General Jackson had said to me— The President observed that while our differences
				with Spain should remain unadjusted, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Clay would seize
				every incident arising from them to assail the Administration— If adjusted, he would
				use the adjustment itself for the same purpose— But the possession of the Florida’s,
				with a clear and undisputed title, the acquisition of indemnity for the long
				standing claims of our Citizens upon Spain; and a recognized title extending to the
				South Sea, would be such advantages to this Country that he believed any opposition
				founded upon our consent to take the Sabine for the Western boundary would have
				little weight with the People. At the Office, <mhs:persRef ref="forbes-john">Forbes</mhs:persRef> came to renew his solicitations
				for some appointment, and left with me his resignation of the Office of Consul
				General in Denmark. <mhs:persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hyde de Neuville</mhs:persRef> came at three—
				And I told him that he could now see M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis, and inform
				him of the extent to which we would go for the Western Boundary; that we cannot
				yield an inch further, and wish only to be informed whether he will agree to it, or
				not. That if he does, in point of form the proposition may be made by us and
				accepted by him; or made by him and accepted by us, as would be most agreeable to
				himself. De Neuville, hinged most upon the line to the South Sea; and said Onis was
				très recalcitrant upon that point. But he promised to see him and bring me his
				answer to-morrow— A Frenchman by the name of <mhs:persRef ref="lintroy-unknown">Lintroy</mhs:persRef>, came this Evening, with an
				invention for taking grease-spots out of woollen and Silk; for which he has many
				certificates, and wishes to obtain the signature of the President, and mine. He is
				to call again at ten O’Clock the day after to-morrow Morning— <mhs:persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi
					rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</mhs:persRef> is better— <mhs:persRef ref="buchanan-mary">Mary Buchanan</mhs:persRef> dined abroad.</p>
		</div>
	</div>
	
	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-03">
		<head>3 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-03"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Elections, Presidential (1820)</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Native Americans</note>
			<note type="subject">Seminole Wars</note>
			<note type="subject">U.S. Constitution</note>
			<note type="subject">War of 1812</note>
			<note type="subject">West, The</note>
		</bibl>
		
		<div type="docbody">
			
			<p><pb type="ms" n="26"/><dateline>3. VI:</dateline> <mhs:persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General Jackson</mhs:persRef> came to my house this morning, and I
				shewed him the boundary line which has been offered to the <mhs:persRef ref="onis-luis">Spanish Minister</mhs:persRef>, and
				that which we propose to offer, upon <mhs:persRef ref="melish-john">Melish’s</mhs:persRef> Map. He said, there were many
				individuals who would take exception to our receding so far from the Boundary of the
				Rio del Norte which we claim, as the Sabine, and the enemies of the Administration
				would certainly make a handle of it to assail them; but the possession of the
				Florida’s, was of so great importance to the Southern frontier of the United States,
				and so essential even to their safety, that the vast majority of the Nation would be
				satisfied, with the Western boundary, as we propose, if we obtain the Florida’s. He
				shewed me on the map the operations of the British force during the late war; and
				remarked that while the Mouths of the Florida Rivers should be accessible to a
				foreign Naval force there would be no security for the Southern part of the United
				States— He also entered into Conversation, upon the subject of the discussion now
				pending in the House of Representatives, on his proceedings in the late Seminole
				War; upon that which is preparing in the Senate, under the auspices of <mhs:persRef ref="forsyth-john">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth</mhs:persRef> of Georgia, and upon the general order, given
				by Jackson in 1817. which was considered as setting at defiance the War Department.
				He imputed the whole to <mhs:persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi rend="superscript">r </hi>Crawford’s</mhs:persRef> resentments
				against him, on account of his having at the last Presidential Election supported
					<mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Monroe</mhs:persRef> against him— Said there was not a single
				Officer in the army known to have been at that time in favour of Monroe, whom
				Crawford had not since insulted— That M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Monroe was of
				an open, fair unsuspecting character; amiable in the highest degree; and would not
				believe human nature capable of the baseness which Crawford, while holding a
				confidential office under him was practising against him— I told Jackson, that M<hi
					rend="superscript">r.</hi> Crawford had never in any of the discussions on the
				Seminole War, said a word which led me to suppose he had any hostile feeling against
				him— He replied that however that might be, Crawford was now setting the whole
				delegation of Georgia against him; and by intentional insult, and the grossest
				violation of all military principle had compelled him to issue the order of 1817.
				Crawford, he said, was a man restrained by no principle, and capable of any
				baseness— The first act that brought him into notice, was a conspiracy between him
				as a lawyer, and <mhs:persRef ref="tait-charles">Tait</mhs:persRef> the <hi rend="strikethrough">late</hi> Senator form Georgia,
				taking clandestinely a false affidavit, charging a <mhs:persRef ref="clarke-john">General George Clarke</mhs:persRef>, as a
				speculator in the Yazoo Lands, while a member of the Georgia Legislature— Clarke
				proved the falsehood of the charge— challenged Crawford and broke his arm, and wore
				out a cow-hide on Tait’s back— Crawford was now canvassing for the next Presidential
				election, and actually wrote a Letter to <mhs:persRef key="clay-henry">Clay</mhs:persRef>, proposing a coalition with him to
				overthrow M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Monroe’s administration. M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Clay had declared in a public speech that he would not
				make any systematic opposition to this administration—but he certainly had received
				such a Letter from Crawford; for a person of high standing here at Washington, had
				told him Jackson since he has been now here, that he had seen it— And whenever
				Crawford’s name shall be brought forward as a Candidate for the Presidency, the
				whole transaction should be unveiled to the public— It would not be worthwhile to
				disclose it now— As to Forsyth, what motive he could have for his present conduct,
				other than that of subserviency to Crawford, he could not imagine— But he carried
				his inveteracy to such lengths that he was to make it a new charge against Jackson,
				that in the late campaign, he had accepted the aid of mounted Volunteers, instead of
				Militia; and yesterday his Committee had sent for <mhs:persRef ref="call-unknown">Captain Call</mhs:persRef> and examines him to
				make out a charge that he, Jackson had speculated in a purchase of lands at
				Pensacola, which was utterly false— A man of his name (no relation of his, for he
				had not a relation in the world,) an irishman, had gone from Nashville, and made
				some speculation in lands at Pensacola, but in which he himself had no interest or
				concern. The bitterness with which Forsyth is pursuing this attack upon Jackson has
				become notorious, and the more extraordinary, as Forsyth has already been notified
				that he will be nominated as Minister to Spain, before the close of the Session of
				Congress— That Crawford has written such a Letter to Clay as Jackson has been
				informed is to the last degree improbable; he has too much discretion to have put
				himself so much in Clay’s power. But that all his conduct is governed by his views
				to the Presidency as the immediate successor to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Monroe, and that his hopes depend upon a result unfavourable to the success, or at
				least to the popularity of the administration is perfectly clear— The important and
				critical interests of the Country, are those the management of which belongs to the
				Department of State— Those incidental to the Treasury are in a state which would
				give an able financier an opportunity to display his talents, but Crawford has no
				talents as a financier. He is just and barely equal to the current routine of the
				business of his Office— His talent is intrigue— And as it is in the foreign Affairs
				that the success or failure of the Administration will be most conspicuous, and as
				their success would promote the reputation and influence, and their failure would
				lead to the disgrace of the Secretary of State, Crawford’s <pb type="ms" n="27"
				/>personal views centre in the ill success of the Administration, in its foreign
				Relations, and perhaps unconscious of his own motives, he will always be impelled to
				throw obstacles in its way, and to bring upon the Department of State especially,
				any feeling of public dissatisfaction that he can— I have felt this even in the
				Negotiation of the late Convention with Great-Britain; in the course of which he
				took ground of disapprobation, of which he certainly would have made a handle if the
				negotiation had terminated unsuccessfully; and of which I have no doubt he avails
				himself as it is, in his private Conversations, to hint that the success might have
				been greater. I feel him continually in the Negotiation with Spain, and in the
				transactions with <mhs:persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">Hyde de Neuville</mhs:persRef>, and always in the way of increasing
				difficulties— Crawford is not a worse man, than the usual herd of ambitious
				intriguers. Perhaps not so bad as many of them— I do not think him entirely
				unprincipled; but his ambition swallows up his principle. His position is a bad one—
				Having been a caucus Candidate for the Presidency, against M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Monroe, he feels as if his very existence was staked upon his being his
				successor— And although himself a member of the Administration, he perceives every
				day more clearly, that his only prospect of success hereafter depends upon the
				failure of the Administration, by measures, of which he must take care to make known
				his disapprobation— This forced and unnatural position is one of the numerous evils,
				consequent upon the practice which has grown up under this Constitution, but
				contrary to its Spirit, by which the members of Congress meet in Caucus, and
				determine by a majority upon the Candidate for the Presidency to be supported by the
				whole Meeting. A practice which places the President in a state of undue
				subserviency to the members of the Legislature; and which connected with the other
				practice of re-electing only once the same President, leads to a thousand corrupt
				cabals between the Members of Congress and the Heads of the Departments, who are
				thus almost necessarily made rival pretenders to the succession. The only possible
				chance for a Head of Department to attain the Presidency, is by ingratiating himself
				personally with the Members of Congress, and as many of them have objects of their
				own to obtain, the temptation is immense to corrupt coalitions, and tends to make
				all the public offices objects of bargain and sale— That there has been intercourse
				of this kind, more or less explicit between Crawford and Clay can scarcely be
				doubted— But a Coalition between them would be liable to many difficulties. They are
				both native Virginians— Clay’s ambition has been so pampered by success, that he has
				evidently formed hopes of coming in as the immediate successor of M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Monroe. He refused both the War Department, and the
				Mission to England. Last winter he aimed at the unlimited controul of the House of
				Representatives, and at the formation of a Western party. His prospect of coalition
				then was with <mhs:persRef ref="clinton-dewitt">Governor Clinton</mhs:persRef>; and it was positively, but I think erroneously said
				to have been effected. I has this winter much more the appearance of being concluded
				with Crawford; but the Georgian attack upon Jackson has scarcely any support from
				the West, though an immense effort has been made to engage Virginia, in the cause;
				and with partial success. Clay’s opposition has hitherto been so unsuccessful, that
				he sees I believe the necessity of contenting himself with a secondary Station under
				the next Presidency; and this may bring him back to a coalition with Crawford or
				Clinton, as the chances may arise— His opposition to Jackson now is involuntary and
				merely counteractive. At the Office, I had successively as visitors, <mhs:persRef ref="verplanck-gulian">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Verplanck</mhs:persRef>, who came to urge the removal of <mhs:persRef ref="fisk-jonathan">Fiske</mhs:persRef>, the
				District Attorney at New-York, for habitual intemperance, and the appointment of <mhs:persRef ref="hoffman-josiah">J.
				O. Hoffman</mhs:persRef> a federalist as his successor— <mhs:persRef ref="edwards-ninian">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Edwards</mhs:persRef>,
				Senator from Illinois concerning the appointment of a District Attorney and Marshal
				for that State, which he wished to have postponed— He apologized for shewing me a
				Letter from <mhs:persRef ref="grundy-felix">Felix Grundy</mhs:persRef>, now of Tennessee, and sometime a member of Congress from
				that State, but formerly an inhabitant of Kentucky, and rival of Clay. Edwards had
				written to him to urge him to come into Congress again; but he apparently declines.
				Edwards says that he himself shall not come as a Senator again. <mhs:persRef ref="woodside-john">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Woodsides</mhs:persRef> came to press me for a Report, in <mhs:persRef ref="cathcart-james">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r </hi>Cathcart’s</mhs:persRef> case— <mhs:persRef ref="mitchell-david">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Mitchell</mhs:persRef> for some new provision to a Bill now before Congress relating to the
				Seaman’s fund. <mhs:persRef ref="bourqueney-francois">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bourqueney</mhs:persRef>, Secretary to the French
				Legation, brought me a long Note, in English, from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> De
				Neuville, upon the present Negotiation with Spain; and said M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> De Neuville himself would call upon me to morrow. I received a Note from
					<mhs:persRef key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot</mhs:persRef> asking an Audience of <pb type="ms" n="28"
				/>the President, to present a Letter from the <mhs:persRef ref="george-iv">British Prince Regent</mhs:persRef>, announcing the
				demise of the <mhs:persRef ref="charlotte2">Queen</mhs:persRef>. The President fixed one O’Clock to-morrow for receiving him.
				The President also asked me this Morning whether I thought there would be any
				impropriety in General Jackson’s attending this Evening at the Drawing-Room. I said
				surely not. He has declined receiving any public attentions, while motions of
				censure upon his conduct are in discussion before Congress; but his attendance at
				the Drawing-Room is a mark of Respect for him, which the President not having
				censured him, has no reason for declining— Jackson did attend the Drawing Room,
				which was more crowded than any former one this Winter; and from the earnestness
				with which the company pressed round him, the eagerness with which multitudes pushed
				to obtain personal introductions to him, and the eye of respect and gratitude which
				from every quarter beamed upon him, it had as much the appearance of being his
				drawing-Room as the President’s.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-04">
		<head>4 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-04"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">West, The</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>4. VII:30.</dateline> Just before One O’Clock I attended at the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">Presidents</mhs:persRef>,
				to present <mhs:persRef key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot</mhs:persRef>— The President had forgotten the
				appointment, but was ready in time— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot came
				punctually and delivered the Letter from the <mhs:persRef ref="george-iv">Prince Regent</mhs:persRef> announcing the death of
				<mhs:persRef ref="charlotte2">the Queen of England</mhs:persRef>, on the 17<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>of November— He also
				told the President of the leave of absence that he had obtained and of his intention
				to embark about the beginning of April, in a frigate which he expected would come to
				Annapolis to take him— After he was gone I read the Note in English which I received
				yesterday from <mhs:persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">the French Minister</mhs:persRef>. This proposes that we should take for the
				Western Boundary with Spain, the course of the red River to the 100<hi
					rend="superscript">th. </hi>degree of Longitude from London, then a line North
				to the Arkansas then to the source of that river, thence to the Multnomah, following
				its course to Latitude 43. and on that parallel of Latitude to the South Sea. The
				President was much inclined to accept this line; but I think it would not be
				acceptable to the Nation, and that if <mhs:persRef ref="onis-luis">Onis</mhs:persRef> intends to conclude at all we can obtain
				better— I returned to the Office, and M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> De Neuville
				soon after came there— I discussed with him the substance of his Note; told him how
				exceedingly anxious the President was to accomplish an arrangement with Spain; but
				that we gave up the boundary on one side, Spain must give up on the other— After
				much conversation we were unable to meet on the proposed line; but De Neuville
				intimated that he was persuaded M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis and should
				agree. The misfortune is that upon this as well as other subjects the other Members
				of the Administration and Members of Congress talk freely both with De Neuville and
				Onis, who gather from them a knowledge how far they may urge pretensions, and how
				far we shall be prevailed upon to concede— <mhs:persRef ref="frye-nathaniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Frye</mhs:persRef> spent
				part of the Evening with us, and afterwards <mhs:persRef ref="bailey-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bailey</mhs:persRef>
				called with young <mhs:persRef ref="gerry-james">Gerry</mhs:persRef>, second Son of <mhs:persRef ref="gerry-elbridge">the late Vice President</mhs:persRef> a Midshipman in the
				Navy, just returned from the Mediterranean— He goes to-morrow for Boston.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-05">
		<head>5 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-05"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Seminole Wars</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>5. VI:</dateline> At ten this Morning, I attended a meeting of the
				Commissioners of the sinking fund, which was held in the Office of the <mhs:persRef ref="cutts-charles">Secretary of
				the Senate</mhs:persRef>. <mhs:persRef ref="tompkins-daniel">Vice President Tompkins</mhs:persRef>, the Secretary of Treasury, <mhs:persRef key="crawford-william-harris">Crawford</mhs:persRef>, and
				<mhs:persRef ref="wirt-william">Attorney General Wirt</mhs:persRef> were present, but not the <mhs:persRef ref="marshall-john">Chief Justice</mhs:persRef>— M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford had prepared the annual Report to both Houses
				of Congress, which was read and signed— The Meeting was over in half an hour.
				Tompkins told a Story, of a Justice of Peace in the State of New-York who for ten
				years together was in the constant practice of swearing witnesses, and certifying
				that he had sworn them, that they were neither interested nor disinterested in the
				event of the suit upon which they testified—meaning that they were neither directly
				nor indirectly interested— Upon which Crawford told of a man in the State of
				Georgia, who had two Sons, with whom he was dissatisfied, and upon being told that a
				certain Cause in Court was to be referred to two indifferent men, said it ought then
				to be referred to his two sons, for they were two of the d——dest indifferent men in
				the State. After the Meeting was over, I went into the Senate Chamber, and hear
				their debates for about an hour. They were upon certain private claims. I had some
				conversation with <mhs:persRef ref="king-rufus">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> King</mhs:persRef>, upon <mhs:persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General Jackson’s</mhs:persRef> case.
				King is on the Committee of which <mhs:persRef ref="forsyth-john">Forsyth</mhs:persRef> is chairman and which it is apprehended
				will make a report unfavourable to Jackson. He says that Forsyth is the most
				inveterate &amp; malignant against Jackson, of any man he has seen. He is also well
				acquainted with all the cabaling and electioneering passions and practices that are
				mingled up with this affair, and says if the subject does come before the Senate he
				will expose some of them. From the Senate, I went into the House of Representatives,
				where they were in Committee of the whole upon the Resolutions for censuring
				Jackson’s proceedings in Florida— <mhs:persRef ref="harrison-william">General Harrison</mhs:persRef> of Ohio was speaking, and soon
				concluded— He was followed by <mhs:persRef ref="baldwin-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Baldwin</mhs:persRef> whom I heard
				for about an hour, in favour of Jackson. I left him speaking— It was thus near three
				O’Clock when I reached my Office— I found there had been a Note from the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President</mhs:persRef>,
				which the Messenger had taken to my house—when he brought it back, it proved to
				contain a request that I would give notice to the other <pb type="ms" n="29"
				/>members of the Administration, and meet at his house this day at half past one
				O’Clock to consider of the proposals in <mhs:persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">De Neuvilles’</mhs:persRef> English Note— It was four
				o’Clock when I received this Note, and of course too late for a Meeting this day. I
				therefore called at the Presidents, on my way home; and he directed me to notify the
				meeting for to-morrow at Noon— <mhs:persRef ref="forbes-john">Forbes</mhs:persRef> was with me this Evening, so that I had no
				time for writing, and my Journal of course runs again in arrear—</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-06">
		<head>6 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-06"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Dueling</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Press</note>
			<note type="subject">West, The</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>6. VI:45.</dateline> Attended the Cabinet Meeting at the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</mhs:persRef>— The
				<mhs:persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">French Minister’s</mhs:persRef> English Note was read and discussed. The anxiety of the President
				to accomplish a settlement of our differences with Spain is so great, that he
				strongly inclines to agree to this Western boundary, and take the line of 100
				Longitude from the red to the Arkansas rivers, and the line of 43. Latitude to the
				South Sea— I had however drafted an Article proposing the line between 101 and 102.
				of Longitude, and that of 41. to the South Sea with a Stipulation that Spain should
				make no Settlements on the red or Arkansas rivers, nor have the Navigation of them,
				which it was agreed I should offer, and then come as near to the proposals of De
				Neuville as may be found necessary— On going to the Office I sent for De Neuville
				who immediately came. I gave him a copy of the Article that I had drafted, and had
				much discussion with him of it. He urged very strenuously that we should accept the
				lines as proposed in his English Note, and said <mhs:persRef ref="onis-luis">Onis</mhs:persRef> never would consent to
				stipulate against making the Settlements, or against Spain’s having the Navigation
				of the Rivers— I finally told him that if M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis would
				accept the remainder of my drafted Article, we would give up the exclusions; and if
				he would accept the Latitude 41. I would refer to the President and recommend the
				acceptance of the Longitude 100— I dined with a Mass of Virginians, lodging at
				<mhs:persRef ref="strother-john">Strothers</mhs:persRef> Hotel— Consisting of <mhs:persRef ref="barbour-philip">P. P. Barbour</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="garnett-robert">Garnett</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="nelson-hugh">H. Nelson</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="newton-thomas">Newton</mhs:persRef>, and some
				others— The company were nineteen, among whom were <mhs:persRef ref="calhoun-john">Calhoun</mhs:persRef> and <mhs:persRef ref="thompson-smith">Thompson</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="edwards-ninian">Edwards</mhs:persRef>,
				Senator from Illinois and <mhs:persRef ref="monroe-joseph">J. J. Monroe</mhs:persRef>— I had been all the day not very well, and
				came home much indisposed— A Shocking incident occurred this day; which occasioned a
				general sensation of horror and disgust. <mhs:persRef ref="mason-armistead">Armistead Thompson Mason</mhs:persRef>, late a Senator in
				Congress from Virginia, son of <mhs:persRef ref="mason-stevens">Stephens Thompson Mason</mhs:persRef>, also formerly a Senator, was
				this morning at Bladensburg shot through the heart, in a duel fought with Muskets,
				at six paces distance, by <mhs:persRef ref="mccarty-john">John M’Carthy</mhs:persRef> his Cousin by blood, and nearly related to
				him by Marriage— The Muskets were loaded each with three balls, and M’Carthy escaped
				with life, only because the balls struck the butt end of his musket, glanced off and
				wounded him in the arm. The cause of the quarrel was political, and originated from
				M’Carthy’s having voted against Mason at the last Election of Members of the House
				of Representatives in Congress for Loudoun County, Virginia. This is one sample of
				the violence of political passions in this Country— Mason was of course an ardent
				partizan, and as he was a man of very promising talents, he is much regretted— But
				he had been raving to fight a duel, ever since he had lost his Election. He posted
				his successful rival <mhs:persRef ref="mercer-charles">C. F. Mercer</mhs:persRef>, as a liar, coward and scoundrel, for refusing to
				fight him more than a year ago; and the newspapers of last Summer were filled with
				his charges of cowardice against M’Carthy for hesitating as to the time, and place,
				and form of meeting him. The duelists here consider this as quite an illegitimate
				battle and almost murder, because it was fought with muskets—but if it had been with
				pistols, though Mason had practiced pistol-shooting, till he could thread a bullet
				on a cambrick needle at twelve paces, and M’Carthy was so near sighted that at the
				same distance he could scarcely discern his man, it would have been quite in
				order.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-07">
		<head>7 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-07"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Religion</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>7. VIII:30.</dateline> I was unwell all Night, and rose very late this
				Morning. <mhs:persRef ref="trumbull-john">Col<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> Trumbull</mhs:persRef> the painter called on me. He
				arrived in the City last Evening, and has left his great picture of the Declaration
				of Independence at Baltimore. He came here to make arrangements with <mhs:persRef ref="bulfinch-charles">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Bulfinch</mhs:persRef> the Architect of the Capitol for a place
				where to suspend it; and is to return to Baltimore to-morrow— I attended at the Hall
				of the House of Representatives, and heard <mhs:persRef ref="kirkland-john">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Kirkland</mhs:persRef>,
				President of Harvard University preach from John XVII.16. “They are not of the
				world, even as I am not of the world.” It was an ingenious and well written
				discourse—a temperate and elegant discussion of the question, how far a christian
				may with propriety mingle in the affairs and shore in the pleasures of the world—
				The house was well filled, but not crowded, and the Sermon gave general
				satisfaction— <mhs:persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="buchanan-mary">Mary Buchanan</mhs:persRef> and <pb type="ms"
					n="30"/><mhs:persRef ref="hellen-mary">Mary Hellen</mhs:persRef> were with me— After bringing them home, I went and paid a
				visit to <mhs:persRef ref="marshall-john">Chief Justice Marshall</mhs:persRef>, and found the Judges <mhs:persRef ref="johnson-william">Johnson</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="duval-gabriel">Duval</mhs:persRef>, and <mhs:persRef ref="story-joseph">Story</mhs:persRef> with
				him. Met <mhs:persRef ref="brown-jacob">General Brown</mhs:persRef> there. I called next upon <mhs:persRef ref="amory-rufus">R. G. Amory</mhs:persRef>, and he came out to me;
				but he was just going to dine, and I did not stop— Then I called on <mhs:persRef ref="upham-nathaniel">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Upham</mhs:persRef> at <mhs:persRef ref="hyatt-unknown">Hyatt’s</mhs:persRef> in the avenue; he also was at dinner,
				I left a card and returned home— The weather and walking was so bad that I did not
				afterwards go out. Evening employed in reading.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-08">
		<head>8 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-08"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Seminole Wars</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>8. VI:</dateline> <mhs:persRef ref="woodbridge-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Woodbridge</mhs:persRef> the Secretary
				of the Michigan territory came to my house this morning to make enquiries concerning
				the printing of the Laws of the Territory; the furnishing copies of the Laws of the
				United States for his Office, and the providing of Seals for six County Courts and
				six Registers of probate in the territory— I asked him to call at the Office, but he
				was too late. I met him as I was returning home and referred him to <mhs:persRef ref="brent-daniel">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Brent</mhs:persRef>— At the Office came successively <mhs:persRef ref="roberts-jonathan">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Roberts</mhs:persRef>, a Senator from the State of Pennsylvania,
					<mhs:persRef ref="buck-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Buck</mhs:persRef>, Consul General from Hamburg, and <mhs:persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> De Neuville</mhs:persRef> the French Minister. Robert’s came to
				recommend the nomination of a <mhs:persRef ref="conard-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Conard</mhs:persRef>, as Marshal for
				the Eastern district of Pennsylvania, <mhs:persRef ref="ingham-samuel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ingham</mhs:persRef> having
				declined accepting it— Roberts read me a Letter from Ingham, giving his reasons for
				declining, recommending Conard, but urging most earnestly that <mhs:persRef ref="moore-daniel">Moore</mhs:persRef> should not be
				appointed; alledging facts highly disreputable to his character, and strong
				suspicions of culpable connivance between him and the late <mhs:persRef ref="smith-john3">Marshal Smith</mhs:persRef>. Roberts
				told me he had seen the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President</mhs:persRef> this Morning, and recommended Conard, whose name
				the President had taken down, and promised to consider of nominating him. M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Buck came to press the object of extending to Hamburg
				the commercial advantages allowed by the Act of Congress of the last Session to the
				Netherlands— I informed him that that the President had sent a message to Congress
				recommending it. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> De Neuville came to tell me that he
				had conferred since our interview last Saturday with <mhs:persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Onis</mhs:persRef>, and had used every possible argument with him to prevail upon him to meet us
				so far as to render a Treaty practicable— That M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis’s
				dispositions and ardent wishes were as favourable as possible to an adjustment— That
				his powers were unlimited, and his Instructions gave him a great Latitude— And that
				he would call upon me himself to-morrow, at any hour that I should appoint and
				deliver to me a projet for a Treaty. What it would be, he De Neuville did not know
				in all its details, and it was proper that we should receive it form M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis himself; but he hoped and believed it would
				contain no insuperable obstacle to a final and amicable adjustment of our
				differences— I appointed One O’Clock to-morrow, to receive M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Onis, of which De Neuville engaged to give him notice— We had a company
				of Gentlemen to dinner— Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> <mhs:persRef ref="amory-rufus">R. G. Amory</mhs:persRef>,
				<mhs:persRef ref="beecher-philemon">Beecher</mhs:persRef>,
				<mhs:persRef ref="kirkland-john">Kirkland</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="lowndes-william">Lowndes</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="mason-jonathan">Mason</mhs:persRef> of Boston and 
				<mhs:persRef ref="mason-william">his Son</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="otis-harrison">Otis</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="parish-unknown">Parish</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="ruggles-benjamin">Ruggles</mhs:persRef>, of Ohio,
				<mhs:persRef ref="schuyler-philip">Schuyler</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="simkins-elred">Simkins</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="taylor-john">Taylor</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="verplanck-gulian">Verplanck</mhs:persRef> and 
				<mhs:persRef ref="westerlo-rensselaer">Westerlo</mhs:persRef>. The 
				two <mhs:persRef ref="coles-edward">brothers</mhs:persRef> <mhs:persRef ref="coles-unknown3">Coles</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="klinckowstrom-axel">Baron Klinkowström</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="lewis-unknown">Commodore Lewis</mhs:persRef>, and 
				<mhs:persRef ref="petry-jean">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Petry</mhs:persRef> had been
				invited but did not come— The company all retired early, except Verplanck who sat
				and conversed with us upon politicks and literature till between 10 and 11. The
				questions upon the proposed Resolutions in the House of Representatives to censure
				<mhs:persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General Jackson’s</mhs:persRef> proceedings in Florida, were this day taken, and all decided
				against the Resolutions and in his favour.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-09">
		<head>9 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-09"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Seminole Wars</note>
			<note type="subject">West, The</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>9. V:15.</dateline> As I was going to the Office this Morning, I met
				<mhs:persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General Jackson</mhs:persRef>, who stopped and told me that he was going to my house; to apologize
				to me, for having declined accepting my invitation to dinner, and afterwards having
				dined with <mhs:persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun</mhs:persRef>, the Secretary of War— He had in
				the first instance declined accepting his invitation also, but M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun having assured him it was only to meet a few
				military friends, who were occasionally here he had been prevailed upon to accept—
				He added that as the question concerning him was now decided, he was going to assure
				me of the sense which he entertained of the part that I had taken in this affair,
				and of the support given him by the Executive Government— I told him I was happy
				that the decision of the house of Representatives, had confirmed the correctness of
				the view taken of his conduct by the President. That my share in these transactions
				had been dictated entirely by a sense of duty and a conviction that his conduct had
				been correct and proper: and that I hoped yet to have the pleasure of seeing him at
				my house— I made a short call at the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</mhs:persRef>, but he was engaged, and I went
				over to the Office, where <mhs:persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</mhs:persRef> came at the appointed
				hour of one, and delivered to me his project of a Treaty for the cession of the
				Florida’s by Spain to the United States, for the settlement of the western boundary,
				and for the adjustment of the claims of indemnities, of the Citizens of the United
				States, against the Spanish Government. He said it was drawn up, in English, with
				reference to the unofficial interviews between <mhs:persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> De
				Neuville</mhs:persRef>, and me, on one part, and the same Minister and himself on the other. It is
				in seventeen Articles; upon which after reading them, I made some observations, and
				promised to lay them before the President; who I presumed would direct me to present
				him a counter-project. He professed the most earnest desire to come to an agreement
				with us, and a strong hope that we might conclude before the end of the present
				Session of Congress— I took his project immediately to the President <pb type="ms"
					n="31"/>to whom I read it, and after conversing with him on the modifications of
				them which it would be expedient on our part to propose, I took it home with me
				promising to prepare to morrow a counterproject; to be submitted the next morning at
				eleven, to the Administration, together with the project itself— I dined with <mhs:persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi
					rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</mhs:persRef> and <mhs:persRef ref="buchanan-mary">Mary Buchanan</mhs:persRef> at M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Onis’s— there was a mixed company of upwards twenty persons; the judges
				of the Supreme Court, Senators and others; among whom a <mhs:persRef ref="hamilton-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Hamilton</mhs:persRef>, whom we knew in England, with <mhs:persRef ref="hamilton-unknown2">his wife</mhs:persRef>, whom he has since
				married. The dinner was quite short and we rose from table, to attend a Ball at <mhs:persRef ref="sewall-unknown2">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Sewall’s</mhs:persRef> on the Capitol Hill. General Jackson, and the
				Officers of his staff were there. He told me that he was going immediately to
				West-Point, and should leave the City on Thursday Morning for Baltimore. <mhs:persRef ref="butler-robert">Col<hi
					rend="superscript">l.</hi> Butler</mhs:persRef>, his adjutant General, spoke to me of the
				Seminole War. and of my Letters to <mhs:persRef ref="erving-george">G. W. Erving</mhs:persRef>— <mhs:persRef ref="gales-joseph">Gales</mhs:persRef> told me that Jackson and <mhs:persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford</mhs:persRef> met this Evening in one of the Ball-rooms,
				without speaking to each other. Home about Midnight. <mhs:persRef ref="brown-jacob">General Brown</mhs:persRef> called at the
				Office this Morning, and recommended very earnestly to me young <mhs:persRef ref="storrow-samuel">Storrow</mhs:persRef>, his judge
				advocate, for an appointment as Secretary of Legation, to any of our Missions
				abroad. I assured him of my own good-will to Storrow, and my disposition to serve
				him; but remarked that there was no immediate prospect of any appointment of that
				description to be filled, and desired him to let Storrow know, how very undesirable
				those appointments are, with regard to any prospects that they hold out. He had told
				me that Storrow’s present situation was merely temporary, and giving him no rank in
				the army held out to him no promise of success for the future— He said Storrow would
				call upon me himself.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-10">
		<head>10 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-10"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Supreme Court</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>10. VI:</dateline> <mhs:persRef ref="tyler-benjamin">B. O. Tyler</mhs:persRef> was here, and took the fac-simile of a
				Letter from <mhs:persRef ref="jefferson-thomas">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Jefferson</mhs:persRef> to <mhs:persRef ref="adams-john">my father</mhs:persRef> which he had made
				and lent to <mhs:persRef ref="gales-joseph">Gales</mhs:persRef> the Printer, who sent it to me. Tyler promised from this to make
				and give me another. <mhs:persRef ref="storrow-samuel">Storrow</mhs:persRef> came and renewed the application for an appointment as
				Secretary of Legation abroad, which <mhs:persRef ref="brown-jacob">General Brown</mhs:persRef> had yesterday made for him. I told
				him that I should be very sincerely disposed to befriend him, but that an office of
				Secretary of Legation would present him no prospect of future advancement, or of a
				permanent condition in life. It might be an object desirable for a young man,
				wishing to visit Europe, and acquire some knowledge of the world, but he had seen
				Europe, and nothing there would have to him the charm of novelty, or furnish him
				with any valuable addition to his stock of knowledge— In Europe, Diplomatic Offices
				afforded a condition of life, a career to which a man might devote himself entirely,
				and without looking farther— But in the practice under our Government, founded upon
				the nature of our institutions, it was merely an incident in the life of a
				Statesman—a preparation for something else—essentially transient and offering in
				itself no prospects worthy of honourable ambition— He said he was satisfied from the
				view I had given him of the subject, that it would not be for his interest to obtain
				the appointment which he had desired, and that he should conclude upon another
				course, and go and settle in the State of Ohio— <mhs:persRef ref="sanford-nathan">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Sanford</mhs:persRef> was here— He has been of late a very frequent visitor, though I have seldom
				seen him— This morning he made his proposals of marriage to <mhs:persRef ref="buchanan-mary">Mary Buchanan</mhs:persRef>— He is a
				widower of forty, with four children, and she a girl of nineteen— He is an active
				and earnest <mhs:persRef ref="clinton-dewitt">Clintonian</mhs:persRef>, and has been quite undisguised heretofore in opinions quite
				unfavourable to me— Not long since he came and tendered his services as Minister to
				France, in case of <mhs:persRef ref="gallatin-albert">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gallatin’s</mhs:persRef> return— I mentioned his
				offer to the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President</mhs:persRef>, who observed that it involved some delicate considerations—
					M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sanford’s matrimonial projects I presume have no
				connection with his politics. His answer this Morning, I understand was negative,
				but not definitive— I was engaged in preparing a counterproject for a Treaty with
				Spain, to that presented to me yesterday by <mhs:persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</mhs:persRef>— I
				made it, by marginal alterations, and additions, and by erasures in his project— I
				then took it to the Office, and gave it to <mhs:persRef ref="brent-daniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Brent</mhs:persRef>, to
				make out for to-morrow Morning, a copy, half-sided for consideration at the Cabinet
				Meeting. <mhs:persRef ref="hale-salma">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hale</mhs:persRef>, a member of the House of
				Representatives from New Hampshire came to the Office, to recommend <mhs:persRef ref="livermore-arthur">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Arthur Livermore</mhs:persRef>, one of his colleagues in the House
				for the appointment as one of the Circuit judges of the United States, if a bill,
				now before Congress should pass both Houses and become a Law. Its provisions are to
				appoint eight Circuit Judges, and to release the Judges of the Supreme Court from
				the duties of Circuit Judges, and to reduce their number to five— I attended this
				Evening with <mhs:persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</mhs:persRef> and Mary Buchanan a Ball at <mhs:persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun’s</mhs:persRef>— The house was <pb type="ms" n="32"/>crowded
				with company to excess. <mhs:persRef key="crawford-william-harris">Crawford</mhs:persRef> and <mhs:persRef ref="jackson-andrew">Jackson</mhs:persRef> were there, without speaking to each
				other. I gave notice to Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Crawford, Calhoun,
				<mhs:persRef ref="thompson-smith">Thompson</mhs:persRef> and <mhs:persRef ref="wirt-william">Wirt</mhs:persRef>, to attend at the President’s at eleven O’Clock to-morrow
				Morning.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-11">
		<head>11 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-11"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Louisiana Purchase</note>
			<note type="subject">Native Americans</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
			<note type="subject">Seminole Wars</note>
			<note type="subject">West, The</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>11. VII:</dateline> There was a full Meeting of the Members of the
				Administration at eleven O’Clock this Morning— I found on going to the Office that
					<mhs:persRef ref="brent-daniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Brent</mhs:persRef> was not there, and sent to his house for
				the copy of my Counterproject for a Treaty with Spain. He sent it to the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</mhs:persRef>
				with <mhs:persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis’s</mhs:persRef> project, both of which were fully
				discussed— Several other alterations and modifications of Onis’s project were
				proposed. The meeting broke up at four O’Clock, adjourning till to-morrow, without
				coming to ultimate conclusion— The second Article of Onis’s project contains the
				cession of the Florida’s by the <mhs:persRef ref="ferdinand-vii">king of Spain</mhs:persRef> to the United States, but describing
				the Florida’s “such as they were ceded by Great-Britain in 1783 and with the limits
				by which they are designated in the Treaty of limits and Navigation concluded
				between Spain and the United States on the 27<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>of
				October 1795.” I struck out this passage, as being useless to define the cession,
				and as implying an admission that the part of West Florida, of which we are already
				in possession was not included in the cession of Louisiana, as we have always
				contended— It was agreed that I should insist upon their being struck out. I
				proposed also that the second and third Articles of Onis’s project should be
				included in one Article; with an additional clause providing for the delivery of the
				archives and documents; which was approved— Onis’s fourth Article contains his
				boundary line West of the Mississippi, beginning at the Sabine on the gulph of
				Mexico, following the present boundary of the State of Louisiana to the red river
				then the course of the red river to Longitude 100 and Latitude 33 1/4 thence a line
				North to the Arkansaw, then the course of the Arkansaw to its source and to Latitude
				42. thence to the source of the Multnomah, then following that river to 43. and
				thence in that parallel to the South Sea”— The alteration that I proposed was to
				follow the Red River to Longitude 102 and Latitude 34—thence a North line to the
				Arkansaw—then following to its source, in Latitude 41. North, and thence by the
				parallel to the South Sea— The Rivers and all the islands in them to belong to the
				United States, and the Western and Southern Banks of the Rivers to form the boundary
				of Spain— We are now approaching so near to an agreement that the President inclines
				to give up all that remains in contest— He was this day decidedly for agreeing to
				the 100<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>degree of Longitude the 43<hi
					rend="superscript">d. </hi>of Latitude, and for taking the middle of the rivers,
				if we can not get more— The members of the Administration, all incline the same way;
				but I was convinced that we should obtain more by adhering steadily to our points—
				Onis’s eighth Article provides that the Territories in the two Florida’s occupied by
				the troops of the United States, should first be formally restored to Spanish
				Commissioners, to be again delivered up to the Commissioners or Officers of the
				United States— The alteration that I propose is that the places already in our
				possession shall remain so, and the rest be delivered up to our Officers— But this
				being merely matter of form it was concluded not to be tenacious about it— Onis’s
					9<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>Article, confirms all grants of lands made
				before the 24<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>of January 1818, that being the day
				when he made the first proposal for the cession of the Florida’s, and declares all
				grants subsequent to that date null and void, the grantees not having fulfilled the
				conditions of the cessions— I proposed to add that all prior grants should be valid
				only to the same extent that they would be to the king of Spain himself— It was
				agreed that I should urge for this addition— The tenth Article contains the mutual
				renunciations of claims of indemnity— Onis has taken the draft of our renunciations
				from our own proposals heretofore made— Among his renunciations on the part of
				Spain, is one for the revenues collected by us in the Florida’s, and for damages to
				the crown, in consequence of our invasion— I drew a counter-renunciation of the
				indemnities due to the United States, for the expences of the late campaign in
				Florida, necessitated by the failure of Spain to fulfil her Treaty stipulation to
				restrain be force her Indians from hostilities against us— But as an alternative I
				drew a short mutual renunciation of indemnities on both sides, for the late
				transactions in Florida— The eleventh Article annuls in part the Convention of
				August 1802. and provides that the indemnities due to the Citizens of the United
				States, for spoliations shall be made form the proceeds of the public Lands in
				Florida. It releases all Claims of Citizens of the United States, upon the
				Government of Spain, reserving only those upon individuals— I proposed a
				modification of this release, confining it only to those claims for which the
				claimants were entitled to the interposition of their respective Governments— This
				modification was however rejected on the principle that we could not before hand
				decide what claimants were and what were not rigorously entitled to the
				interposition of their Government— There was a long and earnest discussion of this
				point; and distinctions taken between claims upon contracts and claims for
				wrongs—captures at sea, and seizures <pb type="ms" n="33"/>in the Ports— <mhs:persRef key="crawford-william-harris">Crawford</mhs:persRef>
				said that if we admitted claims upon contracts, the whole floating debt of Spain
				would be brought down upon us. The President drew up a description confined to
				unlawful captures at sea, and unlawful seizures in the Ports of Spain and the
				Colonies; it was debated whether the claims of <mhs:persRef ref="meade-richard">R. W. Meade</mhs:persRef>, of <mhs:persRef ref="robinson-william">W. D. Robinson</mhs:persRef>, of
				<mhs:persRef ref="lloyd-james">Lloyd</mhs:persRef> &amp; <mhs:persRef ref="perkins-unknown2">Perkins</mhs:persRef>, of <mhs:persRef ref="yard-james">James Yard</mhs:persRef>, and of <mhs:persRef ref="smith-samuel2">Smith</mhs:persRef> and <mhs:persRef ref="buchanan-james">Buchanan</mhs:persRef> would be embraced by
				this description, and whether provision ought to be made for them— Crawford was for
				reducing as much as possible the claims to be compensated, and for striking out that
				item of the renunciations which had been proposed by me, in my Letter to Onis, of
				31. October last, and which included all claims statements of which have been
				presented to the Department of State, or to the Minister of the United States in
				Spain— Crawford said this was not binding upon us now, because it had not been
				accepted when offered— Calhoun inclined the same way— <mhs:persRef ref="thompson-smith">Thompson</mhs:persRef> doubted whether the
				seizures at Lima, by the <mhs:persRef ref="lapezuela-joaquin">Vice-Roy of Peru</mhs:persRef>, of vessels and Cargoes for which there
				were licences from the Spanish Government, would form claims upon contract, or upon
				unlawful seizure; and Wirt said it would very well bear an argument— The whole
				discussion upon this Article was adjourned till to-morrow at Noon— I had drawn an
				additional Article, to be the 11<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>providing for the
				examination and adjustment of all the claims by three Commissioners, Citizens of the
				United States, to sit at Washington, and providing for the payment of the claims to
				the amount of five Millions of dollars. It was determined that this Article should
				be proposed—and also that the 13<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>and 14<hi
					rend="superscript">th. </hi>Articles of Onis’s project should not be admitted—
				These were stipulations that all vessels should be cleared out for Ports
				specifically named in the papers; and that all others should be liable to capture
				and condemnation. The 15<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>Article was an engagement to
				deliver up deserters from merchant vessels; which it was decided should be admitted—
				The 17<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>was a stipulation that Spanish vessels should
				for twelve years be admitted into all the Ports of both Florida’s, on the same
				footing as vessels of the United States, and always afterwards upon the footing of
				the most favoured Nation— As we are now in controversy with France upon the
				construction of a similar Article in the Convention for the cession of Louisiana, it
				was resolved not to agree to it in this Treaty. The 16<hi rend="superscript">th.
				</hi>Article promised a certificate that the United States have received no
				satisfaction from France, for the captures by French privateers and condemnations by
				French Consuls, within Spanish Jurisdiction, so that Spain may claim indemnity for
				them from France. I proposed to certify the fact in the Article itself, and to
				modify the last part of it, and say, without naming France—so that Spain may avail
				herself of it in such manner as she may deem just and proper— This was also
				determined— I dined at <mhs:persRef ref="lee-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> William Lee’s</mhs:persRef> with a company
				of Gentlemen, among whom was <mhs:persRef ref="vanness-william">Judge W. P. Van Ness</mhs:persRef> of New York— I had at the
				President’s request some conversation with Judge Van Ness concerning the district
				Attorney at New-York, <mhs:persRef ref="fisk-jonathan">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Fisk</mhs:persRef>— The complaints against
				him for gross and notorious intemperance, have become so loud and numerous, that the
				President has concluded to remove him, unless he will resign: but as in case of a
				removal there must be a previous enquiry, judge Van Ness proposed, to write himself
				to Fiske, and offer him the alternative— He is persuaded that Fiske will resign
				rather than pass through the ordeal of an enquiry. <mhs:persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
				Adams</mhs:persRef> was quite ill, and confined the whole day to her bed.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-12">
		<head>12 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-12"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">West, The</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>12. VII:</dateline> Snow Storm all the Morning. I am so constantly
				occupied, and absorbed by the Negotiation with <mhs:persRef ref="onis-luis">Onis</mhs:persRef>, that almost all other business
				runs in arrear, and in a most especial manner this Journal. (13 [symbols]) I rode to the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</mhs:persRef>, and the adjourned Cabinet Meeting was
				held— The subjects left undecided yesterday were resumed, and I was finally
				authorised to accept the longitude 100 from the red river to the Arkansaw, and the
				Latitude 43. to the South Sea; if better can not be obtained— With regard to the
				claims, I had drawn up a project of a clause admitting all those which have been
				stated at the Department of State, or to the <mhs:persRef ref="erving-george">American Minister at Madrid</mhs:persRef>; and
				excluding all such as could be satisfied by the ordinary administration of the
				judicial tribunals of Spain— This was however not adopted, being considered as vague
				and uncertain— The President’s proposed draft, limiting the claims of this
				specification to those for unlawful seizures at Sea, or in the Ports of Spain and
				the Colonies was adopted— After it was thus settled what should be offered as our
				Counter-project I went to the Office, and altered the draft which had been copied by
					<mhs:persRef ref="brent-daniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Brent</mhs:persRef>, making it informable to the determinations
				of the Meeting, and left it with M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Brent to make out a
				second, fair copy to be <pb type="ms" n="34"/>ready to morrow and to be communicated
				to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis— This was <mhs:persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">my wife’s</mhs:persRef> birth-day— We were
				invited to an Evening party at <mhs:persRef ref="tayloe-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Tayloe’s</mhs:persRef>; but were
				prevented from attending it by the Stormy weather.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-13">
		<head>13 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-13"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Privateering</note>
			<note type="subject">West, The</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>13. VII:15.</dateline> <mhs:persRef ref="trumbull-john">Col<hi rend="superscript">l. </hi>Trumbull</mhs:persRef> called
				upon me this Morning, to inform me that he had finally arrived with his great
				picture of the Declaration of Independence, painted for Congress— It is to be
				suspended for the present in one of the chambers of the North wing of the Capitol.
				Since the picture was finished last September he has exhibited it successively for
				several weeks in New-York Boston, Philadelphia and Baltimore— Some dissatisfaction
				was shewn at this in Congress, where <mhs:persRef ref="spencer-john">J. C. Spencer</mhs:persRef> moved to withhold the
				appropriation due for the picture, by contract, on that account. They objected also
				to the sum given for the four pictures, which is certainly to say the least very
				liberal. It is thirty-two thousand dollars for the four pictures; of which 8000
				dollars were paid in advance, and 6000 are to be paid at the delivery of each
				picture. <mhs:persRef ref="lewis-unknown">Commodore Lewis</mhs:persRef> was also here, to press for the settlement of his account
				as a special agent of the Government, appointed first to go to South America; and
				who finally went to Port au Prince; and after staying there a few Months came home
				without leave; as he says, dying, and now requires to be paid for all the time
				before he went; and all the time since his return— <mhs:persRef ref="brent-daniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Brent</mhs:persRef> came and brought his fair copy of the Counterproject of a Treaty with Spain to
				be offered to <mhs:persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</mhs:persRef>. After calling at the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</mhs:persRef>,
				I sent for <mhs:persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">De Neuville</mhs:persRef> the French Minister, who came to the Office— I read to him
				the parts of our Counterproject which differ from the project of M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis, explained to him our motives for rejecting some
				of the Articles offered by him, and the reasons of the modifications which we
				desired to some of the others. I told him that Onis’s project had been for two days
				discussed in full meetings of the administration— That the project we now had to
				offer was the last we could make; I should send it this day to M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis; and as it was of extreme importance that we
				should come to some termination immediately, I wished him to see Onis and prevail
				upon him to give us an answer; yes or no— He said he would see him and endeavour to
				prevail upon him to meet us as far as might be in his power; but he suggested the
				difficulties upon which he knew Onis would lay the greatest stress— He pleaded with
				extreme earnestness for the 43<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> degree of Latitude to
				the South Sea; and he was sure Onis would insist upon the middle of the rivers for
				the boundary— He would also object to the limitation of five Millions of Dollars to
				be assumed by the United States to pay their own Citizens, for claims upon Spain;
				because it would have the appearance as if it was the sum given for the Florida’s
				which every body knows to be worth more than ten times that sum— De Neuville had
				also objections of his own to the 16<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>Article of
				Onis’s project— That is the certificate that the United States have not received
				from France compensation for the captures by French privateers and condemnations by
				French Consuls within Spanish Jurisdiction; so that Spain might redemand the
				compensation from France— It seems Onis had never shewn him that Article of his
				project, and when I read it to him with the modification proposed by me, he appeared
				surprized and somewhat irritated; not against us but against Onis— He said he should
				advise him to strike it out, and if he refused would send him his own pamphlet
				signed Verus 14 [symbols]. I told him that it was an Article
				to which we could not object; but which was not desired by us— If he could obtain
				the consent of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis that it should be omitted we
				should certainly not insist upon it being retained— Upon the whole affair he
				promised to see and converse with Onis, and let me know the result to-morrow. <mhs:persRef ref="bailey-john">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Bailey</mhs:persRef> spent the Evening here.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-14">
		<head>14 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-14"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Religion</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>14. VI:15.</dateline> The Avenues and roads are so bad that walking is
				almost impracticable. I rode to the Capitol and heard <mhs:persRef ref="kirkland-john">D<hi rend="superscript"
					>r.</hi> Kirkland</mhs:persRef> preach upon Christian Charity— A very ingenious and well
				written discourse, delivered with propriety; but without that animation and burning
				zeal which gathers multitudes of hearers. The hall was not crowded, and scarcely
				filled. As I was coming away, <mhs:persRef key="clay-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Clay</mhs:persRef> the Speaker took a
				seat with me in my Carriage, and I took him home to his lodgings at <mhs:persRef ref="davis-unknown">Davis’s</mhs:persRef>— He
				spoke in handsome terms of President Kirkland’s sermon, and said he was much pleased
				with this system of religion that the Clergymen in and around Boston, are now <hi
					rend="italic">getting up</hi>. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Clay complained of
				having been very unwell, the last week or ten days— After setting him down, and
				paying a number of visits to members of Congress on the Capitol Hill, I came home—
				Had short visits from <mhs:persRef ref="baldwin-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Baldwin</mhs:persRef>, member of the House
				from Pennsylvania, and from <mhs:persRef ref="marshall-john">Chief Justice Marshall</mhs:persRef>, and <mhs:persRef ref="livingston-henry">Judge Livingston</mhs:persRef>. Passed the
				remainder of the day and the Evening at home, expecting to see or hear from <mhs:persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> De Neuville</mhs:persRef> the French Minister; but was
				disappointed.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-15">
		<head>15 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-15"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Louisiana Purchase</note>
			<note type="subject">West, The</note>
			<note type="subject">Westward Exploration and Expansion/Westward Migration/Manifest Destiny</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>15. VII:</dateline> At the Office, I had visitors,<mhs:persRef ref="graham-john"> M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> John Grahm</mhs:persRef>, who came to make some enquiries of preparations, for his
				Mission as Minister Plenipotentiary at Rio Janeiro, to which he has been appointed.
				A question has arisen who is to go as his <pb type="ms" n="35"/>Secretary of
				Legation— <mhs:persRef ref="appleton-john">John James Appleton</mhs:persRef>, is one of the applicants, and a <mhs:persRef ref="everett-unknown">D<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Everitt</mhs:persRef> of Virginia, has been mentioned to the
				<mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President</mhs:persRef> as a proper person. The appointment has accordingly been offered to him,
				but M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Graham doubts whether he will accept it— <mhs:persRef ref="curson-unknown">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Curson</mhs:persRef> brought me a Letter of introduction from <mhs:persRef ref="lloyd-james">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> James Lloyd</mhs:persRef> of Boston. He was the supercargo of a
				Vessel sent by Lloyd and the <mhs:persRef ref="perkins-thomas">Perkins’s</mhs:persRef> several years since to Lima, under a licence
				from the <mhs:persRef ref="ferdinand-vii">king of Spain</mhs:persRef>, but the ship was seized and confiscated by the <mhs:persRef ref="lapezuela-joaquin">Vice-Roy of
				Peru</mhs:persRef>; and although restitution has since been decreed by the Spanish Government,
				nothing has ever been obtained, and this is now one of the heavy claims the
				adjustment of which is to be provided for in the Treaty with Spain. Curson is going
				on immediately to South Carolina. <mhs:persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> De Neuville</mhs:persRef> the
				French Minister came, and reported to me the substance of his interviews with M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis, relative to the Counter-project for a Treaty
				which I sent to Onis the day before yesterday— He desires some further explanation
				with regard to my throwing into one, the second Article of his project, and to the
				additional clause to it proposed by me. Without knowing what particular explanations
				were desired I gave M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> De Neuville the reasons for
				making one Article of the two, and for the addition proposed. There were in this
				Article and in many others of the project sentimental professions of friendship and
				affection between the United States and the king of Spain, to say the least entirely
				superfluous, and which I therefore struck out— But the boundaries of the Florida’s
				as his project proposed to describe them could not be admitted by us, without giving
				up the ground for which we had always contended that West-Florida to the Perdido,
				belonged to Louisiana. It was unnecessary for the contracting parties to say any
				thing of their motives—unnecessary to say any thing directly contrary to their past
				pretensions; and one of the most important principles in drawing up public compacts
				was brevity— As few words as possible to express with precision the agreement— The
				additional clause was intended merely to secure the delivery to the Officers or
				Commissioners of the United States of the Archives and Documents of the ceded
				Provinces— This explanation M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> De Neuville supposed
				would be sufficient— A more formidable objection was made by <mhs:persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Onis</mhs:persRef> to my third Article, containing the Boundary line Westward of the
				Mississippi. After a long and violent struggle he had agreed to take Longitude 100
				from the red river to the Arkansaw, and Latitude 42 from the source of the Arkansaw
				to the South Sea. But he insisted upon having the middle of all the rivers for the
				boundary and not as I proposed, the westward Southern Banks; and he also insisted
				upon the free Navigation of the rivers to be common to both Nations. De Neuville
				urged these demands with great earnestness and thought it was a point of honour
				which Onis could not abandon without humiliation. I told him that I could see no
				humiliation in it. We were to agree upon a boundary; for which purpose the bank of a
				river was more simple and less liable to occasion future controversy than the middle
				of the river. It was extremely difficult to ascertain where the middle of a river
				throughout its course was. It would take a century to settle the middle of the
				Sabine, red and Arkansaw Rivers, and to which of the parties every island in them
				would belong. But by taking the Banks for the boundary and declaring the rivers and
				all their islands to belong to the United States, there could be no question
				herafter between the parties to arise from this arrangement— It was of no importance
				to Spain, who never would have any settlements upon these rivers—but the United
				States would have extensive settlements upon them, within a very few years. Then the
				Islands in the rivers would be occupied, and questions of title and controversies
				with Spain. My principle had been to cut up all this by the Roots, which would be
				done by taking the Banks of the rivers for the boundary— There were I told him
				several examples of it in the boundaries between the States of this Union, and we
				were now engaged in a long, tedious, and expensive Negotiation, with Great-Britain
				to settle a boundary, all the difficulties of which arise from having assumed a
				middle of rivers, and lakes for the line. De Neuville acknowledged that this view of
				the subject took away all ground of objection upon the point of honour and said he
				would endeavour to convince Onis of it, but if the Banks of the rivers were to form
				the boundaries, the Spanish settlers must at least have the use of the Waters, and
				the Navigation of the rivers to the Sea. I told him that such a stipulation if made
				would be merely nominal, as there was not the remotest probability of there ever
				being any Spanish settlers there— I could not promise the acceptance of <hi
					rend="italic">any</hi> variation from the project, I had now sent to M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis— All I could say was, that if he would agree to
				take the Banks of the rivers for the boundary, I would <pb type="ms" n="36"/>refer
				to the President for his consideration the question with regard to the use of the
				Waters and the Navigation of the rivers to the Sea— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Onis agrees to the 4<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>5<hi rend="superscript">th.
				</hi>and 6<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>Articles of my Counter-project, and to the
					7<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>which provides for the delivery of the places
				in Florida, to the Officers of the United States within six Months after the
				exchange of the Ratifications; and for the evacuation by the Spanish troops— But
					M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis asks that the United States should furnish
				transports and the necessary escort for conveying them to the Havanna— I told M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> De Neuville, that while M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Onis was so punctilious upon the point of honour this was a proposal that I should
				not have expected from him; but as he did think proper to make it, I would refer it
				to the President, and did not expect that it would be refused— M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis insists upon the 9<hi rend="superscript">th.
				</hi>Article of his project as drawn up by him; which confirms as valid all grants
				of Land in Florida made before the 24<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>of January
				1818. and annuls all grants made since then for non performance of the Conditions—my
				proposed amendment was to confirm of the grants prior to 1818 only those, the
				conditions of which have been performed— Onis rejects this, and says the reason
				assigned for annulling the grants subsequent to 24. January 1818 is only to save the
				honour of the Spanish crown— I now discussed this subject with De Neuville, much at
				large; and told him it was impossible for us to confirm by the Treaty grants which
				without the Treaty would be null and void— We did not intend neither could the king
				of Spain desire that we should make the Treaty an engine for fraud; to sanction
				titles which the king of Spain himself does not acknowledge, and which would strip
				the United States of the whole fund from which the sums we assume to pay for
				indemnities to our own citizens must be paid— He said there might be many honest,
				bona fide grantees partly settled upon their lands, but who in the full confidence
				that they would never be dispossessed, had been prevented from performing all the
				conditions of their grants or had neglected them— And as they would never have been
				molested by the king of Spain, it would be very hard upon them if the Treaty should
				turn them out of their Estates— I told him we should have no such intention or
				desire— Bona fide holders of land for settlement, in actual possession would be
				doubtless suffered to hold their lands, as they would have held them under the
				Spanish Government— But we could not cripple our own resources, and at the same time
				sanction fraud— All therefore that I could consent to refer again to the President
				was, that grants prior to 24. January 1818, should be binding upon the United States
				to the same extent that they would be upon the king of Spain if the territory had
				remained subject to Spain— If there was an invincible objection on the part of Spain
				to have this principle established by an Article in the Treaty, we might perhaps
				take the Article drawn by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis, delivering at the
				signature of the Treaty a declaration to be made public, to the same effect— So that
				there might be no misunderstanding of our intentions. De Neuville declared himself
				satisfied upon this point.— In the renunciation of claims in the ninth Article 15
					[symbols] Onis proposes to add those for seizures in the
					<hi rend="italic">Territories</hi> of Spain and her Colonies to be added to
				those at Sea, and in the Ports. The object of this addition De Neuville said was to
				include the claims of <mhs:persRef ref="chouteau-auguste">Chouteau</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="demun-jules">Demun</mhs:persRef>, and others in the Missouri Territory for
				seizures of their property, in a trading speculation by the <mhs:persRef ref="apodaca-juan">Vice-Roy of Mexico</mhs:persRef>— De
				Mun is of French origin and has <mhs:persRef ref="demun-unknown">a brother</mhs:persRef> living with De Neuville, and attached to
				his Legation— Onis asks further that to the mutual renunciation of claims for
				indemnities, arising from the late military transactions in Florida, should be added
				a clause that satisfaction shall be made by the United States for any damages
				suffered by individual inhabitants and Spanish Officers in Florida, by the late
				operations of the American army. I observed there had been formal stipulations that
				private property should be respected, and there was no reason to suppose they had
				been violated— I could not perceive therefore the necessity for such a clause. He
				replied that there were some such complaints, and there might be others— M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis thought himself bound while agreeing to the
				cession of the Territory, to secure protection to the lawful interests of the
				inhabitants who were Spanish subjects— That they should obtain justice for
				individual injuries, as if they were citizens of the United States— I took the
				clause for reference to the President— Onis agrees to the 10<hi rend="superscript"
					>th</hi> Article, annulling the Convention of August 1802— In the eleventh he
				insists upon omitting the limitation of the sum to be assumed by the United States
				for payment of the claims of their Citizens upon Spain, to five Millions of Dollars.
				This was one of the points most strongly debated between us; I insisted that as this
				Article particularly regarded the U.S. themselves, and we agreed to give a full
				discharge to Spain, she could have no right to ask the omission of the limitation;
				and if there should be no limitation of the sum, besides the uncertainty under which
				we should be, of what we should <pb type="ms" n="37"/>have engaged to perform, there
				would be great alarm here among the public, and exaggerated representations of the
				claims assumed, which might even endanger the ratification of the Treaty by the
				Senate. He said Onis was exceedingly anxious upon this Article; and fearful that he
				would be blamed in Spain for having sold the Florida’s for five Millions of dollars.
				He said there were difficulties to get over in the king’s Council at Madrid, as well
				as in the Senate of the United States. There was an influence of Priests in the
				Council, which was always counteracting the policy of the Ministers; and which
				produced the most extraordinary inconsistencies and absurdities in the proceedings
				of that body. The Minister was never sure of any thing. One day he would obtain a
				solemn resolution of the Council, and give instructions to a Minister abroad
				accordingly; and the next day, by some manoeuvre of the king’s Confessor, or some
				Grandee of Spain, of the royal household the Resolution would be annulled by another
				contradictory to it. He had seen a succession of Instructions to Onis, marked by
				these successive and contradictory Resolutions of the royal Council. Nothing could
				be more ridiculous and disgusting. But these Priests who had no measures of their
				own to propose, and were never responsible for any thing, were always setting up the
				honour and dignity of Spain—the glory of the Monarchy, and talking as in the time of
				<mhs:persRef ref="charles-v">Charles the fifth</mhs:persRef>. Now if the limitation of five Millions should be in the Treaty it
				might give them a handle to say that the interest and honour of Spain were both
				sacrificed by the bargain— I rejoined that it was notorious that the Florida’s had
				always been a burden instead of a benefit to Spain— That so far as her interest was
				concerned, to obtain five Millions of Dollars for them would be a bargain for Onis
				to boast of instead of being ashamed. As a mere pecuniary bargain it would be a hard
				one to us. That as to the Priests, if Onis signed the Treaty without transcending
				his powers, it would be too late, when it should reach Madrid, for them to resist
				its ratification— And he himself had told me that he had unlimited powers— That he
				could if he chose cede to the United States the kingdom of Mexico, without
				transcending them— However, I would take for reference to the President the
				proposition to leave out the limitation, to which for my own part, I should not have
				much objection— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis agrees to omit the 13<hi
					rend="superscript">th. </hi>and 14<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>Articles of
				his project. He insists upon the 16<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>which De Neuville
				thinks is very indecent, and he has no doubt will be disapproved by the Spanish
				Government— But he admits we cannot with propriety reject it and as to Spain’s
				redemanding the indemnity from France; let her come when she will said De Neuville;
				we have an answer ready for her— Onis clings likewise to his 17<hi
					rend="superscript">th. </hi>Article, the privilege for twelve years to Spanish
				vessels in all the Ports of the ceded territories, and the treatment of the most
				favoured Nation forever afterwards— I told De Neuville we could not agree to it. As
				to the latter clause he knew we were now in controversy with him on the effect of a
				similar stipulation in the Louisiana Convention, and the other part of the Article
				would admit Spanish vessels, as priviledged to the Port of Mobile and the parts of
				Florida, which we claim as our own, and of which we have been for years in
				possession— He then said if we could not grant the whole of the Article, we might at
				least grant it in part— It would probably never be of much use to Spain; but having
				the, appearance of a commercial privilege it might help to reconcile the Nation to
				the cession, we might omit the last clause and confine the remainder to the places
				of which possession is yet to be given to us— I consented to take for reference to
				the President, the question of the twelve years privilege, limited to the Ports of
				Pensacola and S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Augustine— After going through this
				discussion of all the Articles of the Treaty De Neuville promised to see M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis again, to report to him my observations, and
				to-morrow will let me know the result. We had company to dine with us— 
				<mhs:persRef ref="brown-jacob">Gen<hi rend="superscript">l. </hi>Brown</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="biddle-thomas">Major Biddle</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="storrow-samuel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Storrow</mhs:persRef>, and 
				Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs:</hi> <mhs:persRef ref="brent-daniel">D. Brent</mhs:persRef>; 
				<mhs:persRef ref="barbour-philip">P. Barbour</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="garnett-robert">Garnett</mhs:persRef>,
				<mhs:persRef ref="morton-marcus">M. Morton</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="sanford-nathan">Sanford</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="smyth-alexander">Al<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Smyth</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="todd-thomas">Todd</mhs:persRef> and 
				<mhs:persRef ref="trumbull-john">Trumbull</mhs:persRef>—
				Invitations had been sent to 
				<mhs:persRef ref="jones-unknown3">Col<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> Jones</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="wool-john">Col<hi rend="superscript">l </hi>Wool</mhs:persRef> and 
				<mhs:persRef ref="harrison-unknown2">Lieut<hi rend="superscript">t. </hi>Harrison</mhs:persRef>
				of General Brown’s suite, to 
				<mhs:persRef ref="macomb-alexander">General Macomb</mhs:persRef> and 
				<mhs:persRef ref="root-unknown">Captain Root</mhs:persRef>, and to 
				Mess<hi	rend="superscript">rs.</hi> <mhs:persRef ref="bryan-henry">Bryan</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="leake-walter">Leak</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="newton-thomas">Newton</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="sawyer-lemuel">Sawyer</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="walker-david">Walker</mhs:persRef> of Kentucky and
				<mhs:persRef ref="williams-thomas">Williams</mhs:persRef> of Mississippi, all of whom sent excuses or failed to come; our party was
				therefore quite small. They left us early after dinner; and we went to a Ball at
					<mhs:persRef key="bagot-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagots</mhs:persRef>— The roads were excessively bad; almost
				impassable— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> De Neuville’s Carriage overset as he was
				going home almost in front of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bagot’s door— <mhs:persRef ref="holmes-john">Holmes</mhs:persRef>
				and a party of members of Congress overset in a Slough opposite the Treasury
				Department Office— It was Midnight when we came home; and not without difficulty
				that we reached the house, with our horses one of which in heavy roads is addicted
				to <hi rend="italic">balking</hi>.</p>
		</div>
	</div>
	
	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-16">
		<head>16 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-16"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Missouri Compromise</note>
			<note type="subject">Sectionalism</note>
			<note type="subject">Slavery</note>
		</bibl>
		
		<div type="docbody">
			
			<p><pb type="ms" n="38"/><dateline>16. VII:15.</dateline> [symbols] <mhs:persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> De Neuville</mhs:persRef> sent me this Morning a Note with a written
				Statement part French and part English of the substance of our Conversation
				yesterday, and the points upon which <mhs:persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</mhs:persRef> and I have
				come to an agreement, and those upon which the arrangement is yet to be completed.
				The paper though short contains a view sufficiently correct of all the material
				parts of our conversation, though with an apparent, and probably only apparent
				mistake of the 16<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>for the 14<hi rend="superscript"
					>th. </hi>Article— He sent me this minute of what passed between us, by way of
				precaution, to be sure of what he might say to Onis from me, and wrote me that after
				seeing Onis this Morning, he would call at my Office between two and three O’Clock—
				At the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</mhs:persRef> I met <mhs:persRef ref="thompson-smith">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Thompson</mhs:persRef> the Secretary of
				the Navy— De Neuville came to the Office according to his promise, and told me that
				Onis had concluded to come to our terms— He had agreed to all the essential points—
				He would have a copy of the Treaty in Spanish made out as soon as possible, and
				bring it to me himself, to be laid before the President— He had given up some of the
				objects on which we had differed with great reluctance, and hoped we should yet be
				willing to reconsider, them before concluding— He clung very tenaciously to the
				middle of the rivers for the boundaries; but he had convinced him there was nothing
				humiliating for Spain, in assuming the banks— As to the article relating to the
				grants of Lands in Florida, Onis’s object was merely to secure the bona fide holders
				of lands, and not to cover any fraudulent concessions. He made it even a point of
				honour to annul the grants made by the <mhs:persRef ref="ferdinand-vii">king</mhs:persRef> last Winter, because hints had been
				thrown out, that he himself had been personally interested in them. He was also
				exceedingly anxious that the limitation of the sum assumed by the United States to
				five Millions of dollars should be omitted, but will not make it a sine qua non. The
				privilege for Spanish vessels at S<hi rend="superscript">t. </hi>Augustine and
				Pensacola for twelve years, was a very important object to him, and he hoped the
				President would consent to it— At all Events, it might now be considered as certain
				that we should conclude a Treaty— This is the first day that I have permitted myself
				to indulge this hope; and with the hope came an anxiety more profound than I have
				ever felt lest it should ultimately be deceived— We all attended a Ball this Evening
				at M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis’s. The rumour that we are upon the point of
				concluding a Treaty has got abroad to such an extent, that many enquiries were made
				of me upon the subject— Many which I could not answer with propriety, and which it
				was at the same time difficult to parry— I had some conversation with M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis himself who told me that he would have his
				Spanish copy of the amended project made out to-morrow or the next day— He pressed
				me very urgently for the middle of the rivers and for the omission of the limitation
				of five Millions; and pretended that De Neuville had told him we should yield those
				points—which however De Neuville himself expressly denied. The excessive curiosity
				upon the subject of this Negotiation with Spain is qualified only by the agitation
				of a new question in the House of Representatives, on a Bill for admitting the
				Missouri territory into the Union as a State—a Motion for exploding Slavery from it,
				has set the two sides of the house, Slave-holders and non Slave-holders into a
				violent flame against each other, and <mhs:persRef ref="middleton-henry">Middleton</mhs:persRef> told me <mhs:persRef key="clay-henry">Clay</mhs:persRef> had seized the
				opportunity of pushing himself forward as the champion of the Southern interest. He
				would thus contrive to keep himself always in the public eye, as a party leader, and
				be ready for every event that may happen— It was about midnight when we returned
				home from the Ball. The Senate yesterday confirmed the nomination of <mhs:persRef ref="forsyth-john">John Forsyth</mhs:persRef> of
				Georgia, as Minister Plenipotentiary to Spain. He has been several years a member of
				the House of Representatives from Georgia and chairman of the Committee for Foreign
				Relations. After being re-elected to the next Congress, he has in the course of the
				present Winter transferred to the Senate in the place of <mhs:persRef ref="troup-george">Col<hi rend="superscript"
					>l.</hi> Troup</mhs:persRef>, resigned, and after taking his Seat in the Senate was appointed
				on the military Committee and its Chairman. Some weeks since I was directed by the
				President to offer him the Mission to Spain, which he immediately declared his
				readiness to accept— Notwithstanding which he has retained his Seat in the Senate,
				and been among the busiest and most ardent adversaries of <mhs:persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General Jackson</mhs:persRef>. With a
				Spanish Mission before him this was neither very proper nor very delicate, and three
				or four days since he concluded to abandon the prosecution, and gave notice to the
				President that he was ready to be nominated for Spain. I presume he obtained this
				appointment through the influence of <mhs:persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford</mhs:persRef>— He is
				a man of some talents but very indolent. <mhs:persRef ref="meigs-clara">His wife</mhs:persRef> is daughter to <mhs:persRef ref="meigs-josiah">Josiah Meigs</mhs:persRef>, who
				is at the head of the land Office, and niece to <mhs:persRef ref="meigs-return">Return Jonathan Meigs</mhs:persRef>, Post Master
				General— These are both Offices having extensive patronage scattered all over the
				Union, and their influence was perhaps not without its weight in forming M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford’s estimate of Forsyth’s fitness for the
				Mission to Madrid— I have not formed a very exalted opinion of Forsyth’s principles
				or of the loftiness or delicacy of his character— He was last winter a seeker for
				office, and at the same time effecting a high and even uncivil tone of independence
				of the Executive in his Speeches in the House of Representatives. This Winter he
				offered himself in the Newspapers, to the Legislature of Georgia, soliciting to be
				elected their Senator, and <pb type="ms" n="39"/>after accepting the offer of an
				appointment by the Executive, to Spain, he has pursued in the Senate a course,
				suited above all things to embarrass the executive in his transactions with Spain.
				These are not the actions of a trusty man—yet I hope he will hereafter prove to be
				one.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-17">
		<head>17 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-17"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams Family Finances</note>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
			<note type="subject">Seminole Wars</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>17. VII:15.</dateline> <mhs:persRef ref="chauncey-isaac">Commodore Chauncey</mhs:persRef> came to my house this Morning to
				make enquiries, what compensation was to be allowed him for having acted as a
				Commissioner in concluding the last Treaty with Algiers. Also whether any
				compensation from the public for having had <mhs:persRef ref="shaler-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Shaler</mhs:persRef>
				the Consul General at Algiers, about eight months on board his ship in the
				Mediterranean— And for having given a passage to some other of the Consuls in
				Barbary. Shaler left Algiers on account of the plague and has now been more than a
				year absent from his Post— Chauncey says he was eight Months of the time on board of
				his ship— I could not answer these questions but told him I would submit them to the
				<mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President</mhs:persRef>. He said he had heard the allowance for acting as a Commissioner on a
				similar occasion was one thousand dollars— I told him that I thought the charge of
				maintenance for the Consuls on board his ship must be at their own expence, and not
				at that of the public— I called at the Metropolis Bank, and renewed one of my Notes
				there. Met there <mhs:persRef ref="tayloe-james">Col<hi rend="superscript">l. </hi>Tayloe</mhs:persRef> who took me in his
				Carriage and left me at the President’s. He told me he had between sixty and seventy
				thousand dollars in the Stock of this Bank, and he wanted me to give him a power to
				vote for my shares; intimating that <mhs:persRef ref="vanness-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Van Ness</mhs:persRef> the
				President, who now has my power, voted with it to suit his own purposes. That he not
				only used freely and to the utmost extent all the credit that he could obtain for
				himself in the Bank, but that he exerted it for others, some of whom were not
				altogether safe— I was told last Summer that Tayloe, would endeavour to get my power
				away from Van Ness. <mhs:persRef ref="forsyth-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth</mhs:persRef> came to the Office to
				enquire how and when it was expected he should depart upon his Mission to Spain— I
				told him we should wish him to go as soon after the rising of Congress as he
				conveniently could; but I should not have time before then to prepare his
				instructions; the substance of which would entirely depend upon the issue of the
				Negotiation upon which I am now engaged with <mhs:persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</mhs:persRef>. I
				told him what the present state of that Negotiation was, and the flattering
				prospects of a favourable conclusion that it offers— He said he supposed <mhs:persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General
				Jackson’s</mhs:persRef> late campaign had contributed to produce this result; and I told him I had
				no doubt it had, very largely. The remark struck me as singular coming from him;
				after the part he has been taking in the Committee of the Senate against Jackson for
				those very proceedings— We attended the Drawing-Room this Evening at the
				President’s. It is to be the last for the Season, and was much crowded with company.
				There was such a choak up of Carriages in the yard; that we were there nearly if not
				quite an hour before we could get up to the door; and with no small danger of having
				the Pole of a Carriage behind ours, through the pannel upon us. Among the company at
				the drawing-room was my old Senatorial Colleague and antagonist <mhs:persRef ref="pickering-timothy">Timothy Pickering</mhs:persRef>;
				and the old ex-Consul and Chargé d’Affaires at S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi>
				Petersburg, <mhs:persRef ref="harris-levett">Levett Harris</mhs:persRef>.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-18">
		<head>18 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-18"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Health and Illness</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>18. VII:</dateline> <mhs:persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</mhs:persRef> came to the Office,
				and brought me a draught of the Treaty in Spanish; as he said according to the
				counter-project offered by me, modified by the discussions which have taken place by
				the intervention of the French Minister <mhs:persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hyde de
				Neuville—</mhs:persRef> Onis himself has for the last ten days been confined to his house by
				chilblains, and this was the first time of his coming out. Upon reading over his
				project however, I found he had made some variations from the agreement as settled
				with De Neuville— He had in particular assumed the middle of the rivers for the
				boundaries, instead of the western Bank of the Sabine, and the Southern Bank of the
				Arkansaw— I told him we should not agree to this; when to my astonishment he told me
				that he had spoken of it last Evening at the Drawing Room to the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President</mhs:persRef>; who had
				promised him that we would agree to the middle of the Rivers— I made no reply, but
				merely took it with the rest for reference. He importuned me again very obstinately
				to omit the limitation of five Millions of dollars to the sum assumed by the United
				States to be paid to their Citizens for claims upon Spain, and finding me
				inflexible, he at last urged that at least we should agree to take six Millions for
				the limitation; which however I still resisted— He insisted upon restoring the item
				of renunciation by the United States of all claims which have been presented at the
				Department of State, or to the American Minister at Madrid since the Convention of
				1802— <pb type="ms" n="40"/>I had intended the 4<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>item
				as a substitute, but he reminded me that the fifth had been originally a proposal on
				our part, in my Letter of 31. October last. I answered that it had not then been
				accepted, and was afterwards withdrawn— But he replied that it had been again
				offered by me on the renewal of the Negotiation, and indeed it includes some cases,
				upon which the Government is in some degree pledged to interfere and which are not
				provided for in the other items. I took it for reference. With regard to the Article
				concerning the grants of Lands he claimed an entire confirmation of all grants prior
				to the 24<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>of January 1818. with a formal annulment of
				those made since then—that is those made last Winter, to the <mhs:persRef ref="alagon-unknown">Duke of Alagon</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="punonrostro">Count
				Punon Rostr</mhs:persRef>o and <mhs:persRef ref="vargas-pedro">Vargas</mhs:persRef>. I told him we could not agree to give by the Treaty any
				validity to grants which they would not have without the Treaty. They should be as
				valid to us, as they were to the <mhs:persRef ref="ferdinand-vii">king of Spain</mhs:persRef>; and not more valid— We should not
				disturb bona fide holders—but it certainly could not be the intention of Spain that
				the Treaty should sanction frauds— He said there were some grantees who had been
				long in possession, under condition of cultivating the Lands within prescribed time—
				Many of them had been prevented by the late circumstances of the Nation and the
				Revolutions in Europe from completing their Settlements within the times prescribed
				and according to the tenour of the grants— Such bona fide possessors, would
				certainly never be molested in their possessions or deprived of them by the Spanish
				Government though possibly by the rigorous rules of the judicial tribunals they
				might be held to have forfeited their titles. It would not be just to leave such
				persons exposed to the discretionary effect of a new system administered by
				strangers, and in ceding the Country Spain was bound to provide for their being
				quieted in the tenour of their Estates. He therefore asked that such persons might
				have to complete the cultivation required as a condition of their grants, the time
				allowed them by the grants, reckoning it to commence from the ratification of the
				Treaty— I said the United States would have no wish to disturb bona fide holders
				under such circumstances, and immediately drafted an amendment of the Article to be
				referred to the President; and to which Onis assented. With regard to the privilege
				to Spanish vessels for twelve years at S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Augustine and
				Pensacola—he said we ought to have extended it also to Tampa-Bay; which he was sure
				would be a place of great consequence and of extensive trade within five years—
				After these explanations I took his Spanish Copy, and our Counter-project modelled
				conformably to it, to be presented for consideration to the President— <mhs:persRef ref="strong-harvey">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Harvey Strong</mhs:persRef> of New-York, was at the Office; to
				solicit the appointment of Consul at Glasgow and Greenock—with recommendations from
				<mhs:persRef ref="tompkins-daniel">Vice-President Tompkins</mhs:persRef>, and several other respectable persons. We had at our house
				this Evening a party, and Ball, of about two hundred persons— The company broke up
				about Midnight.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-19">
		<head>19 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-19"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>19. VII:15.</dateline> Cabinet meeting at the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</mhs:persRef> to consider the
				amended project of a Treaty with Spain and the modifications still desired by <mhs:persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> de Onis</mhs:persRef>— A proposal had some time ago been started by
					<mhs:persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford</mhs:persRef> that instead of the Banks of the Red
				River, a chain of mountains running as he says parallel with the river about twenty
				or thirty miles South of it, should be assumed as the boundary from the North west
				corner of Louisiana, to the point where the line is to strike across the red river,
				North to the Arkansaw river. Crawford’s reason for this proposal was, that mountains
				are better boundaries than rivers— But as there is no certainty that there is any
				chain of mountains running South of and parallel with the red river, great part of
				the contemplated line, as the chain marked on <mhs:persRef ref="melish-john">Mellish’s</mhs:persRef> Map, to which the Treaty is
				to refer, extends only a small part of the way, as no one knows how the range of
				mountains there really runs, or at what distance from the river, and as the whole
				idea was an afterthought produced after the proposal made in writing by me to take
				the rivers for the limits, Onis had invariably resisted the alteration, and objected
				even against any discussion of it— Some day this week, <mhs:persRef ref="graham-george">George Graham</mhs:persRef> came to the
				President and told him that there were as many as two hundred American families
				settled on the South side of the red river, and that there would be great
				dissatisfaction with the Treaty in the Southern and Western Country, if we should
				not obtain both sides of that river— Crawford and <mhs:persRef ref="calhoun-john">Calhoun</mhs:persRef>, entered warmly into this
				suggestion, and I was directed to make another trial whether Onis would not take the
				Mountains instead of the river for a boundary. I made the attempt without effect,
				but not without use; for it appeased Onis’s last throes against taking the Banks of
				the Rivers instead of their middle, for boundaries. At the Meeting this morning, I
				remarked that Onis still insisted upon having the middle of the rivers, but I did
				not notice his assertion that the President at the Drawing Room had promised him <pb
					type="ms" n="41"/>we would agree to it. I proposed that we should adhere to the
				principle of owning the rivers and all the islands in them ourselves, and of course
				to having the banks and not the middle of the rivers for boundaries. The President
				thought it was not a point upon which we should endanger the conclusion of the
				Treaty. <mhs:persRef ref="thompson-smith">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thompson</mhs:persRef>, Secretary of the Navy asked if Onis
				would agree to take the banks of the rivers, rather than break off. I said he
				would—he must—he had substantially agreed to it already— Then, said Thompson, insist
				upon it by all means— The President acquiesced, as did Calhoun and <mhs:persRef ref="wirt-william">Wirt</mhs:persRef>— Crawford
				was not present, being confined to his house and bed, by illness. On the proposed
				clause for permitting the navigation of the rivers, to the Sea <unclear>to</unclear> the inhabitants
				of both Nations, M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun immediately objected— He
				said it would give the Spaniards even of Europe the right of Navigating up and down
				the Mississippi; at least as high as the mouth of the red river— It was of course
				agreed that this should not be admitted, and I amended the draught so that the
				common freedom of Navigation, should be co-extensive only with the boundary itself
				on the rivers. The article relating to the grants of Land in Florida, as drawn up
				after my conference with Onis yesterday, was considered, discussed and approved. The
				time allowed to grantees in possession to <hi rend="italic">complete</hi>, their
				settlements according to the tenour of their grants, is to commence from the
				signature of the Treaty— And to make the grants valid, it will be required not only
				that the grantees should be in possession, but that they should have begun making
				the settlements required by the grants— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun said
				this article was now put upon a more satisfactory footing than it had been at any
				time before— All the other Articles as proposed to be amended were approved, but it
				was determined not to omit the limitation to five Millions of dollars, of the sum to
				be paid by the United States, for the claims upon Spain. The Meeting was over
				between two and three O’Clock; I immediately went over to my Office and sent for
					<mhs:persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> De Neuville</mhs:persRef> the French Minister, who shortly
				afterwards came. I told him that having referred to the President all the
				alterations suggested to the project of the Treaty which had been before considered;
				he had again this morning taken the opinion of the members of the Administration—
				That it had been agreed to adopt all the alterations desired by M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis excepting two, one of which was that the middle
				of the rivers should form the boundary, and their Navigation <hi rend="italic">to
					the Sea</hi>, be common, to the inhabitants of both Nations; and the other that
				the limitation of the sum to be paid by the United States for claims upon Spain, to
				five Millions of Dollars, should be struck out. To these two proposals it had been
				determined that we could not accede. It was now necessary for M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis to come to his determination— The conclusion
				could no longer be postponed. I should send the draught as now adjusted, immediately
				to him; and we must sign the Treaty next Monday; or the President must send a
				message to Congress on Tuesday, informing them of the unfinished state of the
				Negotiation; that they may take such measures as they deem advisable before the
				close of the Session of Congress. De Neuville said he was afraid Onis would consider
				the encouragement he had received, to expect that we should yield these points, as a
				pledge, which gave him a right to insist upon them— He, de Neuville had made great
				use of the right of Navigation to the Sea, to prevail upon Onis to give up on other
				points— Onis would be more tenacious of it because it was a stipulation which he
				could make much of in reconciling his Government to the Treaty— I had said I should
				not refuse to remove the limitation of five Millions if the President would consent
				to it, and Onis assured him that the President had promised him at the Drawing-Room,
				that we would take the middle of the rivers for the boundaries, instead of the
				banks— I replied that I had given no encouragement to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Onis, which he could justly consider as a pledge, that any of his proposed
				alterations would be accepted— I had taken them all merely and avowedly for
				reference to the President. I had said that for myself I should not inflexibly
				object to allowing the right of Navigation, of the inhabitants on the rivers to the
				sea, or to omitting the limitation of five Millions, yet I could in no wise answer
				for the decision of the President on those points— But I had invariably insisted on
				having the banks of the rivers for the boundaries; and should certainly consent to
				no others. As to what the President may have said to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Onis at the Drawing room, I was confident Onis had not correctly understood his
				meaning. He had I presumed used some general expression, that we should not break
				off upon small points of difference, but certainly without intending that Onis
				should understand it as a promise upon any particular point in discussion. <pb
					type="ms" n="42"/>But, what right had M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis, to
				speak upon this matter to the President at the Drawing Room, at-all— He was treating
				with me— I had sent him a copy of my full-powers, and received the copy of his. The
				Secretary of State was the officer with whom this negotiation was to be conducted,
				and all immediate applications to the President by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Onis concerning it were improper— I had taken and should take no notice of it in
				this instance; but the President himself would be much and justly displeased, if he
				had reason to think, that a complimentary expression of politeness used by him, in
				answer to a remark made to him by a foreign Minister at the Drawing Room, was to be
				construed into an abandonment of an important principle in a pending Negotiation— De
				Neuville said that was perfectly just— I added further that M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Onis could have no right to consider me pledged for the acceptance of
				any thing in his last proposals, since he himself after agreeing to accept the
				draught as amended after the last discussion between him De Neuville and me, had
				come to me the next morning, and proposed several very important changes to it—and
				particularly that with respect to the grants of lands—by which we were to allow the
				grantees advantages which they would not be entitled to if the Cession should not be
				made— He said that was true; but they were such as ought to be secured to the
				grantees. They were to operate only upon bona fide holders, in possession, and who
				after having begun to make their settlements had been prevented by circumstances
				beyond their controul from completing them— This was mere justice, and was what the
				Spanish Government in making the cession was really bound in duty to secure to them—
				I admitted that it was just; and said that was the motive upon which we had assented
				to it— Still it was a departure from that to which Onis had before assented; and
				thus took from him all pretence that we were pledged to any other of the proposed
				alterations. He then left me saying he would see M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis
				immediately, and endeavour to prevail upon him to accept the Treaty, as we now
				proposed it.— In the Evening there was a Ball at <mhs:persRef ref="gales-joseph">Gales’s</mhs:persRef>, which I attended with <mhs:persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi
					rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</mhs:persRef> and <mhs:persRef ref="buchanan-mary">Mary Buchanan</mhs:persRef>. De Neuville was there; and
				told me that Onis would call upon me to-morrow Morning. He had concluded to sign the
				Treaty— There remained only two or three words in our draft which he wished to have
				altered or explained— The rumours of the Treaty’s being on the eve of conclusion,
				and the curiosity to know something of it, were so general among the company at the
				Ball, that it was with difficulty that I could parry the various questions put to me
				about it— Members of Congress have many of them a pretension that they are entitled
				to know every thing that is doing by the Executive, and others holding to the
				doctrine that Republics have no secrets, think themselves equally authorized to
				question the Secretary of State, how his Treaty with Don Onis comes on— Some had
				already been informed that we were to sign on Monday; while others anticipating the
				fact had heard that we had signed already— We came home from Gales’s, about
				midnight, in a Snow-Storm.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-20">
		<head>20 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-20"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Louisiana Purchase</note>
			<note type="subject">West, The</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>20. VI:15.</dateline> <mhs:persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</mhs:persRef> came this morning to my house, and told me
				that he must accept the Treaty as now prepared, since we would have it so; though he
				still thought we ought to give up the limitation of the five Millions, and the banks
				for the middle of the rivers as the boundaries. I observed there was no time left
				for further discussion; and we had yielded so much that he would have great cause to
				commend himself to his court, for what he had obtained— He said I was harder to deal
				with than the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President</mhs:persRef>, and he must say as a suitor once said to <mhs:persRef ref="philip-iv">Philip 4<hi
					rend="superscript">th</hi></mhs:persRef>—Sire, your Majesty has no influence with the Minister
				of Grace and Justice; for he refuses me, what you have granted— However, to say no
				more of that, said the Chevalier, I want an explanation of the words in your 8<hi
					rend="superscript">th. </hi>Article “shall <hi rend="italic">complete</hi> them”
				referring to the conditions of the grants to be fulfilled— I said they meant that
				this privilege should be confined to bona fide holders of Lands, in actual
				possession, and who have at least begun the settlements required by their grants—
				That it should at once quiet honest grantees who had been prevented from
				accomplishing entirely the conditions required of them, and defeat all fraudulent
				grantees who have neither made nor intended to make any settlement— He said that was
				sufficient— Then in the 11<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>Article, the word <hi
					rend="italic">exonerating</hi>, seemed not quite explicit enough, to discharge
				Spain entirely from the claims in question; he wished therefore to add the words
				“and considering them entirely cancelled,”—to which I immediately agreed— He then
				observed that in the Treaty of 27. October 1795. the king of Spain was first named
				in the copies of the Treaty, in both languages; but now in my draft of this Treaty
				the United States were first named. I told him that in the early Treaties concluded
				by the United States they had not been tenacious, of what is called the alternative
				in naming the parties— But as it was a point always made between the European
				Powers, the Government of the United States had determined not to suffer a departure
				from that usage to grow into a custom against them; and I shewed him the Convention
				of 3. July 1815 in which the alternative had been adopted, with the assent of Great
				Britain; and the Louisiana Conventions, in which it was adopted with France. He said
				he would not make an objection on <pb type="ms" n="43"/>this account, but as the
				precedent of the former Treaty, named the <mhs:persRef ref="ferdinand-vii">king of Spain</mhs:persRef> first, in both languages,
				and as published here, in the United States, and as his Government was apt to be
				exceedingly punctilious on these occasions; he should perhaps on signing the Treaty,
				deliver me a Protest, against its being hereafter ever drawn into a precedent— I
				told him I certainly could not receive any such protest, for that so far from its
				not being drawn into a precedent, it was our express intention that it should be a
				permanent precedent; and I could assure him we should never hereafter conclude a
				Treaty with Spain, without insisting upon the same mode of signature; and the same
				alternative first naming of the parties— He then acquiesced upon the principle but
				enquired how the alternative should be introduced— Whether by naming the United
				States first, in both languages, in our copies of the Treaty, and the king of Spain
				first in both languages, in the copies to be sent to Spain; or whether the United
				States should be first named in their own language, and the king of Spain, in the
				Spanish of all the copies of the Treaty, whether to be kept here or to go to Spain.
				He had brought a printed copy of a Treaty between Spain and England, with king of
				Spain named first in both languages; of which it was apparent that the copies
				possessed in England named the king of Great-Britain first; also in both languages—
				I told him, I thought it would be best that all the copies should be alike; and
				therefore the United States should be named first in their own language, and the
				king of Spain, first named in Spanish—which I shewed him was conformable to the
				arrangement in our Louisiana Conventions. To which he assented— We agreed also that
				we should both sign the Treaty in both Languages—I first and he second in the
				English copy, and he first, and I second in the Spanish copy— It was then agreed
				that the Treaty should be executed in triplicate copies on both sides— That we would
				have at least two copies prepared on Monday Morning; when he would come at ten
				O’Clock to the Office of the Department of State— We would then execute them, so
				that our copy may be sent on the same day to the Senate— The other four copies may
				be made out as soon afterwards as possible, and when ready we can sign and seal
				them— At the Office I had a long visit from <mhs:persRef ref="king-rufus">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Rufus
				King</mhs:persRef>, the Senator; with whom I had a conversation of two hours upon political
				affairs. His principal object was to communicate his opinion that it would be most
				expedient not to accept the Article relative to trade with the British West-India
				Islands and Colonies in North America, which was suspended for reference to the
				Government of the United States, at the conclusion of the Convention with
				Great-Britain of 20. October last. On this subject M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Otis entertains an opinion directly opposite to that of M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> King; and is very anxious that the Article should be accepted. I told
					M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> King the state of the Negotiation with Spain, and
				that a Treaty would be sent in to the Senate on Monday. I mentioned to him in
				confidence the substance of its principle articles; with which he declared himself
				well satisfied— <mhs:persRef ref="">Captain James Barron</mhs:persRef> came also to the Office and asked of me a
				written certificate, that in June 1814. he had applied at Gothenburg for a passage
				to the U.S. in the John Adams, for the purpose of obtaining employment in the public
				Service during the War— I promised to draw up for him a certificate to that effect,
				to be ready to-morrow Evening or Monday Morning— I dined at <mhs:persRef ref="strother-john">Strother’s</mhs:persRef> Hotel, with
				the Mess, consisting of <mhs:persRef ref="otis-harrison">Otis</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="ogden-david">David A. Ogden</mhs:persRef> and <mhs:persRef ref="mclane-louis">M’Lane</mhs:persRef> of Delaware. <mhs:persRef key="bagot-charles">Bagot</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="correa-joseph">Correa</mhs:persRef>,
				<mhs:persRef ref="greuhm-frederick">Greuhm</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="thompson-smith">Clay Thompson</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="calhoun-john">Calhoun</mhs:persRef>, and some others were there. From thence I went and
				passed the Evening at <mhs:persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">Hyde de Neuville</mhs:persRef> the French Ministers 2 [symbols]. Found <mhs:persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</mhs:persRef>, and <mhs:persRef ref="buchanan-mary">Mary Buchanan</mhs:persRef>
				there. It was a Ball, and the company numerous. <mhs:persRef ref="sanford-nathan">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Sanford</mhs:persRef>, Senator from New-York spoke to me of the Spanish Negotiation. I told him
				the Treaty would be sent in to the Senate on Monday, and mentioned generally its
				principal stipulations. He said he believed there would be an opposition to it, in
				the Senate; particularly to admitting the Sabine river as the boundary westward of
				the Mississippi; but he did not think the opposition would prevail— I said if it
				should, they would send us back the Treaty and we would try if we could do better—
				It was past midnight when we came home.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-21">
		<head>21 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-21"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">West, The</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>21. VIII:</dateline> <mhs:persRef ref="trimble-david">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Trimble</mhs:persRef>, one of the
				Members of the House of Representatives from Kentucky came this morning and had a
				conversation of more than two hours with me; entering into all the depths and
				meanderings of Kentucky State <pb type="ms" n="44"/>Politicks; and explaining to me,
				all the projects and counterprojects of and for <mhs:persRef key="clay-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Clay</mhs:persRef>,
					<mhs:persRef ref="johnson-richard">Col<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi> R. M. Johnson</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="pope-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				John Pope</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="mckee-samuel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M’Kee</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="sharp-solomon">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Sharpe</mhs:persRef>, and others, the result of all which is that he wishes. <mhs:persRef ref="robertson-george">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> George Robertson</mhs:persRef> now one of his colleagues to be
				appointed Governor of the New Territory of Arkansaw now in the process of being
				carved out from the Missouri Territory by an act of Congress. He left with me
				several Letters some to the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President</mhs:persRef>, some to Robertson, and some to himself,
				recommending Robertson; I promised to lay them all before the President. <mhs:persRef ref="brent-daniel">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Brent</mhs:persRef> also come to inform me of the progress made in
				preparing the Treaty. The two copies making out at Onis’s, will be ready to-morrow
				morning. <mhs:persRef ref="purviance-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Purviance</mhs:persRef> was engaged all day in copying at
				the Department Office; and <mhs:persRef ref="young-moses">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Young</mhs:persRef> at his house. I
				received last Evening two Letters from <mhs:persRef ref="eppes-john">J. W. Eppes</mhs:persRef>, chairman of the Committee of
				Ways and Means of the Senate, asking various explanations of the estimates from the
				Department of State for the Appropriations of the present year— I had given most of
				them yesterday to <mhs:persRef ref="king-rufus">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> King</mhs:persRef>, who is a member of the
				Committee, and who had mentioned to me that such explanations were desired— M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Eppes’s Letters mentioned that the Committee were to
				meet to-morrow Morning, before the Senate would be in Session, and that he wished
				then to have my answer— I went therefore to the Office, for the first time of a
				Sunday, and drafted an answer to Eppes’s Letters, giving him all the explanations
				they required. I found Daniel Brent and Purviance at the Office; at work; left the
				draft of the Letter to Eppes, to be sent to him at nine O’Clock to-morrow Morning—
				As I was returning home, I was overtaken by <mhs:persRef ref="otis-harrison">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Otis</mhs:persRef>, and
					<mhs:persRef ref="mclane-louis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M’Lane</mhs:persRef> of Delaware— Otis observed that it was
				usual enough at that hour, (between five and six) to meet me returning home from my
				Office, on week-days; but he presumed I was not coming from thence now— I told him,
				I was; but that it was not a usual practice of mine— He might attribute it to one of
				his colleagues in the Senate who late last Evening, had called upon me for a Report
				to be made early to-morrow Morning; which Report had required my attendance at my
				Office this day. He replied by intimating a suspicion that other and more important
				business had contributed to call me to my Office on a Sunday— But as he was not
				alone, I did not appear to notice his insinuation— There are incidents in life,
				which by the means of associations have an interest in them not belonging to
				themselves, and which language can scarcely express. Otis will probably never forget
				this accidental meeting of me in the Street this day. He immediately and justly
				inferred where I came from, and what I was doing. He would have been puzzled to
				account for the effect of it on his own feelings; and I am ashamed of the
				involuntary exultation which it produced upon mine— When I came home I found <mhs:persRef key="smith-catherine-johnson">M<hi
					rend="superscript">rs</hi> W. S. Smith</mhs:persRef> here— She dined and spent the Evening
				with us.<mhs:persRef ref="ingalls-william"> D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ingalls</mhs:persRef> and <mhs:persRef ref="bailey-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Bailey</mhs:persRef> called while we were at dinner, but did not come in.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-22">
		<head>22 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-22"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Bank of the United States</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Religion</note>
			<note type="subject">Supreme Court</note>
			<note type="subject">Treaty of Ghent</note>
			<note type="subject">West, The</note>
			<note type="subject">Westward Exploration and Expansion/Westward Migration/Manifest Destiny</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>22. V:45.</dateline> I made a Certificate for <mhs:persRef ref="barron-james">Captain Barron</mhs:persRef>; but had not
				time to get a copy of it written, before I was obliged to go to the Office. <mhs:persRef ref="onis-louis">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</mhs:persRef> came at eleven, with <mhs:persRef ref="stoughton-francis">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Stoughton</mhs:persRef>, one of the persons attached to his Legation— The two copies
				of the Treaty made out at his house were ready; none of ours were entirely finished—
				We exchanged the original full powers on both sides, which I believe to be the
				correct course on the conclusion of Treaties; though at Ghent, and on the conclusion
				of the Convention of 3. July 1815. the originals were only exhibited, and copies
				exchanged. I had one of the copies of the Treaty, and M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Onis the other— I read the English side which he collated, and he the Spanish side
				which I collated. We then signed and sealed both copies, on both sides; I first, on
				the English, and he first on the Spanish side: some few errors of copying, and even
				of translation were discovered, and rectified. It was agreed that the four other
				copies should be executed in two or three days, as soon as they are all prepared.
					M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis took with him his executed copy of the
				Treaty, and I went over with ours to the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</mhs:persRef>. The Message and Documents to
				be sent with it to the Senate, were all prepared; but the President’s brother, and
				private Secretary <mhs:persRef ref="monroe-joseph">Joseph Jones Monroe</mhs:persRef> was gone to the Capitol, with another message
				to Congress, and <mhs:persRef ref="gouverneur-samuel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Gouverneur</mhs:persRef> <mhs:persRef ref="monroe-elizabeth">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>rs</hi> Monroe’s</mhs:persRef> nephew who also resides at the President’s and acts
				occasionally as his Secretary was likewise abroad. The President requested me to ask
					<mhs:persRef ref="brent-daniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> D. Brent</mhs:persRef>, to take the Message with the Treaty to
				the Senate, which he did— <mhs:persRef ref="ingalls-william">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ingalls</mhs:persRef> of Boston called at
				the Office, and had some conversation with me— He brought me Letters from <mhs:persRef ref="degrand-peter">Degrand</mhs:persRef>— I
				sent him an invitation to dine with us next Thursday; but he leaves the city to
				return to Philadelphia to-morrow. As I was going home from my Office I met <mhs:persRef ref="fromentin-eligius">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Fromentin</mhs:persRef>, a Senator from Louisiana, and asked him if
				the Treaty had been received by the Senate— He said it had—was read; and as far as
				he could judge had been received with universal satisfaction. I dined with <mhs:persRef ref="simkins-eldred">Eldred
				Simkins</mhs:persRef>, a member of the House of Representatives, from South-Carolina, at <mhs:persRef ref="dowson-alfred">Dowson’s</mhs:persRef>
				Hotel—many of the members of both houses of Congress lodge there, and among them
				<mhs:persRef ref="smith-samuel2">General S. Smith</mhs:persRef> of Baltimore, with <mhs:persRef ref="smith-margaret">his wife</mhs:persRef>, and her <pb type="ms" n="45"/>sister,
				<mhs:persRef ref="spear-nancy">Miss Spear</mhs:persRef>, who were at table. There was much conversation upon the subject of the
				Treaty this day signed, as well as upon the arguments now delivering before the
				Supreme Court of the United States, and the debates in the House of Representatives
				on the subject of the Bank— I attended this Evening by invitation, a Ball at
				Georgetown in celebration of <mhs:persRef ref="washington-george">Washington’s</mhs:persRef> Birth-day— <mhs:persRef ref="otis-harrison">Otis</mhs:persRef> went with <mhs:persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi
					rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</mhs:persRef> and <mhs:persRef ref="buchanan-mary">Mary Buchanan</mhs:persRef>, and sent his Chair for me to
				Dowson’s— I went in it alone. The President was at the Ball— I introduced D<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Ingalls to him— We remained till after supper, and
					<mhs:persRef ref="schuyler-mary">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Schuyler</mhs:persRef> was assigned by the managers to me, to
				lead down to the supper room— She is the wife of a member of Congress from the State
				of New York, and a daughter of my old acquaintance <mhs:persRef ref="sawyer-micajah">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Sawyer</mhs:persRef> of Newbury-Port— We came home immediately after the Ladies had supped, but it
				was near one in the Morning when I closed the day; with ejaculations of fervent
				gratitude to the giver of all good— It was perhaps the most important day of my
				life— What the consequences may be of the compact this day signed with Spain, is
				known only to the all wise, and all beneficent disposer of Events; who has brought
				it about in a manner utterly unexpected, and by means the most extraordinary and
				unforeseen. Its prospects are propitious and flattering in an eminent degree— May
				they be realized by the same superintending bounty that produced them! May no
				disappointment embitter the hope, which this event warrants us in cherishing; and
				may its future influence on the destinies of my Country be as extensive and as
				favourable as our warmest anticipations can paint it! Let no idle, and unfounded
				exultation take possession of my mind as if I could ascribe to my own foresight or
				exertions any portion of the Event— It is the work of an intelligent, and all
				embracing cause. May it speed as it has begun; for without a continuation of the
				blessings already showered down upon it, all that has been done will be worse than
				useless and vain— The acquisition of the Florida’s has long been an object of
				earnest desire to this Country— The acknowledgment of a definite line of boundary to
				the South Sea, forms a great Epocha in our History. The first proposal of it in this
				Negotiation was my own; and I trust it is now secured beyond the reach of
				revocation— It was not even among our claims by the Treaty of Independence with
				Great Britain— It was not among our pretensions under the purchase of Louisiana—for
				that gave us only the range of the Mississippi and its waters— I first introduced it
				in the written proposal of 31. October last, after having discussed it verbally both
				with Onis and <mhs:persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">De Neuville</mhs:persRef>. It is the only peculiar and appropriate right acquired by
				this Treaty, in the Event of its Ratification. I record the first assertion of this
				claim for the United States as my own; because it is known to be mine, perhaps only
				to the members of the present Administration; and may perhaps never be known to the
				public; and if ever known will be soon and easily forgotten. The provision by the
				acquisition of the Florida’s of a fund for the satisfaction of claims held by
				Citizens of the United States upon the Spanish Government has been steadily pursued
				through a Negotiation, now of fifteen years standing. It is of the whole Treaty,
				that which in the case of the ratification, will have the most immediate and
				sensible effects. The change in the relations with Spain, from the highest mutual
				exasperation and imminent War, to a fair prospect of tranquility and of secure peace
				completes the auspicious characters of this transaction in its present aspect; which
				fills my heart with gratitude unutterable to the first Cause of all. Yet let me not
				forget that in the midst of this hope there are seeds of fear— The ratification of
				Spain is yet uncertain, and may by many possible events be defeated— If ratified,
				many difficulties will certainly arise to clog the execution of the Treaty. There is
				some discontent at the acceptance of the Sabine as our boundary from the gulph of
				Mexico to the red river— The amount of claims upon Spain which we have renounced and
				cancelled will prove five times greater than the sum which we have assumed to pay;
				and that, when finally ascertained will leave all the claimants dissatisfied— For
				although our scale of comparison is between what they will obtain under the Treaty,
				and what they would have obtained from Spain, without it; that is, absolutely
				nothing; yet theirs will be between their entire <hi rend="italic">right</hi> which
				we cancel, and the very imperfect indemnity which we secure for them. The Florida’s
				will be found in all probability less valuable in possession than when merely
				coveted— Most of the lands will be found to have been granted, and it may be doubted
				whether enough will be <pb type="ms" n="46"/>left to raise from their proceeds even
				the five Millions to be paid for the claims. A watchful eye; a resolute purpose, a
				calm and patient temper, and a favouring Providence will all be as indispensable for
				the future, as they have been for the past in the management of this Negotiation—
				May they not be found wanting.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-23">
		<head>23 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-23"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Press</note>
			<note type="subject">Seminole Wars</note>
			<note type="subject">West, The</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>23. VII:</dateline> A continual succession of visitors, at my house and at
				the Office, absorbed the whole of this day. <mhs:persRef ref="trumbull-john">Col<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi>
				Trumbull</mhs:persRef> came to enquire about the payment for his Picture of the Declaration of
				Independence. By his contract made with <mhs:persRef key="rush-richard">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Rush</mhs:persRef> under a
				Resolution of Congress, he was to paint four large pictures for which he was to
				receive 32000 dollars; of which 8000 in advance, and 6000 upon the delivery of each
				picture. He received the advance, and now calls for 6000 dollars, the second
				payment— It is a precious bargain for him; and a most liberal one to say the least
				on the part of Congress. I told him he should have the money as soon as the
				appropriation Act should have past; which will be in two or three days. He said he
				wished to leave the City, and would leave an order to receive the money for him,
				with <mhs:persRef ref="king-rufus">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> R. King</mhs:persRef>—to which I agreed. <mhs:persRef ref="johnson-richard">Col<hi
					rend="superscript">l. </hi>R. M. Johnson</mhs:persRef> came to recommend <mhs:persRef ref="thornton-william">D<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Thornton</mhs:persRef> as an Agent to be sent to Buenos-Ayres; and
				<mhs:persRef ref="allison-burgess">Doctor Allison</mhs:persRef>, to be superintendent of the Patent Office— <mhs:persRef ref="pegram-john">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Pegram</mhs:persRef>, a Member of the House of Representatives from Virginia came to
				the Office to recommend a Printer in that State for the publication of the Laws of
				the United States, but as the Law allows only the appointment of three in each
				State, and those for Virginia, were all appointed in December I could not gratify
				his wish— <mhs:persRef ref="mitchell-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Mitchell</mhs:persRef>, late Consul at Martinique came to
				shew me a Letter from his successor <mhs:persRef ref="marean-silas">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Marean</mhs:persRef> announcing
				a new regulation in that Island, which prohibits foreigners from doing business
				there as merchants. <mhs:persRef ref="forbes-john">Forbes</mhs:persRef> came to renew his solicitations for a place; with
				recommendations from sundry members of Congress. He wishes to be Marshal for the
				District of Massachusetts, if <mhs:persRef ref="prince-james">Prince</mhs:persRef>, the present Marshal would resign— Or a
				Commissioner of Bankrupts, if the Act should pass; or Commissioner under the Spanish
				Treaty, or any thing that will give him bread in his old age. He is one of the many
				hard strugglers through life, doomed to seek for public office, as a refuge from
				private failure and misfortune— A <mhs:persRef ref="lawrence-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lawrence</mhs:persRef> came
				concerning a claim on Spain, and <mhs:persRef ref="morton-marcus">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Morton</mhs:persRef>, member of
				Congress from Massachusetts, with a <mhs:persRef ref="webb-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Webb</mhs:persRef> an applicant
				for some appointment— Immediately after dinner I received a Note from <mhs:persRef ref="trimble-david">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Trimble</mhs:persRef> requesting to see me this Evening or to-morrow
				Morning. I sent him word I would see him immediately. He came, and spent a couple of
				hours with me, urging anew the appointment of <mhs:persRef ref="robertson-george">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Robertson</mhs:persRef> as Governor of the Arkansaw territory— <mhs:persRef ref="sharp-solomon">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Sharpe</mhs:persRef>, another Kentucky candidate formerly a member of Congress, has been
				recommended by <mhs:persRef ref="calhoun-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Calhoun</mhs:persRef>, and a <mhs:persRef ref="butler-unknown">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Butler</mhs:persRef> has also been suggested to the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President</mhs:persRef> as a suitable person—
				But Trimble holds that man will be acceptable to Kentucky but Robertson, and that
				his appointment will give universal satisfaction to all parties. I promised to
				report his representations faithfully to the President— In the Washington City
				Gazette of this day there was an Article announcing that the President had yesterday
				communicated to the Senate a Treaty concluded with the <mhs:persRef ref="onis-luis">Spanish Minister</mhs:persRef>; and then
				noticing the western boundary line from the Sabine; says it is thought the Senate,
				will not without strong opposition, relinquish the territory between the Sabine,
				&amp; the Rio del Norte—and concludes “We trust the Senate will not agree to it.”
				This paragraph comes directly or indirectly from <mhs:persRef key="clay-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Clay</mhs:persRef>. <mhs:persRef key="crawford-william-harris">Crawford</mhs:persRef> told me some time since that <mhs:persRef ref="elliott-william">Elliot</mhs:persRef> the Editor of the Gazette boasted
				that Clay was one of the writers for the paper, and although it has not supported
				him against <mhs:persRef ref="jackson-andrew">Jackson</mhs:persRef> upon the Seminole War questions, it has been almost neutralized
				upon them since Clay unexpectedly took his side against Jackson and in every other
				respect is still devoted to him. The paragraph of this day is an experiment— An
				attempt to rouse an opposition against the Treaty in the Senate, with a view to
				produce a division of sentiment upon it, in the public mind.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-24">
		<head>24 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-24"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Native Americans</note>
			<note type="subject">Press</note>
			<note type="subject">Religion</note>
			<note type="subject">Seminole Wars</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>24. VI:45.</dateline> Calling at the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</mhs:persRef> this morning I met there
					<mhs:persRef ref="forsyth-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth</mhs:persRef>, and <mhs:persRef ref="storer-clement">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Storer</mhs:persRef>, member of the Senate from New-Hampshire enquiring of the latter whether the
				Senate had acted upon the Treaty with Spain, he said they would take it up this day,
				the papers connected with it having been printed yesterday— I observed that as an
				Act of Congress founded upon it would be necessary before the close of the Session,
				there was no time to be lost, and he promised to have it called up this day— The
				President said that <mhs:persRef ref="holmes-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Holmes</mhs:persRef> chairman of the Committee
				of foreign relations had been with him, and was desirous of introducing the Bill
				which would be necessary to provide for carrying the Treaty into execution. He
				desired me therefore to see him as soon as the Senate should have passed upon the
				Treaty. They did pass upon it this day; and <hi rend="italic">unanimously</hi> gave
				their advice and consent to its ratification. I sent a message to M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Holmes requesting him to call at my house to-morrow
				Morning; and prepared a draught of a Message to both houses of Congress, to be sent
				to them with copies of the Treaty in our own language. The President said M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth had concluded to go to Spain immediately, and
				to take the Treaty <pb type="ms" n="47"/>with him for the purpose of exchanging the
				Ratifications— He would now go in a public ship; the first that could be ready to
				take him; and he would return home next Autumn to settle his private affairs in
				Georgia, and take out his family to Spain— I sent to <mhs:persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Onis</mhs:persRef> requesting him to call at the Office; which he immediately did. I told him that
				as and Act of Congress would be necessary to authorize the President on the
				ratification of the Treaty to take possession of the ceded territories, copies of it
				must be communicated to both houses of Congress, by which measure it would probably
				soon be published in the Newspapers; and I asked if he would have any objection to
				its being published immediately— He said he was apprehensive that in that case his
				Government would receive it through the newspapers, before they would receive it
				officially from him; which would expose him to be censured. He therefore hoped the
				publication would be deferred as long as possible— I told him that M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth would take out the President’s ratification,
				and would go in the course of a few days— He said he should send <mhs:persRef ref="zamorana-unknown">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Zamorano</mhs:persRef> with his copy of the executed Treaty, and
				asked if a passage could not be given him in the same ship with M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Forsyth. I promised to mention it to the President,
				and told him I could venture by anticipation to assure him that M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Zamorano should have a birth— We agreed to execute the
				four additional copies of the Treaty to-morrow. On returning home to dinner I found
				at the house <mhs:persRef ref="rogers-lloyd">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lloyd Rogers</mhs:persRef> of Baltimore, who dined
				with us. After dinner we went to Strothers Hotel and attended the French Readings
				and Recitations of <mhs:persRef ref="artiguenave-joseph">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Artiguenave</mhs:persRef>. He recited seven or
				eight Stanza’s of <mhs:persRef ref="rousseau-john">Rousseau’s</mhs:persRef> Ode a la Fortune—the Sonnet Scene from the Misanthrope,
				a Scene from Marius à Minturne, and the frenzy of Orestes from the Iphigenia en
				Tauride of Guymon de la Touche— He introduced the several subjects with some
				critical and rhetorical remarks— His declamation was pretty good; but not of the
				highest character— There were less than one hundred persons present—the greater
				number consisting of the foreign Ministers and their families— I had omitted to
				mention that Artiguenave called upon me on Monday, with a Letter of recommendation
				from <mhs:persRef ref="humphreys-anne">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Humphreys</mhs:persRef> of Boston— Another visitor at the
				Office on Monday was <mhs:persRef ref="worcester-samuel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Worcester</mhs:persRef>, the clergyman of
				Salem, who was introduced to me by <mhs:persRef ref="silsbee-nathaniel">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Silsbee</mhs:persRef>, and who
				brought me a Letter of recommendation from <mhs:persRef ref="gray-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> William
				Gray</mhs:persRef> of Boston— He had some charge from a missionary Society concerning certain
				Cherokee Indians who are now here, occupied upon a Treaty for the cession of their
				Lands to the United States with a view to their removal to the Western side of the
				Mississippi— M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Worcester asked my assistance to promote
				certain objects of schooling and religious instruction for these unfortunate
				Indians, if it should become a subject of consideration to the Administration
				generally; I readily promised it, but oppressed as I have been with business of my
				own department, I have not even had time to acquire an exact knowledge of what this
				is— It was a remarkable circumstance that on this day when the Senate unanimously
				advised and consented to the ratification of the Treaty with Spain, a Committee of
				five members, of the same body made a Report severely censuring <mhs:persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General Jackson</mhs:persRef> for
				the transactions of his campaign in Florida, which have been among the most
				immediate and prominent causes that produced that Treaty— This is the Committee from
				which Forsyth withdrew, and upon which <mhs:persRef ref="eppes-john">Eppes</mhs:persRef> was appointed to take his place— <mhs:persRef ref="lacock-abner">Lacock</mhs:persRef>
				of Pennsylvania as chairman made the Report with which <mhs:persRef ref="burrill-james">Burrill</mhs:persRef> of Rhode-Island, and
				Eppes concurred— <mhs:persRef ref="king-rufus">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> King</mhs:persRef> of New-York, and <mhs:persRef ref="eaton-john">Eaton</mhs:persRef> of
				Tennessee were opposed to making the Report, the sole object of which is to defame
				Jackson; for it concludes without offering any Resolution, and it was not even
				intended that there should be a debate upon the acceptance or rejection of the
				Report.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-25">
		<head>25 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-25"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Florida Annexation</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
			<note type="subject">Louisiana Purchase</note>
			<note type="subject">U.S. Constitution</note>
			<note type="subject">West, The</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>25. V:45.</dateline> Snow all the morning. <mhs:persRef ref="holmes-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Holmes</mhs:persRef>, chairman of the Committee of foreign Relations, called at my house; and upon
				examination of the Treaty with Spain took minutes of the Bill to be offered to
				Congress, for carrying it into execution, provisionally tell the end of the next
				Session of Congress, the act to take effect from the time of the exchange of the
				ratifications of the Treaty— We recurred to the Precedents of the first act by which
					<mhs:persRef ref="jefferson-thomas">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Jefferson</mhs:persRef> was authorised to take possession of
				Louisiana, and of that by which an appropriation was made, and authority given to
					M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Jefferson to appoint Commissioners during the
				recess, under the Convention of <pb type="ms" n="48"/>the 11<hi rend="superscript"
					>th. </hi>of August 1802 with Spain— Holmes minuted as objects to be embraced by
				the Bill, the power to take possession of the Territories; of providing for sending
				the Spanish troops to the Havanna, and of appointing Commissioners during the recess
				of the Senate; to be nominated at their next meeting— At the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</mhs:persRef>, I gave him
				the Letters which <mhs:persRef ref="trimble-david">Trimble</mhs:persRef> had put into my hands recommending <mhs:persRef ref="robertson-george">Robertson</mhs:persRef>, as Governor
				of the Arkansaw territory; and repeated to him the uneasiness expressed by Trimble,
				as being felt in the western Country, and particularly in Kentucky, at the supposed
				neglect of them in making appointments to office; and his observations upon the good
				effect in supporting and encouraging the friends of the President and his
				Administration, which would follow the appointment of Robertson— The President
				intimated a doubt whether Robertson could be appointed consistently with the
				Constitution which prescribes, Article 1. Section 6. Paragraph 2. that No Senator,
				or representative shall, during the time for which he was elected, be appointed to
				any civil office under the authority of the United States, which shall have been
				created, or the emoluments whereof shall have been increased during such time”— This
				will certainly preclude the appointment of Robertson, if the nomination is to be
				made before the close of the present Session of Congress— At the Office <mhs:persRef ref="onis-luis">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Onis</mhs:persRef> came with <mhs:persRef ref="stoughton-francis">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Stoughton</mhs:persRef>, and we executed the four remaining copies of the Treaty, after carefully
				reading and collating them with our copy already executed— Onis took two of the
				copies now signed and sealed, and two of them remain at the Office. We had a company
				of Gentlemen to dine with us— Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> <mhs:persRef ref="artiguenave-joseph">Artiguenave</mhs:persRef>,
				<mhs:persRef ref="bailey-john">Bailey</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="fuller-timothy">Fuller</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="hale-salma">Hale</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="harris-levett">Harris</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="ingersoll-charles">Ingersoll</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="law-thomas">Law</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="little-peter">Little</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="parrott-john">Parrott</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="rogers-lloyd">Rogers</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="silsbee-nathaniel">Silsbee</mhs:persRef>,
				<mhs:persRef ref="upham-nathaniel">Upham</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="vaughan-benjamin">Benj<hi rend="superscript">n.</hi> Vaughan</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="vaughan-petty">Petty Vaughan</mhs:persRef>, and 
				<mhs:persRef ref="worcester-samuel">Worcester</mhs:persRef>—
					Mess<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> <mhs:persRef ref="butler-thomas">Butler</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="clagett-clifton">Claggett</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="crawford-joel">Joel Crawford</mhs:persRef>, 
				<mhs:persRef ref="ingalls-william">Ingalls</mhs:persRef>,
				<mhs:persRef ref="sampson-zabdiel">Sampson</mhs:persRef> and 
				<mhs:persRef ref="shaw-henry">Shaw</mhs:persRef> were invited, but sent excuses, or did not come. <mhs:persRef ref="buchanan-mary">Mary Buchanan</mhs:persRef> was
				unwell, and did not dine with us. The company broke up, between nine and ten.— The
				Treaty was sent this day by Message, to Congress.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-26">
		<head>26 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-26"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Commerce</note>
			<note type="subject">Elections, Presidential (1820)</note>
			<note type="subject">Seminole Wars</note>
			<note type="subject">Supreme Court</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>26. VII:</dateline> A day, such as grow up and spread over my present
				station in life, with weed-like fertility. A day of visitors and applicants— First
				came to my house a man by the name of <mhs:persRef ref="sherburne-unknown">Sherburne</mhs:persRef>; who was for sometime Consul, or
				Consular agent, and now highly self-recommended as a Commissioner of the claims
				under the Treaty with Spain. He also recommends <mhs:persRef ref="sherburne-unknown2">his Son</mhs:persRef>, to be the Secretary of that
				Commission— He told me that <mhs:persRef key="crawford-william-harris">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crawford</mhs:persRef>, who was well
				acquainted with his character and with his conduct in France, would also recommend
				him— He kept me above an hour, explaining to me how exceedingly convenient it would
				be to him, to his affairs and to his family to have the Office, and telling me all
				his family concerns, removals and projects— I asked him if he understood the Spanish
				language, and observed it would be a qualification very useful to a Commissioner
				under this Treaty— He said no, he was not acquainted with the Spanish; but he
				thought he could easily learn enough of it in a short time, to answer every
				necessary purpose— This Gentleman was followed by <mhs:persRef ref="roberts-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
				Roberts</mhs:persRef> the Senator from Pennsylvania, who came and introduced to me, <mhs:persRef ref="binns-john">M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> John Binns</mhs:persRef>, Editor of the Democratic Press; an evening
				Newspaper published at Philadelphia, &amp; a personage of high political consequence
				in that State. Binns is publishing a splendid Edition of the Declaration of
				Independence, engraved upon copper-plate, surrounded by the arms of the thirteen
				original States, and surmounted with Portraits of <mhs:persRef ref="hancock-john">Hancock</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="washington-george">Washington</mhs:persRef> and <mhs:persRef ref="jefferson-thomas">Jefferson</mhs:persRef>—
				He has now come here with his engraver to take fac simile’s of the signatures; and
				asked permission to take them in one of the Offices at the Department; to which I
				consented. He was afterwards at the Department, and brought one of the impressions
				of his Plate; which I saw— At the Office, came successively <mhs:persRef ref="mcrae-alexander">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> M’Rae</mhs:persRef>, who was last Spring appointed Consul at Amsterdam, but has not
				yet concluded whether he will accept the appointment or not. He is a particular
				personal friend of the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">Presidents</mhs:persRef> and a man of talents and information. He gave me
				some account of the political intrigues which have been working at Richmond upon the
				affairs of the Seminole War, and <mhs:persRef ref="jackson-andrew">General Jacksons</mhs:persRef> transactions. Some of the men of
				the highest standing and greatest abilities in Virginia, are personal rivals and
				adversaries of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Monroe— His popularity however
				throughout the State, supported by the weight and influence of M<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Jefferson, and <mhs:persRef ref="madison-james">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Madison</mhs:persRef>
				, is so great that they do not venture to assail him directly and in front— They are
				therefore constantly on the watch for any occasion upon which they can attack his
				administration, and Jackson and the Seminole War have furnished the best of which
				they have yet been able to avail themselves. They are hitherto unsuccessful. But the
					<pb type="ms" n="49"/>misfortune of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Monroe is,
				that the Virginians have discovered it will be necessary to render his
				administration unpopular for the purpose of securing the next Presidency to a
				Virginian— <mhs:persRef ref="buck-charles">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Buck</mhs:persRef> the Consul general from Hamburg came
				to take leave, upon his return to Philadelphia, and to express his gratification, at
				the Act which has past extending the revocation of discriminating duties to the
				Ships and Shipments of Hamburg. <mhs:persRef ref="appleton-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Appleton</mhs:persRef> came to
				solicit again the nomination as Secretary of Legation to Rio de Janeiro— <mhs:persRef ref="everett-unknown">D<hi
					rend="superscript">r</hi> Everitt</mhs:persRef> has concluded it seems, not to accept; and the
				President and <mhs:persRef ref="graham-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Graham</mhs:persRef> are both willing that Appleton
				should be appointed— This Evening, I attended with <mhs:persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
				Adams</mhs:persRef> and <mhs:persRef ref="buchanan-mary">Mary Buchanan</mhs:persRef>, a Ball, given by subscription of Members of Congress
				together with some of the principal Inhabitants of Washington and Georgetown, to
				<mhs:persRef ref="bagot-charles;bagot-mary">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Bagot</mhs:persRef>, upon
				their intended return to England. This is a compliment which has never before been
				paid to any foreign Minister, and which is not universally approved; as a bad
				precedent— We attended by invitation. The Ball was at <mhs:persRef ref="crawford-william">Crawford’s</mhs:persRef> Hotel in Georgetown
				and numerously attended. The managers assigned to me <mhs:persRef ref="wirt-elizabeth">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
				Wirt</mhs:persRef>, the <mhs:persRef ref="wirt-william">Attorney General’s</mhs:persRef> wife, to lead down to supper— There was a single toast
				given after supper; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript"
					>rs</hi> Bagot; upon which he rose and returned thanks in a short, modest and
				suitable speech—upon which the band of music struck up, God save the
				king—immediately followed by Yankee-doodle. An association about as incongruous, as
				any that I ever witnessed. We came home immediately after supper, but it was near
				one of the Morning. <mhs:persRef ref="middleton-henry">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Middleton</mhs:persRef> spoke to me of <mhs:persRef ref="johnson-william">Judge
				William Johnson</mhs:persRef> of the Supreme Court; who has obtained through <mhs:persRef key="crawford-william-harris">Crawford’s</mhs:persRef> influence
				the appointment of Collector of the customs at the Port of Charleston, and after
				getting the place will neither accept nor decline it; but is negotiating to keep his
				Office as judge upon condition that <mhs:persRef ref="johnson-james2">his brother</mhs:persRef>, a very good Carpenter at Charleston
				shall be appointed Collector in his stead— Middleton says that Johnson is one of
				Crawford’s electioneering machines. That previous to the Legislative caucus of 1816.
				Johnson who was then here, sitting as a judge of the Supreme Court, took great,
				constant and indecent pains in support of Crawford against M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Monroe. That he solicited and urged <mhs:persRef ref="lowndes-william">Lowndes</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="calhoun-john">Calhoun</mhs:persRef> and him Middleton
				in behalf of Crawford; although they were all in favour of M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Monroe. He says that Johnson’s brother is utterly unfit for the Office
				of Collector, and is not a little incensed at this intrigue to obtain the
				appointment for him.</p>
		</div>
	</div>

	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-27">
		<head>27 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-27"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
		</bibl>

		<div type="docbody">

			<p><dateline>27. VII:</dateline> <mhs:persRef ref="artiguenave-joseph">Artiguenave</mhs:persRef> called on me this Morning, and said he
				proposed to have his second evening of French Readings and Recitations next Friday.
				That among the selections that he had used at Boston, Philadelphia and Baltimore was
				a piece very good for declamation, from the <mhs:persRef ref="raynal-guillaume">Abbé Raynal’s</mhs:persRef> History; upon the
				Declaration of Independence of this Country. He had been advised to deliver it here;
				but as the <mhs:persRef key="bagot-charles">British Minister</mhs:persRef> and the members of his Legation might attend, and
				perhaps consider it offensive, he had thought it best to take my advice—upon it,
				before coming to his determination. He brought me one of his pamphlets containing
				this piece, which I read, and then told him that I saw no objection to his speaking
				it; unless he considered as such the chance which it might produce, of his losing
				the members of the English Legation from among his hearers. That was for his
				consideration— He said he would deliver it. <mhs:persRef ref="vanness-william">Judge Van Ness</mhs:persRef> of New-York came, and
				brought a Letter from <mhs:persRef ref="fisk-jonathan">Fisk</mhs:persRef> the District Attorney there; in answer to that which Van
				Ness at his own suggestion and with the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President’s</mhs:persRef> assent had written to him— That
				Letter gave Fisk the alternative, either of resigning his Office, or of under going
				an enquiry to be instituted by the President, upon the numerous charges against
				Fisk, of gross and habitual intemperance. Fisk’s answer is ambiguous and
				evasive—complains of his having enemies; offers to resign next May, if the President
				insists upon it, declines passing the ordeal of enquiry, unless by persons of his on
				nomination, and wearies himself in efforts to escape from the confession of that
				which he has not the courage to deny— Judge Van Ness left the Letter with me, to be
				shewn to the President. I met the Secretary of the Navy, <mhs:persRef ref="thompson-smith">M<hi rend="superscript"
					>r</hi> Thompson</mhs:persRef> at the President’s. He considers Fisk’s case as too notorious
				to bear the test of an enquiry. I dined with <mhs:persRef ref="lowndes-william">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lowndes</mhs:persRef>,
				the member of Congress from South Carolina; with the <mhs:persRef ref="correa-joseph">Abbe Correa</mhs:persRef>, <mhs:persRef ref="hopkinson-joseph">Hopkinson</mhs:persRef>, and two
				or three others— Lowndes is going to spend the Summer in Europe; and is to embark
				immediately after the termination of the Session of Congress. Evening with <mhs:persRef key="adams-louisa-catherine">M<hi
					rend="superscript">rs</hi> Adams</mhs:persRef> and <mhs:persRef ref="buchanan-mary">Mary Buchanan</mhs:persRef> at the <mhs:persRef key="hyde-de-neuville-jean">French Minister’s</mhs:persRef>—a
				Ball.</p>
			
		</div>
	</div>
	
	<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-28">
		<head>28 February 1819</head>
		<bibl>
			<author>JQA</author>
			<date type="creation" when="1819-02-28"/>
			<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
			<note type="subject">Adams-Onis Treaty</note>
			<note type="subject">Foreign Relations</note>
		</bibl>
		
		<div type="docbody">
			<p><pb type="ms" n="50"/><dateline>28. VII:</dateline> <mhs:persRef ref="cardelli-pietro">Cardelli</mhs:persRef> came this Morning to solicit again my
				influence with the <mhs:persRef key="monroe-james">President</mhs:persRef> to prevail upon him to sit for his bust. I promised to
				speak for him as soon as the Session the Congress should be closed— <mhs:persRef ref="brent-daniel">Daniel Brent</mhs:persRef> was
				also here— I received a Note from <mhs:persRef ref="holmes-john">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Holmes</mhs:persRef>, Chairman of
				the Committee of Foreign Relations, observing that the Committee had proposed a Bill
				for carrying the Spanish Treaty into Execution, without including the appointment of
				Commissioners, and enquiring what sum would be necessary to fill the blank of the
				appropriation. I went up to the Hall of the House of Representatives, and heard a
				Sermon from a <mhs:persRef ref="smith-unknown3">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Smith</mhs:persRef>. Holmes was there, and after the
				service was over I told him I had received his Note, but had made no estimate of the
				sum that would be necessary for the appropriation— He said he supposed from twenty
				to thirty thousand dollars would be sufficient, to which I assented— I asked him why
				the Committee had omitted giving the authority for the temporary appointment of the
				Commissioners during the recess— He said they had thought the appointment would not
				be necessary before the next Session of Congress; and the Treaty itself stipulated
				for the Sanction of the Senate to the appointments— I replied that the convention of
				1802 had done the same yet the Law of 1804. had authorised temporary appointments by
				the President; and in this case it might have the effect of enabling the
				Commissioners to meet, and of course to accomplish their business half a year sooner
				than if the organization of the Commission must be deferred till the next Session of
				Congress. The difference therefore will be equivalent to half a years interest upon
				the whole amount of the claims which by the delay will be lost if interest is
				allowed upon the claims, to the public, and to the claimants, if interest is not
				allowed. Holmes concurred in these opinions and said he would to-morrow Morning
				propose to the Committee to offer a new Section as an Amendment to the Bill,
				authorizing the appointment of the Commissioners, by the President, during the
				recess, and if the Committee should decline proposing it, he would offer it himself
				to the House as an Amendment— <mhs:persRef ref="hopkinson-joseph">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hopkinson</mhs:persRef> &amp; <mhs:persRef ref="forbes-john">Forbes</mhs:persRef>
				spent the Evening with us.</p>
			
		</div>
	</div>
			<div type="entry" xml:id="jqadiaries-v31-1819-02-xx">
				<head>Day</head>
				<bibl>
					<author>JQA</author>
					<date type="creation" when="1819-02-xx"/>
					<editor role="transcription">Neal Millikan</editor>
				</bibl>
				
				<div type="docbody">
					<!-- This is a summary entry without a date.-->
					
			<p><dateline rend="italic">Day.</dateline> In its general distribution similar to the last Month.
				But is has been more oppressed with important occupations, and more interrupted by
				dissipation— We have oftener had company at home; and I have been oftener in company
				abroad— Dinners, Evening parties and Balls, have absorbed an unreasonable portion of
				my time; but I have indulged myself and others by mingling in Society, partly to
				repel a reproach which has been very assiduously spread abroad, of a reserved,
				gloomy, unsocial temper, as belonging to my character, and partly because the
				Session of Congress is to close so soon, that the sacrifice to frivolity will be
				short. Evening companies make late hours, and the loss of the morning invariably
				follows that of the Evening. Besides the heavy and increasing breaches thus produced
				in my Correspondence, this mode of life runs up a long arrearage in my journal. I
				have accordingly written nothing since the 11<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>How
				often has this complaint been made! How frequent, and how fruitless my Resolutions,
				upon retrieving arrears to incur them no more. The extreme importance in the record
				of my life, of this month now just expired has been the very occasion which
				prevented the narrative from keeping pace with the occurrence of Events— I complete
				the record 28 [symbols] at precisely four weeks distance from
				the time, and with a hand which I can scarcely call my own— Yet a few days, and it
				will no longer hold a pen— Let the will, outlast the power of the fingers; and let
				me find consolation for unavoidable inability, in the recollection of accomplished
				good.</p>
		</div>
	</div>
</div>
