<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title/>
				<author>Joseph Zavoral</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition><date>2018-06-08</date></edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<p>unknown</p>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Converted from a Word document</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
					<label>DOCX to TEI</label>
				</application>
				<application ident="MHS-WETVAC" version="0.1b">
					<label>MHS-WETVAC</label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<listChange>
				<change><date>2018-09-24T18:29:22Z</date><name>Joseph Zavoral</name></change>
			</listChange>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="doc" xml:id="RBT00091">
				<bibl>
					<date type="creation" when="1832-08-28"/>
					<author>RBT</author>
					<name type="transcriber">Joseph Zavoral</name>
					<date type="transcription" when="2015-06-04"/>
				</bibl>
				<div type="docbody">
					<head>To [Thomas Ellicott?]</head>
					<opener>
						<dateline>Frederick County Augt 28. 1832</dateline>
						<salute>My Dear Sir</salute>
					</opener>
					<p>I am glad to hear you have been so well employed &amp; hope to receive the
						communication you promise at an early day. - Any thing you may direct to me
						to Bruceville Frede - rick County will come safe. I have in the hope of
						benefitting Mrs. Taney’s health taken a small farm house, which is within a
						mile and a half of Bruceville, &amp; shall probably continue where I now am
						until Some time in October. She is I hope recovering - but it is very slowly
						- &amp; the symptoms are not always favourable.</p>
					<p>When you write again, do me the favour to say whether Mr. Jno. Ridgely has
						deposited any money to my credit in your Bank within the last six or eight
						weeks. - I have not <pb n="2"/> yet received the dividends due me in July -
						Please have them passed to my credit.</p>
					<p>I ought not perhaps to mingle Bank matters with other concerns. - So as I do
						not choose to have my letters to you used as vouchers for Bank transactions
						- if it is necessary to give an order to transfer my dividends to my acc.
						have the goodness to let me know &amp; I will Send it in proper form.</p>
					<p>The elections in Kentucky &amp; Missouri show that the President &amp;
						directors of the Bank of the U. States are not likely to gain much by the
						conflict which they have taken to much pains to produce. - The days of the
						Bank are now numbered &amp; the country saved from its corrupting influence,
						provided the public attention is kept fixed upon the subject &amp;
						continually enlightened by communications from those who understand it. -
						Have you made up your mind as to the scheme of a national Bank or Banks,
						which could discharge with commerce the duties of fiscal agents and have no
						power or privacy beyond what is necessary to perform this duty? - Is any
						such national Bank necessary? <pb n="3"/>Cannot the duties be performed by
						the state Banks? - Upon these points I am most anxious to see your notions.
						- They are great national questions which no one can decide but one who is
						like yourself familiar with banking &amp; commercial operations, and who has
						the courage to form his opinions upon his own experience &amp; observations,
						&amp; does not slavishly adopt the theories which others have put forward. </p>
					<closer>With best wishes I am Dr. Sir truly your friend<signed> R. B.
							Taney</signed>
					</closer>
				</div>
				<div type="docback">
					<note type="source"><p> ALS</p>
						<p>DLC</p>
						<p>(MMC 2191, Folder 3)</p>
					</note>

				</div>
			</div>
			<!-- //document -->
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
