<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title/>
				<author>Patricia Kalayjian</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition><date>2018-08-19</date></edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<p>unknown</p>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Converted from a Word document</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
					<label>DOCX to TEI</label>
				</application>
				<application ident="MHS-WETVAC" version="0.1b">
					<label>MHS-WETVAC</label>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
		  <change><date>2018-09-24T18:07:28Z</date><name>Patricia Kalayjian</name></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="doc" xml:id="CMS1804-04-01">
				<bibl>
					<date type="creation" when="1804-04-01"/>
					<author>Catharine Maria Sedgwick</author>
					<name type="transcriber">Pat Kalayjian</name>
					<date type="transcription" when="2018-08-19"/>
				</bibl>
				<div type="docbody">
					<head>Catharine Maria Sedgwick to Theodore Sedgwick I</head>
					<opener>
						<dateline>Stockbridge 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> April 1804 </dateline>
						<salute>Dear Papa</salute>
					</opener>
					<p>Mama <add>has</add> received your letter &amp; you will easily believe me,
						when I tell you that she was very much rejoiced, for we have been not a
						little anxious about you. Mama has I think been much better since you left
						home, than she was previous to it. We are all looking for the time, &amp;
						anticipating the pleasure which your arrival will give us. &amp; indeed it
						is almost the only topic we have <add>for conversation</add>. Stockbridge is
						<unclear/> barren of incidents to call forth either wonder, admiration, or
						disgust. I sincerely believe there has nothing happened since your
						departure, that has affected as much, or appeared of half the importance, as
						some wounds which old Bose has received; &amp; though we feared they would
						prove mortal: he is apparently in a state of convalescence; but I yet have
						my doubts whether the poor animal will survive to see his dear Master.</p>
					<p>Harry wrote us last week, and in his letter gave us an account of a rebellion
						that there has lately been in their class-- --. It seems one of the class
						was accused by the authority, of absenting himself from meeting in the
						afternoon -- He denied the charge-- but the President thinking <pb n="2"/>
						he had sufficient evidence to convict him, ordered him to appear at prayers
						to receive his punishment; but being advised by some turbulent members of
						the class not to obey his commands, he didnot attend prayers: The authority
						after consulting some time the next day rusticated him -- In the evening
						almost every member of the class retired to their rooms, and notwithstanding
						the tutors <supplied>interposed</supplied> they continued all the evening to
						make a most tremendous noise. The next day there were three sent home. Harry
						was not one of the rebels, he doesnot mention whether Robert was or not.
						Mama wishes you would be so kind as to purchase her the Bishops of London
						Lectures, delivered in Lent. I believe his name is Bieby Porteus<ptr
							type="noteRef" n="1" target="CMS1804-04-01-fn-1"/>. Mama thinks she
						shall want two pieces of <add>fine</add> Linen. Aunt Dwight has returned;
						and offers her kind remembrance. Our dear Charles has gone to Lenox. George
						is as good a boy as ever, &amp; sends his love to his <hi rend="underline"
							>dear</hi> Grandpapa. Joh has behaved extremely well -- I wish I could
						say as much of Cato. -- -- M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Allen is dead,
						&amp; M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
						<unclear/> is but just alive. -- -- I should not have delayed so long to
						write you, but I have been sick ever since you left us. <pb n="3"/></p>
					<p>2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> April </p>
					<p>The town meeting is over -- the Jacobins have carried the day -- -- they have
						a majority of 7 for Governor, 10 for lieutenant Governor &amp; Senator --
							M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Williams says there were at least 30
						people there whose faces he never saw before, and who he verily believes, if
						they were turned <add>out</add> of the house; and the doors have been shut
						upon them; they never would have found the way <add>home</add> for they were
						led there by our <hi rend="underline">wise</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline"
							>great</hi> men. . . . But their most diabolical act was endeavoring to
						lessen D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> West,s salary; <unclear/> fortunately
						they didnot succeed -- -- -- Thus you see my dear Papa I have become quite a
						politician; but I have <supplied>written</supplied> this merely for your
						information. -- --</p>
					<closer>Yours affectionately,<signed>C M Sedgwick <pb n="4"/></signed>
					</closer>
				</div>
				<div type="docback">
					<note type="source"><p><lb/>Document type. Letter</p>
						<p>Repository. Massachusetts Historical Society</p>
						<p>Collection. Catharine Maria Sedgwick I</p>
						<p>Condition. Some areas difficult to read because of ink bleed through;
							worn edges; tear.</p>
					</note>
					<note type="address"><p> </p>
						<p>Hon<hi rend="superscript">ble</hi> Theodore Sedgwick </p>
						<p>Boston</p>
					</note>
					<note type="notation"><p> Stockbridge April 3<hi rend="superscript">rd:</hi>
							Stockbridge is stamped; date is handwritten. (Postal Service.)</p>
					</note>
					<note type="notation"><p> Catharine M. Sedgwick/to her father 1804 (Dewey)</p>
					</note>
					<note xml:id="CMS1804-04-01-fn-1"><p> Beilby Porteus (8 May 1731 – 13 May 1809);
							Bishop of London, 1787-1809. Noted abolitionist.</p>
					</note>

				</div>
			</div>
			<!-- //document -->
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
