<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title/><author>Patricia Kalayjian</author></titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition><date>2018-06-20</date></edition></editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p>unknown</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Converted from a Word document</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<appInfo>
<application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<listChange>
<change><date>2018-07-20T19:26:37Z</date><name>Patricia Kalayjian</name></change></listChange>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader><text>
<body>
<p>New York Dec’ 15th 1810</p>
<p>I couldnot resist a certain impulsive motion towards my pen, when I heard that Gen’l ^W[hiton]^<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p> General Joseph Whiton of Lee, MA. See <ref target="https://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;GRid=105627930">https://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;GRid=105627930</ref></p>
</note><note place="end"/> was going this Evening, &amp; I involuntarily began to address my dear Charles-- I cannot say that I should not have done it with malice prepense,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p> Legal term for malice aforethought.</p>
</note> but the fact is I did it without any prepense at all. If I do not write more than ten lines, &amp; those not worth the reading, forgive me dear Charles, […] in consideration of an intolerable headache [&amp;] stupidity. [&amp;]Oh I am no philosopher. I deny the doctrine that pain is no Evil, &amp; hold that an effect must follow a cause, &amp; that if I have a headache, I must have a heartache too -- .  I presume our friend Mrs. Forbes has long before this dispelled the “dark clouds” that shrouded her purpose, &amp; made you al stare &amp; gape with amazement-- I think we shall soon get so accustomed at Stockbridge to the most wonderful wonders that the world ever wondered at that they will be no more strange to us than the rising and setting of the Sun-- We will write a new play which shall annihilate the separation of the rival Mothers &amp; the rival Queens, and call the rival Strangers. {{2}} And if you please dear Charles we will have an under plot. [W] There shall be a young man in all the pride of self confidence conquered at the very moment that he is toasting his security against the whole artillery of a young Lady’s charms-- You must supply me with the detail of incidents, &amp; I will furnish the denouement. -- --</p>
<p>We often wish my dear Brother that you was here, to partake in some of our pleasures &amp; to confer a great deal of happiness. But after all there is no place like that home that is adorned &amp; blessed with the presence of our beloved Parent. -- -- I have just received Papa’s letter. I am sincerely sorry that the judge left my letter for I think it might have been of service in [guarding] Papa. I am extremely concerned to hear of Mrs. Sedgwick’s indisposition, tell my dearest Papa, &amp; tell [Mrs] her that if I am sure I could be of service &amp; comfort to them, &amp; that if they wish it I will come home at any time --There are persons constantly going to Albany with whom I would willingly trust myself, &amp; with whom I think I could go very comfortably-- -- -- -- My dearest Papa must not withhold the expression of his wishes from any consideration of the difficulty of travelling far at this Season, for I do not fear it at all, &amp; even if I did, I hope I could conquer trifles to gratify them. -- -- -- -- {{3}}</p>
<p>My feelings are all still interested for Mrs. Morgan -- -- -- -- I must take leave of you my dear Brother, for I have scarcely time to write a few lines to Eliza_</p>
<p>	Dear dear Charles may Heaven bless you all_ Adieu Ever [yrs]</p>
<p>						Catharine M. Sedgwick</p>
<p>I have got the letters I wrote to send by the Judge, &amp; shall forward them by Gen’l Whilton</p>
<p>Frances says I must scold you for your [ultimate] &amp; unkind silence—Indeed dear Charles it is very wrong in you -- -- -- {{4}}</p>
<p>Gen’l Whiton will confer a particular favor by delivering these letters immediately.</p>
<p>Mr. Charles Sedgwick</p>
<p>Gen’ Whiton Stockbridge</p>
<p>Marginalia include: vertical lines in left margin of pages 1 and 2, short vertical lines in mid-sentence and corresponding to a break in the marginal vertical line on page 2 that may indicate a passage not to be copied, “1810” and “C. M. Sedgwick, Dec. 15, 1810” on page 4.</p>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>