<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title/><author>Lucinda Damon Bach</author></titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition><date>2018-06-27</date></edition></editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p>unknown</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Converted from a Word document</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<appInfo>
<application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<listChange>
<change><date>2018-07-20T19:55:10Z</date><name>Lucinda Damon Bach</name></change></listChange>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader><text>
<body>
<div type="doc" xml:id="1818_1_22 CMS to Robert Sedgwick">
<head>Location and Description: SFP Box 78 Folder 19</head>
<bibl>
	<date type="creation" when="0000-00-00"/>
	<author>Location and Description: SFP Box 78 Folder 19</author>
	<name type="recip"></name>
	<name type="transcriber"></name>
	<date type="transcription" when=""/>
</bibl>
<div type="docbody">
<p>1818_1_22_CMS to Robert Sedgwick</p>
<p>Location and Description: SFP Box 78 Folder 19</p>
<p>4 page letter, tears from wax seal but no text affected. 4 images taken 11-12-16.</p>
<p>Stockbridge Jan’y [January] 22 1818.</p>
<p>Thanks to Him dear Robert who hath blessed your coming in and going out we have heard of your safe arrival in NYork. Tho we have yet no official communication on the subject </p>
<p>	We all mourned over your Hartford Circuit [?], and are now a little afraid that the vexation attending your return will host [? cast?] a shade over the visit whose memory is blessed to us_ It is not perhaps best that we should always glide over smooth waters, though I could wish dear Brother that peace might be commanded wherever it is your destiny to be_  _ _ It was sometime before we recovered our equilibrium after your departure_ Charles returned as sad as if he had performed the last rites to his last friend_ But at length by the aid of that Monitor which Teaches us to change repining into gratitude, and with the help of that good philosophy which tells us in whatsoever state we are, therewith to be content in short by humility as to our deserts, moderation in our wants, and gratitude for our possessions [?] in spirit of the withdrawing of that sun in whose beams we had all laughed and rejoiced, we recoverd [sic] in a few days our habitual cheerfulness _ _ _ I was afraid that you was not as happy here as you should have been, There were some circumstance about it that I could have wished different but I could not change them _ _ _ It may prove a blessing to Theodore that your visit happened just at that time _ _ He seems to feel the importance </p>
<p>[2] of recovering your good opinion_ I meant to have suggested to you that it might perhaps be best to say very little to Harry and Jane on the subject of Theodore’s misconduct, for it would naturally produce in them feeling, that would make his living with them an unhappiness to them I certainly would not wish to give them any false impression, but I wish to leave them free from any that Theodore might have a fair chance to win their good opinion_ I cannot but hope that placed under the authority of his Uncles, with the influence of their example and character, and participating the effects of the loveliness of our excellent and beloved sister, he will benefit as he ought and deserve ! [?] such advantages_  ) [?] We ought to pity him_ A malignant star reigned over his childhood_ and we my dear Robert, to whom all the ways of providence have been so benignant, whose infancy was so safe, and so blessed, we surely ought to make great allowances for the unhappy circumstance in which Theodore’s character was formed_ you and I know what they were _ _ _ _ I think he may yet be rescued and become an honor to his family_ What happiness is superior to that of saving a fellow Creature from vice and its horrid train and making him virtuous and respectable_ This is a critical period for Theodore_ He certainly does possess many qualities that make a very pleasant [Inmathe?] and his faults seem to me to be those of youth &amp; curable  ___________</p>
<p>[3] He has gone top Mrs Keef’s [?] _ _ _ Our Bombay friend [Luke Ashburner] called to see us yesterday for the first time since you left us_ He has had all his fine picturesque locks shorn_ and “Ichabod, Ichabod’ is written on every hair of his closely shaven crop [?]_ If I had been Madame de Stael I certainly should have wept over such a loss to the fine-arts, or rather I should have said I did_ Mr. A enquired very particularly after you and as he spoke the gleaming of his luminous eye proved how much pleasure you had given him_ </p>
<p>	Fanny has gone upon a Church Crusade, she left her very best love for you and Jane, and Hal_ How is Mary Jones? _ Do you know whether Mrs Banyer ever received a letter from me? If she did not, I wish she may be apprised that I wrote one_ I hope to hear from you on Saturday, and very soon from my dear Jenny. As to Harry I never expect to hear from him. Mrs Elisabeth Rowe’s mode of Correspondence is revived _ _ We are all well_ Love to Aunt Effy_ _ Adieu my dearest Brothers _</p>
<p>	May Heaven’s best blessing attend you_</p>
<p>		Yours ever CMS _</p>
<p>[written sideways in upper right margin]</p>
<p>Lest you should not be very well versed in Judaic love, I will inform that Ichabod means “the glory is departed”</p>
<p>[4]  paid [?]</p>
<p>[blurred, arched stamp] Stockbridge [?]</p>
<p>Robert Sedgwick Esq.</p>
<p>Law_ Buildings_ Vassar [?] St.</p>
<p>New York </p>
<p>[in another hand, upside down]</p>
<p>C. M. Sedgwick</p>
<p>Rcd Jan 26, 1818</p>

</div>
</div><!-- //document -->
</body>
</text>
</TEI>