<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title/><author>Patricia Kalayjian</author></titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition><date>2018-06-20</date></edition></editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p>unknown</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Converted from a Word document</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<appInfo>
<application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<listChange>
<change><date>2018-07-20T19:51:23Z</date><name>Patricia Kalayjian</name></change></listChange>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader><text>
<body>
<div type="doc" xml:id="1816.03.25CMStoFSWWETJune202018">
<head><lb/>{{TRANSCRIBER}} Pat Kalayjian<lb/>{{TRANSCRIPTION-DATE}} 2018-June-20<lb/>{{EDITION}} CMSOL<lb/><lb/>1816-March-25<lb/>CMS to Frances Sedgwick Watson</head>
<bibl>
	<date type="creation" when=""/>
	<author><lb/>{{TRANSCRIBER}} Pat Kalayjian<lb/>{{TRANSCRIPTION-DATE}} 2018-June-20<lb/>{{EDITION}} CMSOL<lb/><lb/>1816-March-25<lb/>CMS</author>
	<name type="recip">Frances Sedgwick Watson</name>
	<name type="transcriber"></name>
	<date type="transcription" when=""/>
</bibl>
<div type="docbody">
<opener>
<dateline><lb/>Albany March 25th 1816</dateline>
<p>	I have just heard of an opportunity to NYork tomorrow, and I cannot forbear writing a few lines to you, dear Sister, tho I am so benumbed with a violent cold in my head, that I can scarcely construct a sentence intelligibly-- -- No cold dear Frances can ever check the warm impulses of my heart towards you -- -- Your last letter inflicted a sad disappointment-- written expressly to come by Robert, it came without any explanation why he didnot bring it; &amp; tho we have had no expectation of seeing Robert here, yet the possibility of such an occurrence awakened thoughts that could not be spoken into peace-- -- -- Still as we hear nothing we hope to see him, and talk it over, as if words multiplied the chances of such a blessed event -- --To all you say of this beloved Brother, my most cordial amen is added-- -- Let us unite our prayers that he may be blessed in every way, that shall tend to perfect his eternal felicity-- -- -- I look forward to a very happy summer at S[tockbridge]-- Have we not always been happy there? -- I esteem it the greatest privilege of my life that I have been enabled in some humble measure to fill the place of our departed friends, by contributing my efforts to [more] preserve the attractions and enjoyments of that home-- And now dear Frances more than ever I discern the wisdom and goodness of Providence, in so ordering my life that I shall have it in my power, to add to the quiet &amp; happiness of yours-- -- The great disadvantage and the only reproach of a single life, is that we <pb n="2"/> poor spinsters are generally condemned to uselessness and Satan availing himself of his prerogative finds “mischief still, for idle hands to do” {{1}} -- -- It has always, and I pray it may ever be my happy destiny to have employment enough to keep me out of danger of falling into the folly of repining or the meanness of envying-- -- -- I hope my dear Frances you will come up the first of May-- -- I shall be ready to return to S at that time-- Let me hear from you soon-- -- Did you ever feel as if your head contained all the waters of the mighty deep-- for if you have you may pity me-- -- Mrs. […] has been passing the evening with us-- She left a kind remembrance for you-- -- I fear very much that she will leave this city as a residence-- She has decided to give up her house, and as none can be obtained that will suit her, and all the influence of her friends thrown in the scale of convenience will probably determine her to remain at NYork-- We are all impatient to see Sally, and I am sure she cannot benefit all her friends lumped together in NYork, so much as she will her Sister here, setting aside her other friends, who will greet her with wreathes of smiles-- -- -- We had Van Vecton  to preach for us yesterday-- I hear he is on his way to being married-- -- -- We have some commissions to trouble you with-- Mrs. Symmes has had a good deal of delicacy in troubling you, but I know dear Sister you will always take a pleasure in obliging this excellent woman-- Then to proceed-- She wishes you to get her 7 yds &amp; ½ of Florence black silk, which we hear is 8/ and […] a yard with [yours]-- Susan wants three pair of good cotton stockings <pb n="3"/> white-- and one pair of lead-colored silk-- not to exceed 20/, 1 pair of white kid gloves, &amp; 1 pair of dark for Susan, 1 pair of dark for Mrs S. and 1 pair for me_-- any color but purple-- -- I wish you to get me 6 yards of black &amp; white, very dark striped or plaid gingham for a common gown-- provided you can get it cheap-- Mrs Symmes wants 6 yards of any pretty gingham for a present to a little servant girl-- There, dear Sister I hope your patience is not exhausted-- We should have enclosed the money, but we are not quite sure of it arriving safely-- Therefore Brother R will please to furnish and charge all excepting mine to T Sedgwick Esq. </p>
<p>They keep every thing up at <lb/>the old prices-- Remember <lb/>me affectionately to your husband <lb/>and the children-- </p>
<p>Theodore Susan &amp; Mrs. Symmes […] <lb/>love_ Adieu dear Sister, yours as ever</p>
<p>CMS</p>
<postscript>To the above articles dear Sister you may add 2 yards of linen cambric to ruffle Theodore’s shirts -- -- -- -- --<lb/>Do not get the table-cloths I wrote to you for -- -- -- -- --</postscript>
<div type="addr"><p>{{SOURCE}}<lb/>Document type. Letter<lb/>Repository. Massachusetts Historical Society<lb/>Collection. Catharine Maria Sedgwick Papers I<lb/>Condition. Blots and wearing at folds<lb/><lb/> Mrs Frances P. Watson<lb/>Care of Mr. Eben’r Watson<lb/>New York</p>
</div>
<note xml:id="1816.03.25CMStoFSWWETJune202018-fn-1">type="fn"><p>{{NOTATION}} Vertical lines in left margin from middle of page 1 to middle of page 2; short vertical lines in mid-paragraph suggest the beginning and end of what Mary E. Dewey intended to include in her collected letters.<lb/><lb/>{{NOTATION}}C M S—1816/ To Mrs Watson/ The “spinster” life/ Copy on page 4 also likely by Dewey.<lb/><lb/><lb/> “For Satan always finds some mischief still for idle hands to do.” Isaac Watts (1674-1748).</p>

</note>
</div>
</div><!-- //document -->
</body>
</text>
</TEI>