<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title/><author>Lucinda Damon Bach</author></titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition><date>2018-06-11</date></edition></editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p>unknown</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Converted from a Word document</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<appInfo>
<application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
</encodingDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<listChange>
<change><date>2018-07-20T20:02:05Z</date><name>Lucinda Damon Bach</name></change></listChange>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader><text>
<body>
<div type="doc" xml:id="1825_7_20_ Lucy Russel_WET_FIX">
<head>CMS to Mrs. William W. Russel</head>
<bibl>
	<date type="creation" when="1825-07-20"/>
	<author>CMS</author>
	<name type="recip">Mrs. William W. Russel</name>
	<name type="transcriber">Deborah Gussman</name>
	<date type="transcription" when=""/>
</bibl>
<div type="docbody">
<opener>
<dateline>						Lenox 20 July - 1825 </dateline>
<salute>My dear Lucy -</salute>
</opener>
<p>	I cannot permit George to return without taking to you the assurance that your recent kindness has been deeply and tenderly felt - My dear Sister was I am sure comforted by it in her extremest need, and felt soothed by the presence of a spirit that could communicate a healing and heavenly influence -</p>
<p>	It is good, as you said, my dear friend to go to the house of mourning in company—to feel—to realise where our common interests centre—and to feel, tho it may be but for a short time, that we have a common property in treasures laid up in heaven—that we have hopes founded on a rock which cannot be moved by any of the casualties of life—by death itself—Oh my dear Lucy—affliction is good. – stern as the truth is—it is necessary—it is emphatically the time <pb n="2"/>to consider—How do the little lights that vanity has kindled and the breath of the word has fanned become dim—our pursuits become vain—our occupations tasteless—and perhaps we are in danger for a time at least of losing all interest in the common affairs of life -.- -- In the adversity of our minds the multitude of our friends disappear from our thoughts, but we cling more closely to those we sincerely love--  </p>
<p>	There is an immense preparation of means in affliction—so much suffering must be meant by a Benevolent Being to produce much good and if it is lost upon us my dear Lucy our guilt must be greatly aggravated—</p>
<p>a severe calamity early in life gains a considerateness to the character that nothing else can— Every discovery that we have made in looking over our beloved Egbert’s papers tends to increase our love for him and the firm and delightful conviction that he was fully prepared for the great change - - In one mem [orandum] to George he says -- “I am not conscious of ever having borne ill will to anyone excepting _____ write to him George, and ask his forgiveness — The person named was not one towards whom he had any personal resentment, but his feeling was caused by knowing that he was in the habit of treating a connection of his ill— Was there not a truly christian</p>
<p>			[scrutiny] in this? - He left a little </p>
<p>			keepsake rolled in a piece of paper</p>
<p>			for a gay young friend of his -- on the </p>
<p>paper was written - “Give _____ this with my love George and beg him to ride no more on Sunday it is God’s day” ----- -- I know it will be gratifying to you and to your husband, who I am sure had a sincere affection for Egbert to know that he left a small proof of his regard for him - He says H he has some champagne in [town]—portion of which he wishes to be given to Mr. Russel– <pb n="3"/> </p>
<p>	I have filled my letter with this melancholy subject in truth I can think of none other—</p>
<p>	 Jane and the children are surprisingly benefitted by the Country—I wish dear Lucy you could make us a visit, and try the invigorating influence of our mountain air—If you are careless about yourself—it is a duty you owe your children to remove them from this dreadful heat </p>
<closer><signed>	My dear friend – remember me aff’ly to your children ^ and husband ^ and believe me always and most sincerely yoursCMS --  </signed>
</closer>
<div type="source"><p>Letter. (are we doing this?)</p>
<p>MHS</p>
<p>SFP Box 80, Folder 21</p>
<p>Condition. (are we doing this?)</p>
</div>
<div type="addr"><p>Mrs. William W. Russel </p>
<p>Franklin Street</p>
<p>New York</p>

</div>
</div>
</div><!-- //document -->
</body>
</text>
</TEI>