<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author>Joseph Zavoral</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2018-06-08</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2018-06-15T14:31:10Z</date><name>Joseph Zavoral</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p style="text-align:center;"><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:12pt">{{DOC}} RBT00094</hi></p><p style="text-align:center;"><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:12pt">{{TRANSCRIBER}} Joseph Zavoral</hi></p><p style="text-align:center;"><hi style="font-size:12pt">{</hi><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:12pt">{TRANSCRIPTION-DATE}} 2014-11-22</hi></p><p style="text-align:center;"><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:12pt">{{EDITOR}} David Ramsey</hi></p><p style="text-align:center;"><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:12pt">1833-01-22</hi></p><p style="text-align:center;"><hi style="font-size:18pt">To [Amos Kendall?]</hi></p><p style="text-align:right;"><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:12pt">{{DATELINE}}</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">Washington, D.C. January 22, 1833</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Confidential</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:12pt">{{SALUTE}}</hi>	<hi style="font-size:12pt">My Dear Sir</hi></p><p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">	This is the first moment since the receipt of your letter that I could take time to write to you a single line. — The administration is most sincerely desirous that the tariff bill reported should pass — I do not speak of every item in the bill nor of all its details — But of the principles on which it is framed which we are anxious to see carried out during the present session. — And if you were as fully aware of the state of the public feeling throughout the country south of the Potomac, you would agree with us in opinion. I have not however time to give you all the reasons and facts, upon which my conclusions </hi> <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:12pt">{{PB}}</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">are founded. But I am sure we are right — and I wish you to examine the matter carefully in all its bearings before you throw any obstacles in the way of the passage of some bill at least framed on the principles on which this has been reported. — The laws will be executed — and the Union will be preserved. — But let us as soon as we can by mutual concession and compromise restore good feeling and harmony to the Union. — We may and shall pass through this crisis — because we have at our head the only man in the country competent to meet it. — But if these local divisions of Northern and Southern interests are to continue and become more and more embittered, the day is not distant when we shall have new difficulties and when there will be no Jackson at the head of affairs to overcome them.</hi>   <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:12pt">{{CLOSE}}</hi>	 <hi style="font-size:12pt">In much haste most truly yrs</hi></p><p style="text-align:right;"><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:12pt">{{SIGNED}}</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">R. B. Taney</hi></p><p rend="footnote text"><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:12pt">{{SOURCE}}</hi>ALS</p><p rend="footnote text">DLC </p><p rend="footnote text">(MMC 2191 Folder 4)</p><p rend="footnote text"><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:12pt">{{NOTE}}</hi>In the absence of an address cover, the identity of the recipient can only be conjectured. The letter is part of a collection of correspondence at the Library of Congress photographed for microfilm in 1983. That collection includes a brief description of the contents, noting that it “Includes correspondence between Taney, Thomas Ellicott, Amos Kendall, and Andrew Jackson relating to the rechartering of the Bank of the United States and a ms. by Taney relating to his part in opposing the renewal.” Taney mentions “local divisions of Northern and Southern interests” in the letter. He seems to allude here to the Nullification Crisis and the Compromise Tariff of 1833, which was enacted less than two months after this letter. If Kendall was the recipient of the letter, it could be that Taney’s plea was for Kendall to provide lenient coverage of the ongoing tariff negotiations in the party newspaper, the <hi rend="italic">Washington Globe</hi>. The letter demonstrates Taney’s role in holding together divergent factions within Jackson’s new Democratic Party. </p></body></text></TEI>